I'm going to talk a little bit about
scaling laws. Originally, I think we
were going to talk about inference, but
I'll I'll take a few minutes to to start
on scaling laws and then we'll kind of
figure out where we'll go from
there. Okay. So, the whole point of
scaling laws is kind of well to begin
with I want you to to put yourself into
the following scenario, right? So you
have a very rich friend um and he or she
has given you 10,000 actually let's say
100,000 H100s for a month um and you
have to build you know the best uh open
source LM that you can right so this is
a a somewhat hard task and we've given
you some of the tools that you need to
make progress on this question um so you
know you can uh put together your your
infra team and your systems people and
you can put together a distributed
training framework um in the next assign
after that you're going to put together
a great pre-training data And then you
kind of know all about you know
architectures and so on. So you kind of
know you have all the pieces and so we
can turn the crank and we can run the
big
model. And in the the first couple
lectures um we talked about you know all
the other various decisions you might
make along this journey right like
what's the architecture what's the
hyperparameters like how are you going
to do all these things well you know I
think the in some ways the answer I gave
you from those early lectures was just
pick what other people have done right
like just follow llama or whatever other
models but in a way that's a very boring
answer because that doesn't let you push
the frontiers right like if you're if
you're in like a big frontier lab and
you're going to build the best model you
don't want to just copy other people,
you want to innovate, right? So, how do
we innovate and get these optimized
solutions in the first place? So, that's
kind of going to be um the point of
scaling laws. What we want to do is we
want to build simple predictive um laws
for the behavior of language models. And
scaling laws are basically this this
whole idea of being able to take small
models, scale them up um and be able to
to do that in order to to improve your
engineering, right? So one way of
thinking about this is the old
unpleasant way of doing deep learning is
just you know train a bunch of big
models tune your hyperparameters so that
your big models are good right um that's
just going to cost tons and tons of
compute like you can't really easily do
that um and so I think the new optimism
um and if you're sort of following a lot
of this these developments on scaling
you know you kind of think of this as
all right we're going to train a bunch
of small models we're going to learn a
lot of things from those small models
and then we're going to extrapolate them
back up two two bigger models, right?
So, we're going to take our smallest
models at, you know, the left side of
this this sort of compute scale here,
and I'm going to learn a lot about what
to do, and then I'm going to nail it in
one go when I build my big
model. Um, and the first place I want to
start with is just kind of the the
history and the background of scaling
laws. Um, and I want to contextualize
this because I think when people talk
about scaling laws, often this is done
in like very
like messaic like AGI terms. They're
like scaling laws just tell you that,
you know, these amazing things are log
linear forever and we will achieve, you
know, super intelligence or something.
Um, but I think scaling laws are
actually much more grounded and have a
lot of interesting history. And so I'm
going to start there to sort of try to
convince you that scaling laws aren't
necessarily just fitting lines on log
plots, although that is a very big part
of what we're going to do. Um, and then
I'm going to do basically very easy
steps. I'm going to try to convince you
that at least for data scaling laws are
very natural thing to think about and
expect. So, so as a person that's kind
of brought up in in statistical machine
learning, you know, my my starting point
is going to be statistical machine
learning, right? Like what is scaling
laws? You know, in some ways scaling
laws are telling us as we increase the
amount of data or we change the model
size, we expect certain behaviors out of
the model, right? And if you go back to
something like machine learning 101 and
if you remember your like VC dimensions
and rotomacher complexities and so on um
in some ways that's the theory version
of exactly this. So, so you know I have
on the top you know uh generalization
bound for how the the generalization
bound for the excess risk of learning
amongst a finite set of k hypotheses and
we see that that should scale as one
over square root of m. Right? In some
ways that's a theoretical version of a
scaling law where we're making
predictions about how fast our error
should decay as a function um of n. on
the bottom we might have something a
little bit more exotic if we're doing
generative modeling and we're our
generative model is a really flexible
nonparametric class um what we might do
instead is we might you know fit some
sort of smooth uh density so in this
case you know uh our prediction is that
the L2 sort of error uh of estimating a
density is going to be upperbounded by
some polomial n to the beta over 2 beta
plus one right this is what some people
might call nonparametric rates so you
know theorists have been thinking for a
very long time about how sample size
especially should relate to error.
Right? This is a very classic problem um
that people have thought about in
machine learning theory. But these are
upper bounds not actual realized loss
values. And really scaling laws are in
some sense the leap from thinking about
kind of the theoretical side of how
should data and model size relate to
performance and going to the empirical
side of saying actually our bounds are
bad but maybe we can actually fit these
things empirically.
And this is a fun trivia fact, you know,
or or arguable trivia fact. Like what is
the first scaling loss paper um and
actually not many papers cite this one,
but I think probably the right first
scaling law papers is um a paper from
1993 Nurips's uh from Bell Labs. Um and
you might recognize some of these names.
These are you know kind of theorists um
and some of the people that have done
really classic work in in machine
learning theory like you know Vapnik and
Karina Cortez and others. And I' I've
taken excerpts because you know I was
reading this paper actually just you
know preparing this this lecture earlier
um and it just struck me how you know
ahead of its time in many ways this
paper was right it's saying you know
training classifiers on large databases
is very computationally demanding and we
need to figure out which ones are good
before actually training them and so
what we're going to do is we're going to
propose a new predictive method that
predicts how good a model is going to be
without actually training the whole
thing right and that look that sounds a
lot like scaling loss Um and you'll see
this later. Um but you know they have a
functional form that's basically like oh
the test error of a model is you know
expressible as some irreducible error
plus a polomially decaying term. And
you're like huh that looks a lot like a
modern scaling law and they even do the
thing where they you know train a bunch
of small models they fit their their
curves and they're like oh we can
accurately predict the behavior of the
model um further out. So, so as with
many things, I guess, you know, scaling
laws partially, you know, thought about
at Bell Labs way back
when. And of course, there's others that
I think, you know, have thought about
related ideas in scaling. Um, not just
scaling knowledge, but also really the
modern mindset I think of of thinking
about scaling. Um, there's another paper
that often gets mentioned in sort of the
history of scaling laws. um Bo Banko and
Bril um who was studying sort of how
does the performance of a certain kind
of NLP system scale with the amount of
data and they have you know what looks
like you know very often a modern
scaling law you know log axis data on
the x-axis performance on the y-axis and
you know they're basically arguing well
look we can get really dramatic
performance improvements just by scaling
up data it's very predictable and you
know maybe we should consider the
trade-off spent between you know
spending time and money on algorithm
development versus just collecting more
data. And you're like, "Huh, that sounds
a lot like what a lot of this
pre-training stuff is thinking
about." And then finally, you know, one
of the things that I think people have
thought about recently and in the past
is, you know, is this thing really
predictable? What are the right
functional forms? Um, and as early as
early as like 2012, you know, people
were really thinking about, all right,
like are these things actually
predictable? you know is power law like
for example power 3 and pow 4 are those
really the right functional forms for
predicting the behavior of models and of
course all of this you know just to
remind you right is thinking about the
behavior of models on the y- axis the
capabilities as a function of the amount
of data that you have on the x-axis here
right so that's the relationship that I
think has been really classically
studied what you might call data scaling
um in all these
cases and if you're interested in like
kind of the the earliest like largecale
old neural scaling law paper that would
probably be hes at all in 2017. Um I
believe they were at by due when they
did this work. Um they showed that for
uh a range of tasks uh machine
translation
um speech and I think like some vision
tasks um they showed that essentially
error rates fall as a power law um and
they even have this nice plot that I
really like to to refer to when when
people are discussing scaling loss that
really your expectation should be that
there's three different regions in the
behavior of a model right initially you
start out at best guess you then enter
into a region where you're kind of
predictably scaling the model that's the
power law region region and then there's
another asmtoic region where you're
approaching essentially the irreducible
error of your model class. Um and I'll
kind of highlight that I think you know
there's been in the last few years a lot
of talk of new phenomena things like oh
emerging capabilities or like scaling
compute being a new thing or uh systems
being really important. Um but had you
been reading sort of Hessnus in 2018
carefully you would have seen
essentially all of these things you know
um they say actually you know it's
really hard to do predictions by scaling
law when models are are at random
performance because suddenly you can
leave the random region. Um they talk
about computational limits actually you
know if we can scale it means actually
scaling by compute is really important.
And then finally they even say things
like you know maybe we should do things
like quantization because if we have
predictable scaling then that means we
should be willing to pay for model
accuracy with compute right these are
all very very modern ideas that I think
a lot of the early scaling law papers I
think kind of understood fairly
intuitively because you know once you
see these plots you kind of see that
actually with predictable resource
investment you get predictable
capabilities improvements right so that
that's in some sense um sort of the core
not quite history but I context um that
has really shaped uh scaling loss. All
right, any questions so far on kind of
the context? This is mainly just kind of
data scaling, but I wanted to make sure
we we go over it carefully.
Yes,
like it's pretty natural for like
scaling. I was wondering like like is
there cases where there isn't scaling
where
Yeah. Yeah. So the question was um you
know it's natural or or maybe it maybe
arguably natural to expect scaling. Are
there cases where we don't get scaling
or we get different kinds of scaling um
and I think one way of thinking about
this is if you're measuring kind of
training loss or like you know held out
versions of training loss then I think
scaling is very natural right like all
of classical statistical theory says you
know things should converge and when
they converge eventually they will get
better right at some sort of very
asmtoic sense. Um but we do see
non-scaling behavior. Um there was a
really interesting competition a few
years back um called like the inverse
scaling prize where they were looking
for things that like scale inversely as
models got better. Um and a lot of these
are are very niche things like you know
models tend to copy better and so if you
want to like suppress copying behavior
becomes really hard for really strong
models for example. Um, but I think one
sort of like thing that ties a lot of
that together is, you know, if you go
really far out of distribution where the
behavior is not well specified by the
data, then you can get all sorts of
behaviors like no scaling at all or
inverse scaling or what have you, right?
So in some sense you can think of this
as like the extension of the classic
like deep learning robustness
problems. Cool. Okay. So now I'm going
to talk about um the scaling behaviors
of LLM like just essentially going
through several kinds of empirical
results. I'm going to walk you through
um data scaling in particular and some
examples just to convince you that this
is a very natural object to expect and
then we'll talk about model size which
is a a you know different kind of a
thing.
Um so um scaling laws I think are fairly
well established and they seem to appear
very very often in kind of many
variables right you see scaling in
compute um on the x-axis these are all
taken from um Kaplan's scaling law paper
which I'll refer to extensively in this
lecture so the x-axis here is is log
compute y-axis here is log test loss um
and on the right you see similar kinds
of scaling both for data set size so
this is the amount of data uh in
parameters. One subtlety I'll mention
here as I as I sort of talk through this
is you know when we scale things like
data set size or parameters we're always
assuming that the other variable in this
case if you're scaling data set size the
model size is much much much bigger than
you can saturate with the data set size
right because obviously if you have way
more data than you know parameters
eventually you're going to sort of
asmtote out right so in all of these
we're trying to avoid the asmtoic regime
um they hold in also pretty non-standard
settings they'll hold for for downstream
tasks they'll hold out of distribution
which is what's being shown here from
the Kaplan paper. Um, and so, you know,
in some ways power law relationships
seem to appear more often than we might
initially expect, especially for these
OOD or other
variables. So, I want to talk through
data scaling laws first because I think
they're the most intuitive. Like, at the
very least, I think the theory for that
is fairly clear. Um, and so to be
precise, when I say something like data
scaling, what I mean is just some sort
of simple formula that maps data set
size, which I'm going to refer to as n,
to um, our excess error, right? Excess
error is the error beyond the
irreducible regime. And you know, if you
recall um, that figure I referred to in
Hess, um, what we are going to expect is
monotonic logistic looking curves. And
really our interest is primarily going
to be in the power law region to the
irreducible error region. Like of course
it's very interesting to also ask
questions about what happens in the
small data regions as we leave random
guessing. Um but that's much much harder
to reason about. Whereas I think this
right tail actually I can hopefully
convince you that this part is actually
a very very natural thing to expect
power loss scaling.
So okay right so the first empirical
observation that we have right and this
is kind of the thing that I'm going to
convince you is natural is when we plot
on the x-axis data set size and on the
y-axis test loss then on the log plot
model performance is linear right um you
might call this scale free or you might
call it power law these are more sort of
physics um physics uh oriented
terminology um and sort of this was
established you know by by many people
um but you might refer to to Kaplan to
see many examples of this. So I think
you know as sort of the previous
question sort of brought up right we
kind of expect error to be monotone we
train on more data error goes down
fairly obvious the part that is less
obvious is the precise functional form
of this scaling right so when I say it's
a power law it's it's linear in log log
space um and then so what is the
implication of that right if something
is linear in log log that means that
there's a polinomial relationship
between your x-axis and your y-axis
right um and why Is polinomial decay
natural? Well, I'm going to walk you
through two examples and both of those
are going to result in some fairly
natural polinomial decay. I'm going to
start with the simplest possible
example, right? Like this is just going
to be, you know, even stats 101 rather
than, you know, machine learning 101.
So, what I want to do is I want to
estimate the mean of a data set, right?
And estimating the mean is a task of
estimating a parameter, right? I can ask
for what's the scaling law. What's the
error of my mean estimation task as a
function of data, right? So I can write
that down. Well, you know, my input
comes from a gausian and the task is to
estimate the average. I've written those
out in the blue box above. And what's
the error? Well, by sort of very
standard arguments, right, the average
is going to be also distributed as a
gausian with the standard deviation
divided by n. So I'm going to get, you
know, sigma squared over n is my
estimation error, right? This is the
expected squared error of my estimate.
And if you look at this, this is
polinomial in n. And just to really
drive the point home, you know, you take
the log of both sides of this. Log of
the error on the left and log of sort of
um of uh n on the right hand side. You
know, I get exactly log of error is
equal to negative log n plus 2 log
sigma. Right? Um so this is exactly the
kind of thing we expect and we expect a
slope of one if we were to fit a scaling
law for mean estimation.
So now you know equipped with this this
new knowledge you might say all right
I'm going to go around and I'm going to
look at what the rates are for
estimating different things and that
will tell me about what I should expect
for data scaling and so you might say oh
what I expect is one overn you might
expect one over square root of n for
agnostic learning um and so on and so
forth so we should expect to see some
like pretty nice round numbers on the
slope here right of a log plot I should
expect to see like one or five um what
do we actually find empirically when we
look across these papers right um just
to sort of call them out in hessness for
machine translation we see 0.13 for
speech we see 0.3 and for language
modeling um we see an exponent
of095 right those are all much much
slower than the 1 overn or one over
square root of n rates that you might
expect when you're just fitting simple
functions so why might this be okay This
will be the last math slide of this this
lecture and then we can go to just
fitting lines on log lock log plots the
rest of the time. But um this will
hopefully drive the point home of why we
might see these particular slopes. So we
know that neural nets aren't just
estimating the mean, right? Or it's not
even fitting a linear regression, right?
They can fit arbitrary functions, right?
So let's turn that into an example and
let's work through that example. So um
my input is um x1 through xn. I have n
samples and I'm going to put them
uniformly in the 2D unit box. um and I
want to estimate some random not random
some arbitrary regression function y
equals f right and I'll assume f is
smooth and so on um if you really want
to be precise right there's some
regularity conditions here um a simple
approach to to estimating a regression
function f is just to cut the 2D space
up into small boxes and within each box
I can measure the average of the y
values right like a very simple
nonparametric regressor is to just cut
the space up and then to estimate what's
going to happen now informally If we
pick, you know, I'm going to have square
root m boxes. Now, each box is going to
get square root of n samples. And now my
error is going to be 1 over of n.
And if you sort of follow this logic
through the more dimensions, you'll see
that in dimensions, this is going to be
error is equal to n^ 1 /d. And then sort
of my overall scaling if I were to take
log log plots of the whole thing is I
expect the slope of negative 1 /d,
right? Um, and so why did I walk you
through this example, right? I walked
you through this example because if you
have flexible function classes, what
people call nonparametric function
classes, you expect dimension dependence
and therefore the slope of the uh
scaling law to actually move sort of
much more slowly. And in some sense, the
slope is telling you almost precisely um
kind of the intrinsic dimensionality or
the ease of learning this task. Um and
people have argued this more formally or
or sort of more literally. Um there's
been several sort of theory/impirical
papers arguing that really the reason
why we get these sort of exotic or
non-standard rates of learning is that
it is closely connected to the the
intrinsic dimensionality of the data. Um
and the sort of for example the plots of
these predictions the dash lines and
these these purple circles um are
somewhat close although um you know you
don't want to read too much into this
because estimation of intrinsic
dimension is is an extremely difficult
problem and as difficult as modeling uh
the data uh overall. Okay. Oh yes. Yeah.
I mean I guess this is related to the
point you made at the end. It's much
more but like yeah how do you how do you
generate data that has an underlying
intrinsic dimension at all from a
simulation perspective? Yeah. So so uh
the results here well if you want for
example to generate data that's actually
not too hard. you could like write down
a function that takes in like five
variables, right? And then that would be
a as long as all five of those variables
like don't, you know, cancel each other.
That's a fivedimensional surface and you
can add a little bit of noise and you're
good to go. Um the difficulty here is
that they're actually doing things like,
you know, training on CFR and then
they're having, you know, different uh
they're trying to estimate the intrinsic
dimensionality of CRA. That's a, you
know, much harder
task. Okay. Um and data scaling laws are
quite useful. Um you know I was going at
this from a let me explain to you
scaling laws perspective but you can
actually use scaling laws to do many
interesting things right you can make
engineering decisions of various kinds
using data scaling laws and people do um
in fact do this. Um for example you know
you might say well how does data set
composition affect performance not just
data set size. Well, um, if you're
changing the test set, you know, uh,
Kaplan at all has a really nice figure
showing actually data composition only
affects the offset, not the slope. And
what that would mean is it says if you
want to pick a really good, uh, data
set, you don't have to necessarily train
your models at a huge scale. You can
scale them down and do your data
selection experiments on much smaller
models. um and the shape of the expected
uh sort of as we mix sort of different
data, we might expect certain kinds of
sort of shapes and you can use
regression and other kinds of techniques
to try to figure out for example optimal
data mixing using scaling laws and
people have written several papers um on
this topic. Although you know as with
all data selection sort of uh research,
a lot of this seems fairly tricky to
execute reliably.
There's other also interesting questions
that you might ask right there's a lot
of discussion these days about you know
are we running out of data right on the
internet and so once you start asking
those questions the other interesting
and important question is well can we
just keep training on the same data we
have what's the diminishing returns
property of that right and so um there's
interesting work extending scaling laws
to multi-epo training um basically
arguing that there's an sort of
effective sample size and after about
four epochs you know you have rapid ly
diminishing returns as you repeat more
and more data. And by modifying sort of
um the usual scaling law, you can
basically get a version where you have
amount of effective data and unique
tokens that sort of diminish out as you
increase the amount of
repetition. Finally, I think one
interesting sort of combination of these
two ideas is if you're thinking about
sort of data selection in the large data
regime, right? Like imagine you're going
to be training on trillions and
trillions of tokens right now. What
would be better? Would it be better to
repeat highquality sources like you know
Wikipedia and perhaps your secret
pirated books 10 times or would it be
better to include new data right um the
fact that you can either repeat data or
you can include more data right now has
multiple sort of axes on which you can
sort of optimize your data mixture. Um
and there's also been some interesting
data scaling work. um this one from CMU
folks um on essentially trading off
between repeating data versus picking
lower quality data that's new, right?
And so all of this really is a is a
really natural extension of what I sort
of already taught you, which is if you
assume that there's a predictive power
law relationship, right? and that this
power law relationship holds sort of on
a per mixture basis, then you can fit
these sort of scaling law extrapolations
and then get an estimate of how good
your data is going to be at scale.
Right? So that's the starting point um
which is data scaling. Right? And
hopefully I've convinced you at this
point both sort of empirically and
conceptually that it's natural to have
you know log log linear relationships
between data and error. Um this
relationship seems to hold very robustly
across domains across different kinds of
models. Um and you can kind of have a
nice clean theoretical understanding um
of what is happening here. Um and once
you do this you can use this for all
sorts of purposes like picking optimal
data mixtures um or whatever else. Okay.
Yes. How was the model size picked on
the data scaling box? Yeah. So um as I
was kind of saying back
in well not this slide but let's see
back in this slide um when we think
about kind of the data size scaling the
the model is always picked to be really
really large. So the data is not
saturating your model right um and you
want to kind of avoid being in this
irreducible error regime. So the model
is always picked to be large enough that
you're in the power law region whenever
you're only varying data. So is it just
one model size for like all of them that
one really really big model size or like
is each point like a different size
model? Yeah. For for for example for
this plot in particular it's for it's
like one big model size. Okay. When
you're looking at for example compute
scaling on this axis then data and model
scale jointly at some like you know
pre-ordained
ratio. Cool. Any other
questions? Good. Okay.
Excellent.
Um, all
right. So, now I think we get to move
from data scaling to, in my opinion,
slightly more mysterious kinds of
scaling. Um, and we're going to talk
about model scaling next. Um, and I
think this is a more practical
engineering set of questions that we're
now going to try to answer. So you're in
charge of you know building and shipping
a really large language model and
there's a lot of interesting ideas out
there right like you could train the
latest you know state space model you
could train a transformer you could use
atom you could use SGD right people
invent all sorts of new tricks which
ones are worth scaling up and which ones
are not um you could also take you know
uh your limited compute resources and
spend them on different things you can
train models for longer or you could
train bigger models right for given flop
you can trade between these do um and
you could also do things like go and
collect more data versus get more GPS.
There's a lot of different sort of
things that you can do and the scaling
laws allow you to have a pretty simple
procedure to just answer all these
questions, right? So, I'll go through um
the classic uh sort of Kaplan scaling
law paper. If you're interested in these
topics, I encourage you to read it. It's
just kind of a gold mine um of all these
kinds of observations. Some of it is
old, but it's um I think still unmatched
in the thoroughess of all the things
that it really studied um in a fairly
nice unified setting. So, architecture-
wise um you might start by asking like
transformers versus LSTMs, right? Which
one's better? Well, you know, the brute
force way might be to, you know, scale
up LSTMs and up to like GPT3 level and
then, you know, you can figure out
whether it's good or not. Um the scaling
law way is much simpler, right? You
basically train a bunch of LSTMs and
transformers across many different
compute thresholds or compute levels and
then you kind of see what happens as you
scale them up. And I think the trends
here are fairly clear, right? Like no
matter how many layers you have on your
LSTMs, there's a pretty big gap, right?
Pretty big constant factor gap between
transformers and LSTMs, right? And
remember this is in log scale. So this
is kind of saying something like, you
know, I don't know what the exact
numbers are, but imagine this is like 15
times less efficient, right? that no
matter where you are on this plot, you
know, the LSTM is, let's say, 15 times
less compute efficient than a
transformer, right? So that there's a
constant factor compute penalty to using
um LSTMs um at least in this plot. You
know, you could you could zoom out and
say, well, there's a lot more
architectures, you know, which ones are,
you know, really good and worth doing.
um and sort of some of the classic
papers. This one is by uh ET and others
uh at Google um have done exactly this
kind of scaling work where they took a
bunch of architectures on the right here
um and they basically scaled them up. So
the x-axis is the amount of compute. The
red line is basically each architecture
and the green line is the transformer
baseline, right? And they ask like oh
can any of these alternative
architectures match or out you know
outscale uh the transformer, right? Um
and what what do they uh end up? Well,
actually the only thing that seems to
like really strongly and reliably beat
the transformer is you know gated linear
units um and mixture of experts. And
once you know it, that's exactly the
kind of stuff that people are doing
today, right? And so this is kind of the
scaling law version of that same idea of
saying like how would you have come to
the conclusion that we should be doing
switch transformers and GLU and and for
example not the performer, right? Okay.
And the scaling law provides some some
clear evidence of why you might want to
do
that. Optimizer choice I think follows a
similar thing. Um this one's from
Hessnus. Um you know they compare SGD
and Atom. They find very similar to
before this kind of constant factor gap
right in compute. um in this case data
set size but of course that translates
to compute um in in the effectiveness of
atom versus SGD right um you know RHN in
this in this case is recurrent highway
nets you can sort of ignore the details
here um you kind of see the the point of
how you would do this analysis rather
than the specific results um that are
shown
here you know in the beginning I also
said something like oh you know depth
versus width like what what should the
aspect ratios be that was one of the
hyperparameter topics we talked out um
and we see sort of similar sort of
analysis but in scaling law form from
Kaplan. I think this one's intriguing to
me at least because you know we might
think that deeper layers get
dramatically better right that there's
like clear separation between the number
of layers but we see at least here that
you know there's actually a lot of sort
of slop one layer is really bad but a
lot of the other sort of layer choices
sort of remain pretty stable. Um and
hopefully this is reminiscent of kind of
that slide I showed back in the
architecture lecture where I said well
you know the aspect ratio the ratio of
width to depth you know roughly um
something like 4 to 16 or something was
a pretty natural number but there's a
really wide basin in which you're
approximately optimal and the scaling
law analysis also backs that up. One
important subtlety um that I do want to
point out um and this one bites people
every now and then is that not all
parameters are equal. like often you
want to do you know parameter scaling
analyses. Um but if you were to say
count embedding parameters as part of
your model well you get like a pretty
different scaling law. You get this you
know kind of weird looking thing that
like slightly bends over here. Um
whereas if you only consider the
non-mbedding parameter you see that much
cleaner result that I showed you before.
Right? So embedding layer parameters
don't really behave the same and they
don't show the same kinds of um sort of
log linear scaling um as the
non-mbbedding parameters uh when you
account for them. Um and there's sort of
related work on saying like not all
parameters are the same um on recent
papers on scaling uh mixtures of experts
where they're also sort of trying to
figure out like what does it mean to be
a parameter when you have such sparsely
activated parameters and in those kinds
of papers they sort of try to derive
essentially things like equivalent
number of dense parameters in order to
sort of try to normalize um the the
number of parameters ine right
um I've showed you this plot um earlier
in the hyperparameter selection, but
hopefully now actually you see the full
context, not just the original sort of
the hyperparameter choice question. Um,
we know that in many cases, um, I'll go
back, let's say, uh, to like here. Often
what we'll see is scaling lock curves
that look like the following. You'll
often see that the slope of the curves
remain very similar. They're
non-crossing and that there's sort of
constant factor offsets between these
curves. And whenever this is true, what
you can then do is you can take a slice
at a particular level of compute or a
particular set of hyperparameters and
analyze the hyperparameter trade-offs
very carefully assuming or and sort of
be sort of safe in sort of scaling that
up. And so when you go to Kaplan's
paper, you'll see exactly these kinds of
analyses being done. Um especially I
think that the center one, the aspect
ratio plot is definitely worth looking
at. you know, they're not just sort of
scaling up and down models. They're
actually taking different slices. So,
different sized models, 50 million, 270
million, 1.5 billion, and they're
looking at how the aspect ratio changes
the loss. And they kind of see that, oh,
actually the shape of the curve, not
just the scaling slopes actually remain
similar. And this means that, you know,
I can pick an aspect ratio between 10 to
100 and any anything in between will
work fine at all of these different
scales, right? And so this is um I think
important to think about. I think
initially when you're trained in sort of
deep learning, you know, model training,
you think about hyperparameter tuning,
but you want to be sort of scale aware
in how you're tuning your
hyperparameters. And that's a really big
difference in mindset, I think, um
between kind of the scaling law style
approach and sort of maybe what you've
been trained or what you've you know
naturally think about in terms of oh
let's just tune these models at a small
scale, right? And so um the same is
being done kind of for feed forward
dimen uh ratio and for attention head
dimension. You know you're varying v
various aspects of scale and you're
trying to see whether sort of the minima
uh remain
similar. Okay. Um another important
thing um next actually maybe not next
lecture but next next lecture I'm going
to talk about um sort of practical case
studies almost of how people have scaled
up models. Um, and we'll actually see
that batch size and learning rate are
actually two really tricky things that
you have to deal with carefully when you
scale models up, right? So, when you
scale models up, you're going to have to
maybe think about, you know, the the
optimal learning rate will be different
across model scales. And if you're doing
that, then actually also maybe the
optimal batch size might end up varying
as well, right? Because those two are
often co- um, and so we need to think
about what the right way of scaling
batch size is and how batch size
interacts with scale and also learning
rates. I'll talk about those um for the
next couple slides. Right? So batch
slides from the systems lecture
hopefully you remember it has
diminishing returns past a certain
point. So up until a certain point so
you know when the batch size is uh
smaller than the noise scale we're on
the left hand sides here right
increasing batch size is almost
equivalent to taking more gradient
steps. So so that's you know roughly
saying if I double my batch size it's as
good as taking two gradient steps. And
that's a really really good place to be,
right? Because now you've got the
systems power of being able to
parallelize across the batch, right?
While having the optimization efficiency
of taking two steps. But past a certain
point, you're going to have ineffective
scaling, right? Where now your sort of
noise scale and your batch size are the
same and the additional uh samples in
your batch that you're taking, you know,
they're not reducing useful noise. it's
getting dominated by kind of the
curvature of um the bias term so to
speak of the curvature of your um
optimization landscape. And one really
useful thing to to think about useful
sort of analysis object um is this
notion of a critical batch size. And the
critical batch size you can think of as
is kind of this threshold point where we
go from perfect scaling to uh dip strong
diminishing returns, right? Um and you
can sort of analyze this in theory and
the in sort of open AI papers on
critical batch sizes do this but you
could also analyze this uh empirically
and this is another thing that's been
studied sort of you know in the scaling
law kind of of way. Um you can kind of
see um you can estimate the point at
which sort of uh progress slow. So you
can estimate empirically what the
critical batch size point trade-off
points are. And you can also basically
train bigger and better models. And one
really interesting thing is as you try
to you know improve the loss so you
you're going left side here. So you're
making losses better and better and
better and better and better. Um your
critical batch size um ends up getting
smaller, right? So the the smaller the
loss target, the bigger uh the overall
batch size um that you can be. Um and so
one of the things that this leads to is
for example if you look at the llama 3
um training report you'll actually see
for example that they'll like increase
the batch size after a certain point or
they'll do things like increase the
batch size um as they train because as
your loss target gets smaller um your
batch sizes um can in turn get
bigger. So um as we increase both
compute and model size like what's the
right thing to do once again we can do
kind of a scaling analysis this is from
Kaplan um and you can try to figure out
you know as we increase the amount of
compute what is um the optimal batch
size and what we kind of see is that you
know um as we increase the amount of
compute um we can actually have
reasonable sort of parallelism. The
number of total steps can stay the same
um at at least within this compute
threshold. the number of total steps can
stay the same um while sort of get
getting the batches bigger and bigger
and bigger and if you fix the amount of
batches of course the number of steps is
going to go up and up and up. So this is
good news hopefully for for data
parallel
processing. So that's the batch size
story. Um the thing you can you should
maybe remember um because I think
critical batch sizes are kind of a messy
concept is that a there's a a sort of
diminishing returns point the critical
batch size that's one thing. The second
one is that it does seem to follow a
pretty predictable scaling often as a
function of your target loss. Um and
given that you can figure out you know
what is the right tradeoffs that I can
make um in terms of systems efficiency
and my optimization
progress as I said before um the other
aspect of this right is you know you've
got your batch size and then you've got
your learning rate and those two are
fairly closely linked with each other.
Um, and I'm going to talk about MUP at
much more extensive length um, in the
next part of the scaling lecture. Um,
but this is kind of a really important I
think broader idea. So you could do one
of two things. And I think this figure
will allow me to talk about both of
these. So let's look at this left plot
first. Um, what's what's labeled
standard practice, right? So when you
train a transformer, right? What you're
basically going to see is something like
this left thing here, this standard
practice. Um so the optimal learning
rate is going to be at different points
and the wider the model right as you
increase your model size and your your
MLPS get wider and wider and wider the
optimal learning rate is going to be
pretty small and as you make your your
model smaller and smaller and smaller
right your losses of course are going to
go up because your model is less you
know less expressive but also the
optimum learning rate is going to also
go up right um and often you know people
say there's a rule of thumb it's like
one over the width is the right rate at
which you could scale the learning rate.
Um more advanced people will actually
fit uh uh basically take these curves,
find the minimum and then fit a scaling
law on the optimum learning rate. And so
there we can see that this is a
predictable decay in learning rate and
maybe we can fit a scaling law. I'll
talk about this more in the next set of
lectures. But an alternative one that I
think many people have started to adopt
and I think is a is a really interesting
thing to think about is that you can
actually reparameterize the model. Um
and in particular, you know, you can do
things like scale the initializa or
scale the learning rates um of different
layers based on the width. You can uh
scale the variance of the initialization
based on based on the width of the
model. Um as well as multiply the output
in the forward paths of of different
layers of the model. Um and if you do
this in a way that you know is dependent
on sort of the width of the model um you
end up with a parameterization of the
model whose learning rate is supposed to
be more stable or at least you know in
the original paper exactly stable across
scale. Right? So you tune your learning
rate once and you don't have to do
anything else. That optimum directly
transfer it's actually you tune it here
on the smallest one and that directly
transfers to the very largest scale.
Right? And this is the the idea called
new P. Um there have been sort of this
original paper that I'm showing you is
called with new P. There's been other
variants. Um Meta with the release of
Llama 4 claims to have invented
something called metap, which I'm not
quite sure what it is yet. Um but you
can sort of see that a lot of labs are
kind of thinking about this, right?
Because if you're going to have to, you
know, rely on predicting what the
optimum learning rate is, then you have
to do all sorts of tricky scaling law
fits and maybe this is very unstable.
But if you can reparameterize your model
then well maybe you don't have to do any
sort of retuning at all. Of course
that's you know way more optimistic than
what happens in practice but hopefully
this gives you a sense of of you know
why this is really cool and really
interesting right scale aware
initializations. Cool. Any questions up
until this point? I feel like I've sort
of gone through a whole bunch of uh
scaling architecture and parameter
stuff. So maybe I'll stop for a moment
here um in case anyone has any
questions.
Yeah, I didn't really get the intuition
behind like if we want a lower loss
target, we want to increase the match
size. I didn't really understand that.
Yeah. Like so when you have a lower loss
target.
Yeah. So, um what you want to do, right,
is the smaller the loss target, the kind
of more sensitive things are. And in the
same way that like you're going to be
lowering your learning rate, right, you
want to also increase your batch size in
order to d noiseise, right? Like the
more sensitive the target that you have,
the sort of more precise your gradients
potentially have to be. Um, one way of
thinking about it is like, you know, as
you're cooling down and your learning
rate is going up, um, maybe your batch
size should increase as well because the
learning rate and batch sizes sort of
affect each other inversely.
Yeah. this backside thing is only true
for NLP not for or for computer vision.
I'm not uh I'm not sure. There is a sort
of related OpenAI scaling paper for sort
of multimodal models but I'm not I don't
remember what that says about critical
batch size for those.
Yeah. Yes.
The noise scale. Yeah. the noise scale
at least in sort of this figure if
that's what you're asking about this is
a kind of theoretical analysis. It's
basically about the gradient noise that
you expect from random sampling within
the batch. Um so this is not like a you
know precisely empirically measured
quantity. It'll be
simple.
Okay. All right. So one thing I'll
caution and I think this is a big
caution for a lot of scaling law works
is that scaling laws are very nicely
behaved for log losses right so we train
on you know uh next token prediction
cross entropies when your scaling law
targets are those cross entropies very
easy works very well um but if you're
trying to do downstream tasks right
you're trying to like directly scale on
benchmarks behavior is much less
predictable um so here on the left side.
This is from um YK's paper uh comparing
lots of different sort of like
hyperparameters and architectures. Um
you see that the number of parameters
which in this case is a surrogate for
compute and the negative log perplexity
is you know very nicely linearly
correlated and what this is basically
saying is well it doesn't matter what
your like depth or width or like precise
setting of the hyperparameters are the
only thing that really matters is your
total compute expenditure right this is
a very simple and nice story but then
you take these models um this was back
in 2023 so you know people were still
kind of doing super glue accuracy um And
you know, you basically say like, okay,
but what's the downstream performance of
these models? And while now we don't see
a very nice linear relationship anymore,
right? We see this like totally
different thing where certain models are
much better than others and certain
architectures are are better than
others. Um, and so you might not expect
exactly this kind of scaling property.
And we've seen variants of this story uh
play out in many different places. Um,
if you followed the literature on state
space models, um, that's one thing that
we've seen. um you know in state space
models you know we see really nice
predictable scaling like the ones on the
left but often um for certain
capabilities like in context learning or
for for QA um people have shown that you
know these models maybe do less well so
it's important to not take this like
perplexity scaling as the same thing as
downstream scaling and you want to be a
little bit cautious whenever you're
doing these kinds of
analyses. Okay. So, um maybe this is not
surprising to some of you, but hopefully
you know this is surprising and
convincing. Um which is that you know if
we want to make lots of engineering
decisions like hyperparameter choices,
architecture decisions, um we can do a
lot of that before training, right? Like
we can train these models at small scale
across several orders of magnitude
compute and then use scale that up in
order to try to predict the behavior of
of models, right? So the scaling law
based design procedure is pretty simple.
You train a few smaller models and these
smaller models should span a couple
orders of magnitude compute. You
establish a scaling law of some kind. So
you you know see that at least on the
models that you trained that there's a
clear log log linear relationship and
then based on this prediction you can
set optimal hyper parameters. Um in many
cases in fact you know these scaling
laws won't really vary too much. Their
slopes will actually be the same. in
which case sort of the correlary to this
is you can just train a few smaller
models and you know the results of those
small models will transfer surprisingly
well to the larger models in many of
these cases but not all of them um
learning rate being an important
exception for
example okay so that's how you do things
like hyperparameter selection and
architecture selection um now I want to
talk about one very important use of
scaling laws one that's had kind of an
outsized influence on you know how we
pick sizes of models how we think about
um data efficiency and so on of these
models. So I think um back in the
earlier days when people were beginning
to scale up these models there's a
really core question that you need to
ask right do we need more data or do we
need bigger models in some sense um you
know back in 2021 to 2023 or something
um you know data was way more abundant
than compute right so we didn't need to
worry about um you know the total data
limitations and so the one limiting
resource is compute right your total
number of flops for your training budget
that's kind of the limiting resource and
you can then spend that resource in many
different ways. You can spend it on
training on lots of data with a small
model or you can train one giant model
on very little data, right? And both of
those extremes seem very wasteful,
right? Like if you have a teenytiny
model, pumping in tons and tons of data
doesn't seem useful. And reverse um if
you have a giant model with like 10
tokens also doesn't seem very useful.
And so this was sort of a core question
for for many people. Um and so there you
know simultaneously several authors sort
of proposed um sort of joint data model
scaling laws to try to answer this
question. And so what are those? Right?
I have been talking about scaling laws
um in essentially one variable
exclusively up until this point. And
that one variable has varied. It has
sometimes been parameters or data or
compute. Um but we've not looked at
joint scaling, right? Um and so data
model scaling laws are things that look
like this. These two sort of um
equations here are both like
functionally equivalent um to first
order um and describe the trade-off
between the amount of data and the
amount of models. So the top one from
Rosenfeld you know is basically saying
there's a part of the error one part of
it that decays polinomially in data
there's a part of the error that decays
polinomially in the model size and then
there's an irreducible error term that
cannot be removed even if I scale both
the data size and the model to infinity
right same effect with Kaplan um but
here they're sort of thinking about
irreducible error rather than uh
reducible error and so there's no
constant term here um so this seems kind
of arbitrary
um because I don't think there's any
sort of you know uh top down reason why
this has to be the correct functional
form but this provides surprisingly good
fits to the joint error that you see in
data and model. So this is from um I
believe Rosenfeld. They show this nice
3D plot of this is the amount of data.
This is um the amount this is the size
of the model and this is the loss on the
y-axis. And the surface that's being fit
is their functional form. The dots are
their runs. Um it might be a little hard
to see from the back, but the surface
fits the dots almost exactly.
Um, and despite the fact that this
functional form is kind of ad hoc, like
it's pulled out of a hat, um, it is
surprisingly accurate. Um, this one's
from from Rosenfeld as well. Um, where
they basically say, okay, I'm only going
to train, um, on essentially the small
half, right? Models that are small and
data that is small, right? So on this
sort of left bottom, and I'm going to
extrapolate to models that are sort of
both large and trained with more models.
And how good is that fit of like joint
extrapolation? Well, quite good, right?
So, if you look at the error, my my um
uh my sort of uh real values are on the
x-axis. My predictions of the error on
the y- axis, and they're sort of almost
exactly right both on like sort of
imageet and on wiki text. So, this seems
pretty good. Um and so, you know, for a
fixed compute budget, now what can we
do? we go back to so for example Kappla
and we see similar things being done
here we see sort of joint scaling of
compute and data. So in this case
parameters are on the x-axis the colors
represent compute and so there's sort of
a third axis of data that's being
implicitly varied in order to vary the
total amount of comput. So as you go uh
shift in uh on these curves um the
parameters are being varied um while the
compute is being held constant and so
the amount of data is going to
vary. So chinchilla I think many of you
have hopefully heard of um is probably
the reference in solving this problem
right. So both Rosenfeld and Kaplan came
up with kind of this joint scaling
functional form and then you know both
of them sort of noticed that it was
possible to use these functional forms
to optimize the trade-off between
compute and data in various ways. Um but
for various reasons it's you know
basically it's hard to fit these sort of
functional forms precisely and the
details like the the sort of learning
rate shapes um being different um are
important and so Kaplan sort of had one
estimate that was quite far off from
what was later in some sense validated
to be optimal. And so the Chinchilla
paper um by a bunch of Google authors
sort of was an attempt to really
empirically try to nail down what is the
right trade-off um between the amount of
tokens and the model size assuming that
your goal is to get the best model for
the smallest amount of training flops.
Right? So they have three different
approaches. Approach one, two, and three
um for basically fitting different
curves and making scaling predictions.
These blue dots are the models that they
trained. Um and the basically the lines
are predicting different optimal
parameter sizes for different flops. And
hopefully most of you kind of know the
chinchilla ratio. That's something like
you know 20 tokens per parameter. And
that comes from exactly this, right?
Like if you take each of these points
and you multiply it by 20, you're going
to get roughly the flop or sorry
multiply it by 20 you'll get the token
count. And so if you multiply the
parameters by that you'll get the flops.
Um the difference between sort of the
the Kaplan uh results which were uh
basically estimating one set of token to
parameter ratios um and sort of the
chinchilla ones. One of the reasons um
is because of learning rate schedules,
right? We know that we train models with
cosine learning rates, right? So cosine
learning rates are going to look
something like this, right? It goes up
and then it comes back down and then
it's going to cool down all the way to a
minimum learning rate at your bottom.
But um you can't one thing about cosine
learning rates that sort of trips
everyone up all the time is you can't
truncate them early right for a cosine
learning rate you have to sort of go all
the way to the end in order to get a
valid model right you have to get a cool
down phase all the way to the end if I
truncate a model in the middle this is
not the same as starting a model from
scratch and training it with a cosine
learning rate somewhere in the middle um
and this was one of the sort of
contributing factors there were others
as well um leading to the Kaplon
estimates um being pretty far off from
the the later sort of more improved
estimates provided uh by the chinchilla
paper. So what do the chinchilla authors
actually do? Well, they have three
different methods of trying to estimate
the optimum uh tradeoff between tokens
to models. And each of these methods are
going to sort of provide different
scaling coefficients, right? Scaling
coefficients for the model size and
scaling coefficients for the data size.
Um, and kind of surprisingly in this
case, they're getting 0.5 on both of
these for methods one and two. And
method 3 is providing pretty different
or slightly different estimates. They're
about off by 0.03. Um, but we'll talk
about that a little bit later. Kaplan at
all, you see, is way off um than any of
the three estimates, right? So, we'll go
over each of these methods. Each of
these makes sense. they make sort of
different assumptions about scaling um
but they end up with very very similar
estimates um at the very end
here. So method one on chinchilla is to
basically take the minimum over curves
um and so what does that mean? Well you
basically overlay all of the different
training curves that you have. So you
can see here um on the x-axis is
different flops on the y-axis is sort of
the the training loss and I have models
trained at many different sizes and of
course you know each of these sizes are
going to be trained to with different
amount of tokens and so they're going to
reach a different sort of to total flop
as I sort of go through training right
now what I'm going to do is I'm going to
look at the lower envelope right the set
of sort of points or checkpoints that
prove to be optimal under any compute
budget and I can take these models and I
can look at okay what were the actual
parameter sizes of these models and you
can see that sort of the the total
compute on the x-axis here and the
number of parameters as well as the
corresponding tokens all forms a
relatively nice uh scaling law right and
so this is kind of the the minimum
envelope method it's basically saying I
expect the minimum training loss where I
optimize over all the model sizes to
actually be optimum in flops and sort of
um to call back to some earlier papers,
right? If you look back at the earlier
um sort of Kaplan paper and other
scaling laws, you see exactly this
already being done. You see, you know,
different models being trained with
different sort of parameters and
different compute scales and we're
taking sort of the minimum across these
and we've already seen that the minimum
forms a scaling law. So this is building
on this observation that the minimum
across many different training curves
across compute will should form a uh
power line. So under that assumption you
can get fairly nice fits. Um and this
gives you know one estimate that is
quite consistent um with others of of
0.5.
Now the other one this I think if you
were to pick a single canonical way to
do the chinchilla analysis um this would
probably be the one and in some ways I
think this is the most conceptually
straightforward one um which is the
isoflop analysis. So to do the isoflop
analysis what you do is you pick a bunch
of compute scales. So each of these
colors is a different amount of compute.
And what I'm going to do is for each of
these compute scales, I can essentially
have models with smaller parameters
trained with more data or more
parameters trained with less data.
Right? So I'm going to sweep over my
sort of model sizes for each of these
flops. And then I can look at the
minimum of each of these curves. I can
either pick the minimum point explicitly
sort of nonparametrically or I could fit
quadratics onto each of these and get
the minimum point of the quadratic. But
in either case, sort of the argument is
fairly simple. The argument is it should
be the case that this minimum itself
follows a predictable scaling law and
thus I can extract from it sort of the
optimum sort of parameters per flop. So
that's the minimum points across all of
these. Um and I can also extract the
optimal number of tokens per flop. I can
read that out by sort of dividing my
flops budget by the number of
parameters. Right? So I can get those
simultaneously. And you can see that
once again this gives very clean sort of
results um that are consistent with
method one. Right? So we can compare
that with before. This says for uh the
eventual chinchilla model budget you
want 63 billion parameters. Um this one
says 67 billion parameters. Um the two
are quite close,
right? Okay. The last one um honestly is
just a little bit messier. Um and this
goes back to kind of that Rosenfeld
paper. Um if you have a functional form
like this one, right? like this uh from
Rosenfeld. A very natural instinct is to
say, I'm just going to train a bunch of
models varying both N and M, right? And
I'm just going to do curve fitting. I'm
going to fit this curve onto whatever I
get a thing I get out of my models,
right? So, I'm going to train a bunch of
models and fit that 3D shape. Um, and we
know from Rosenfeld it's reasonable to
some extent to fit these, right? So,
you've got all these dots which are the
models. Um, I fitted a curve that's this
this sort of heat map color that you see
on the left. Um, and then you can sort
of back out what the implied isoflop
should look like from these dash lines.
But if you look at this, you know,
hopefully you see that the scaling law
fits and like sort of the curve fits
here are just not quite as good um as
the fits in the other plots, right? Um,
and you know, if you look at the
coefficients, the um, chinchilla method
3 just gives way different estimates in
terms of the model size and total token
count than the others, right? And
actually this was a mystery to me for a
long time. I think some of my students
were like why why is method 3 so
different and I said I don't know maybe
scaling laws are just sometimes noisy.
Um I don't know how many of you know
this but this is a really fun trivia
fact. Um or not trivia fact fun uh piece
of trivia let's say. Um so last year
some folks at Epoch AI I don't know what
motivated them to do this were curious
enough about this result that they went
and tried to replicate method 3. Um and
you know the it was very difficult to
replicate it because you don't have the
original data for all of these training
runs. So they actually like went to the
extreme of actually looking at the plots
and using sort of a forensic tool to to
extract the values of the points from
the plots and based on that they could
actually replicate um the original
result. And kind of the funny thing is
they showed that actually the the curve
fitting was the bad part. like their
data in their approach was good, but
actually when they fit the curve, they
didn't necessarily do it right. And so
the original fit had residuals. If
you're familiar with regression, you
know, your residual should be zero mean
centered because otherwise you should
be, you know, offsetting your
predictions to make it zero centered.
Um, their residuals are non zero and
then they, you know, fit it better. And
then when they did fit it better, well
actually their optimal estimate, you
know, almost exactly matched methods one
and two. Um and so this is one of those
funny cases where actually you know the
original authors had both the idea and
the data right but because of a minor
issue in curfeitting they they had kind
of had it wrong and the replication
actually makes it more correct uh than
before. Usually replication sort of
disproved things but in this case
actually the replication just showed
that the original result was correct all
along which is I think a pretty cool uh
result.
Okay, so the final thing I want to talk
about um with kind of this set of
chinchilla results is you know we're
talking about training optimal scaling.
So you have a fixed flops budget. I want
the best possible model um possible but
really I think that the story has really
shifted when sort of chinchilla was
written and the Kaplan paper was
written. um you know LLMs were not
really a product yet and so really the
name of the game was everyone wanted the
most biggest flashiest most intelligent
model but they didn't care about the
inference cost of actually deploying
these systems but nowadays you know what
we really care about is uh inference
costs right because these systems are
actually products they generate revenue
you know you have a cost associated with
the revenue um and so we've seen over
time that actually the tokens per
parameter has steadily grown right like
GPT3 was two tokens per parameter. Um,
Chinchilla moved us to 20 tokens per
parameter and for a bit people played
around with sort of 20 tokens per
parameter stuff, but then you know very
quickly people realized actually what we
care about is, you know, really good
intelligence at really small parameter
sizes and so people have really started
to scale up the number of tokens per
parameter very very rapidly. Um, and I
think I saw yesterday that for example
the most recent uh QEM models were
trained on 30 trillion tokens, right?
you know, people are really pushing the
limits on uh the tokens to parameter
ratio because really you would much
rather pay the upfront cost than to pay
the ongoing operating cost of uh in
running inference on a really big um
expensive
model.
Cool. Last thing um you know that is
kind of a fun side thing that I I want
to end with is to say um you know these
results are are pretty robust and easy
to replicate. Um a few years back uh one
of my students Isan was really
interested in you know really pushing
diffusion models for text forward. And
so one of the things that we had to do
was to say this is a whole new kind of
model. We don't know what the optimal
token to parameter ratio is. We don't
know if this thing even you know
reliably scales. It's a totally
different kind of generative model. Um
what do we do? Well, turns out, you
know, if you just fit uh the same kind
of playbook of saying, "Oh, we're going
to do, you know, isoflop analyses for
auto reggressive models, we get almost
exactly the chinchilla thing without too
much effort." You know, you do the same
kind of analysis on diffusion models.
Wow, we see, you know, very similar
kinds of curves, even though it's a
pretty different generative model
entirely. And then if you plot sort of
the minimum across of these, well, you
see very predictable scaling for both,
separated by a constant offset, right?
Right? Like I don't bring this up to
say, you know, uh because I want the
particularly pushed to diffusion models,
but just as a really random sort of case
study or example to say, you know, these
scaling laws don't necessarily need to
be these very cherrypicked examples.
They seem to happen pretty naturally um
as you're sort of working on new models
or working on new
environments. So, okay. Um you know this
is uh you know the
to put together this last part right log
linearity is not just about sort of
one-dimensional things where we think
about data they extend to sort of model
parameters they extend to total compute
and so that lets us you know make all
sorts of hyperparameter and other
decisions. That's kind of this first
part. Um and they're also letting us
make really smart resource trade-offs
right they let us make trade-offs
between sort of big models versus more
data. Um and we saw that in kind of this
chinchilla analysis and you know it's
kind of remarkable how cleanly uh things
like the isoflop analysis um turn
out. So all right that's all I got for
for basic data sc or basic uh scaling
laws. Um we did a recap or um of Kaplan
as well as Chinchilla today and
hopefully now you're on board with this
idea of data scaling, model scaling um
and using scaling loss to sort of
optimize all the aspects of your model
without actually going all the way to
the large scale training runs. Um thanks
and I'll see you all Thursday.