All right. So today's going to be the
the second of the basic systems
lectures. Um and now we're going to move
on to sort of multi-achine optimization.
And so the focus today is going to be
all about parallelism across uh
machines. And so the goal today is going
to move from, you know, optimizing a
single GPU's throughput to being able to
understand the complexities and the
details that are required to train
really large models, right? And model
when models get large, they no longer
fit on a single GPU. So you've got to
split up your your models across
different machines. Um, but also you've
got to be able to leverage all the
different, you know, uh, servers that
you have in order to train these models
quickly. So we've got both compute and
memory concerns that we're going to have
to deal with and communication across
different machines. It's going to be
quite heterogeneous. We have different
kinds of communication across GPUs at
different levels of hierarchy. And so
this is going to lead to different
parallelization paradigms. Um people use
many different parallelization
strategies all together at once. And
we're going to talk through each one of
the the very popular ones. Um and then
we'll talk about how you combine them
together in order to efficiently train a
very large model. Um and then I'm going
to end the lecture with sort of looking
at some examples um of how people are
actually using these parallelization
strategies um to run their large scale
distributed training runs. Okay. And so
that's going to roughly map to the
different parts of this lecture. We're
just going to talk about the basics of
networking first and then we're going to
talk about you know how do each of these
sort of networking hardware concepts map
to different parallelization strategies
and then finally some case studies to
close off with to show you how it all
comes together. Right? So I told you
about GPU scaling um last week and you
know it's quite impressive seeing this
you know super exponential curve of
flops per GPU going way way up. But if
we want to, you know, rapidly scale out
um, you know, both our compute and
memory, a single GPU isn't enough,
right? We're going to have to wait for,
you know, another couple years for for
this curve to continue going upwards and
upwards and upwards. So, if we want to
train a really powerful language model
here and now today, well, we have to
rely on multi-achine parallelism. So, if
we look at, you know, the world's
fastest supercomputers, that's what's
being shown on the right here. you know,
the the fastest supercomputers have, you
know, exoflops and exoflops of compute.
Um those are kind of the green um lines
that you see over there. That's what
you're really going to have to rely on
if you're going to try to train, you
know, the biggest baddest language
models today. Um and so that's the
compute side of why you want to think
about multi-achine parallelism. But
we've also got a memory angle for
thinking about the same thing, right? So
these two are really the core resources
and the core concerns that you're going
to have to think about. So in terms of
memory right many of the models are
getting quite big and of course you know
memory on GPU is also growing but not
not quite as quickly and a single GPU is
not going to be able to fit these models
right maybe eventually in the distant
future we won't have to worry about a
lot of these um but we've got you know
billions and billions of parameters
they're not going to fit very nicely
into a single GPU so we have to be very
respectful of the memory constraints
that we have so those are kind of the
realities that we have to deal with and
what are kind of the tools that we have
to have to be able to handle these well
you know GPUs I'm sure you've noticed in
the class uh cluster don't come in sort
of singleton right a single machine will
have multiple GPUs within the same sort
of physical uh rack and so here's an
example I I took this I think from the
GPT Neo X uh paper um but this is a old
example but the same lesson applies to
to uh the H100 machines that you have in
class so here there's eight different
GPUs right? They're connected to the
various CPUs through, you know, fast uh
interconnects. Um within each GPUs, you
see this NV switch thing at the bottom.
This is very, very fast connections
across these eight GPUs. But if these
eight GPUs want to talk to GPUs on a
different machine, they're going to have
to go through a networking switch. And
you see this, you know, purple line that
says HDR Infiniband, you know, that's a
much slower connection um uh compared to
the NVLink connection, right? You can
sort of see the difference in the
throughput. that's like about eight
times um slower per lane. Um and so this
kind of hardware hierarchy that we have
is going to have big implications for
how we're going to end up paralyzing our
models in practice, right? And so you
can kind of keep this mental model with
you as I talk through these things. you
know, we have very very fast connections
within a single machine and then when we
go across machines, it's going to get
slower and then depending on the the
kind of hardware we're using, there
might even be another level of slowness
once we go beyond let's say 256 uh GPUs
network together. Um, many of you may
already know this having taken systems
or networking classes, but here's a very
very brief refresher on collective
communication operations. Um, and the
reason why I'm going to bring this up is
there's one particular important sort of
identity or equivalence that you will
kind of need to know to really
understand some of the the finer points
of the performance characteristics uh of
the parallelization algorithms. Right?
So I'll I'll talk through these um and
then I'll talk through uh one important
sort of performance implication. So the
first one which all of you probably have
heard of is all reduced. Right? So you
have you know four machines, four ranks
in this case, each one having its own
sort of piece of data and what you'd
like to do is perform some sort of
reduction operation. Let's say I want to
sum all these these inputs and then I
want the output to be sort of copied
over to every single machine, right? Um
and this is going to you know have
roughly the cost of like two times the
total number of things that you're
you're all reducing. um you have a
broadcast operation and here I'm taking
a single sort of input from rank two and
I'd like to copy it out to all the
remaining ranks right and this is going
to have roughly on the order of one
times the total number of sort of
outputs um in terms of the communication
cost and then we've got reduction where
we got different inputs and that's going
to be summed up and then sent only to
one machine and then the two that are
quite important um even though these may
not be quite as common is going to be
the all gather and scatter right so all
gather is an operation where I'm taking,
you know, a single sort of subcomponent
of, let's say, my parameters from rank
zero and I'm copying it over to all the
ranks. Um, same thing with rank 1 2 3.
So each of these are handling different
parts of let's say the parameters and
they're copied over to the rest of the
machines. So that's sort of, you know,
copying what I have to everyone else.
And then reduce scatter, which is, you
know, I'm taking um, uh, each of the
rows, let's say, I'm summing them up and
then I'm sending the result only to rank
zero, right? So this is a partial
version of an all reduce and hopefully
this diagram makes it clear um how sort
of reduce scatter works and so all
gather and reduce scatter are quite
important because in some sense they are
the primitive by which uh many of the
parallelization algorithm are going to
be built and so uh this is this is kind
of an important sort of equivalence or
an identity I will refer to it um one or
two times as sort of key points in this
lecture if you want to do an all reduce
right let's say I've got um different GP
GPUs, right? AB, B, C, D. Um, and each
of the GPUs are handling a different
data point, right? And so I've got
different gradients for each of these
data points, and I'm going to need to
sum those gradients, and then I need to
pass all those gradients back to the
GPUs, right? This is a classic data
parallel operation that I might need to
do across my four GPUs. So that would be
an all reduce. Um one important thing
though is this could be uh replaced with
two operations a reduce scatter and all
gather where a reduce scatter is going
to you know sum sort of each of the rows
um and then leave the result of the rows
in let's say GPU 0 1 2 3 respectively
right and then I'm going to do a all
gather to sort of copy those back out to
the remaining GPUs right so each GPU now
is getting uh a full sum of uh a part of
the parameters and then it's going to
copy it back to the remaining ing
workers. Um, and in the bandwidth
limited regime, this is basically the
best that you can do, right? All reduce
the best that you can do is roughly
matching, you know, the the bandwidth
that you can get out of a reduce scatter
and all gather. And you can convince
yourself this by writing out how many
sort of communication operations happen
in both all reduce um and the right hand
side. Um the final thing um that I want
to sort of briefly touch on before I
sort of move on to talking about the
parallelization algorithms and this is
like the one place I'll talk about GPU
versus TPU. Um most of the the
discussion today can actually abstract
out the underlying hardware. Um but
there is actually sort of one important
thing that I'll I'll mention up front so
that I can refer to it later as I talk
through this. Um how do we network
together different machines or different
sort of accelerators in sort of GPUs?
Well, you know, as I showed you in uh
the GPT Neo X slide here, how in the GPU
world this generally works is you've got
nodes, single machines that contain,
let's say, eight GPUs, and then you've
got these switches that connect fairly
quickly to each other. And these
machines are connected all to all up to
about 256 GPUs. So that's a a important
threshold up until which you have very
fast arbitrary communication between
machines. And then above that, you're
actually going to need sort of much more
um slow communication. These sort of
leaf switches and spine switches once
you go beyond sort of roughly a single
rack's worth of GPU. On the other hand,
you know, if you look at sort of TPU
design from Google, they actually take a
very different approach to networking
sort of their their machines, um you've
got a single sort of TPU chip and they
all talk to their neighbors very very
quickly. And so this is a very sort of
easily expandable what they call toidal
mesh but you can only talk to your
neighbors. Um and the reason why I'm
talking about this right after the all
reduce slide is if you think about you
know doing these kinds of collective
communications like all reduce or reduce
scatter. Um you can implement them just
as efficiently on a toridal mesh than
you can on a alltoall connection. Um and
so if you're optimizing purely for
collective communications it makes sense
to think about things like TPU
networking um rather than GPU
networking. And I'll talk a little bit
about pros and cons of this later as I
go through different um parallelization
um
operations. So, okay. So, just to put
this together right now, we're going to
start talking about a new unit of sort
of compute, right? Instead of the GPU,
the new unit is the data center. The
whole data center is going to be the
thing that we're going to be doing. Um
and now we're going to try to come up
with algorithms and sort of sharding
strategies that get us two different
things. The first one is linear memory
scaling. So as I scale up the number of
GPUs, the sort of biggest model that I
can train is going to scale linearly
with that, right? So I can train bigger
and bigger models if I really want to,
right? Um I also want linear compute
scaling, right? As I get more and more
GPUs, the the useful computation that
I'm doing to train the model um scales
linearly, right? And then finally, a lot
of this these algorithms are going to be
implemented by just calling these very
simple collective communications
primitives in various ways. And so when
we think about the performance
characteristics of these uh parallel
algorithms, it suffices to reason about
you know basically counting the
collective communications primitives. So
so that's kind of an important way to
think about these. We don't we don't go
all the way down to the low-level
implementation um of these algorithms
here. Okay. Um any questions on part
one? Yes. Sorry, but from the previous
slide, does it mean that it's better to
do reduce scatter gathering rather than
all right? So so this slide, right?
Yeah. So the conclusion of this slide is
that they're equivalent, right? And I
think if you think about something like
um parallel uh doing doing um gradient
descent in parallel, all reduce is a
very natural operation to do because
you'll scatter your sorry you'll you'll
distribute your data to different
machines and then you'll have to all
reduce your gradients together, right?
Um but what I'm saying is this very
natural thing to do of all reduce can
actually be written as a sum of two
different operations. Um and they're
equivalent. So there's no performance
sort of charact by going from this left
representation to this right one at
least in bandwidth and that's going to
have you know important implications in
maybe like five slides. So you can wait
a little bit to see you know why I
mentioned
this.
Okay. Any other questions? Good.
Okay. So now we're going to get started.
Um in some sense this is kind of the the
exciting uh algorithmic meat uh of the
lecture. And there's three kinds of um
parallelism you know strategies
parallelism things that we should really
be thinking about. So the first one is
data parallelism. So data parallelism at
a high level is the idea of I'm going to
roughly copy the parameters across my
different GPUs. I'm not going to worry
about splitting my parameters up. But I
will take my batch and I will split my
batch up and different GPUs or different
machines will get different slices of my
batch. Right? So that's data
parallelism. There's lots of subtleties
in how we execute that. Um, model
parallelism now is starting to say,
okay, I don't want all my GPUs to have
all the different parts of my model,
right? As my models get bigger, that's
going to be a very big problem. So, I
need to cut up my model in very clever
ways, and I need my GPU to handle
different parts of my model, right? So,
that's going to be model parallelism.
Um, and then the final piece is kind of
activation parallelism. um we don't
really think too much about activations
in our day-to-day lives because you know
the PyTorch handles it very
transparently right but as the models
get bigger and the sequence lengths get
longer um the activation memory starts
to be a really big problem so if you
want to train these really big models
with big big batch sizes you have to
somehow manage the memory footprint of
your activations and so we have to split
those up too so there's some ways to
handle that right and when we put all
these together we will have all the
tools we need in order to scale up both
compute and memory gracefully as we have
lots and lots of machines. Right? So, so
these are kind of the core conceptual
objects. And now we're going to talk
about implementing each of these ideas
efficiently. So the starting point of
data parallelism is just sort of SGD,
right? If we're doing very naive batch
stocastic gradient descent, the formula
for doing this looks like this equation
um that I have, you know, right here on
the slide right here. um I'm taking a
batch size capital B and I'm going to
sum up all those gradients and I'm going
to update my parameters. Right? So naive
data parallelism is just saying all
right take your batch size B split that
up and send that to different machines.
Each machine will compute some part of
this sum and then I will exchange all of
my gradients together to synchronize you
know after each sort of before each
gradient step I will synchronize my
gradients and then I will take a
parameter update. Right? So now I've
been talking to you about compute and
memory scaling and all these things. So
let's just talk through, you know, what
it looks like for each of these, right?
So for compute scaling, uh, data
parallelism is pretty great. Um, each
machine, each GPU is going to get B over
M examples. And if my batch size is big
enough, you know, each GPU is going to
get a pretty decent batch size, micro
batch size, um, and it's able to
hopefully saturate its compute. Okay, so
that's good. What's the communication
overhead? Well, I'm going to have to
transmit twice the number uh of my
parameters every batch. Remember, an all
reduce is going to roughly be twice the
amount of stuff that you're all reducing
in terms of communication cost. Um, and
so this is okay if the batch size is
big, right? If my batch sizes are really
big, I can mask the communication
overhead of having to synchronize uh my
gradients every now and then. Memory
scaling, I'm not touching this at all.
Right? Every GPU needs to replicate the
number of parameters. it needs to
replicate the optimizer state. It's it's
pretty bad for memory scaling, right?
So, if we didn't have to worry about,
you know, memory at all, this is a this
is okay
strategy. Um, but I think in practice,
memory is a problem, right? Like I think
everyone of you sitting here has
experienced, you know, trying to put a
big model onto a GPU and PyTorch telling
you, oh, you're out of memory. Um, and
this is, you know, really a problem with
your training as well because if you can
fit, you know, more and more batch
sizes, that's going to make um the the
data parallel more efficient. And so
ideally, you'd like to save on memory.
So, let's take a closer look at the
memory usage of naive data parallel,
right? Um, and the memory situation is
actually worse than it looks. It's
actually quite terrible. Um because you
know you've you've done this in
assignment one but we can sort of think
about how many copies of our model we we
need to sort of store and it's very
large right depending on the precision
by which we're doing some of our
training. Um you're going to need to
store something like 16 bytes of data
per parameter. Um and in fact you need
to store something like five copies of
your weights. Um, and this is really
quite bad because if you just want to
think about your model parameters,
technically you only need two bytes,
right? So where did that factor of eight
come from? Well, at least you need
gradients. And if you're computing your
gradients in BF-16, that's another two
bytes. But then your optimizer state
kind of shows up and that's a that's a
really big problem because you've got
four bytes of sort of master weights,
the things that you're kind of
accumulating into SGD, like these
intermediate sort of sums that you're
doing. um you need you know four or two
bytes for for Adam's first moment
estimates because remember Adam keeps
track of historical gradients and then
Adam also needs second moment estimates
kind of like the variance uh of the the
gradients that you've gotten in the past
and like that's going to need another
four or two bytes and so what originally
looked fine is actually now looking
quite
grim and so you know this 16x if I just
sort of draw it as a picture you know
you realize that most of your memory
usage at least in terms of kind of
parameter memory is really being
dominated by the optimizer states of
your atom optimizer. Right? So your
memory consumed is going to be you know
a a function of you know how many bytes
are being used for your um optimizer
state and that's generally going to be
even more than the core uh parameter and
gradient memory usage. And so for a
simple example of like a 7.5b model
distributed over, you know, 64
accelerators, you're using a ton of
memory, right? And this memory scales
linearly upwards. Total memory at least
scales linearly upwards with the number
of GPUs. So that's that's no good at
all. Um, but if once we sort of look at
this picture, we get some very simple
ideas. You you might wonder clearly or
or maybe not clearly you know I need the
parameters and gradients to be copied
across devices that seems you know
necessary to do data parallel but do I
really need all the optimizer states to
be on every single machine right and
once you ask that question you know you
can maybe get to this second row here
and this is going to be this going to be
called um optimizer state sharding and
if we could do that then at least in
this case we can go from 120 GB of total
memory usage down to
31.4. Um, and then maybe we can start
sharding the gradients. And then now we
can get to 16.6 GB of memory usage. And
then if we also shard the parameters, we
can go all the way down to 1.9 GB of
memory usage. And that would be a pretty
good place to be because now we've sort
of fully sharded out, you know, all of
sort of the optimizer state and
parameter and gradient memory that we
need. Yes. Sorry. Why could we sh
optimizer state if like if we're doing
um I guess the gradient computation on
each of them like
reducing how can we have
that is a very good question and the
question is how can we shard the
optimizer state you know when we're
doing data parallel right GPU0 has to be
responsible for data point one so
clearly it needs to know about all the
parameters and update it so how can it
possibly shard the optimizer state um
And in a way I think zero which is what
this is this is the the zero overhead
data parallel sort of optimizer um this
is a very in some ways clever idea
because it shows you that even when
you're doing data parallel you don't
actually need to copy everything onto
every machine right you can be really
clever about how you do sort of
communications to avoid all of this so
so I will I will talk through exactly
this this is a great question um so what
we're going to do is we're going to
split up the optimizer states as I said
so the first and second moments are now
split up across all the GPUs. Um, but
everyone has the parameters and the
gradients, right? So, so why is this
important? Right? If I have the
parameters and gradients, let's say I'm
GPU0, I have the parameters and
gradients for everything. That's enough
information for me to compute the full
gradient, right? Like the full gradient
update for this example can be computed.
The only thing I can't do is I can't
take that gradient and take an atom
step, right? I can't update my
parameters unless I see all of the
optimizer states, right? So that's kind
of the key idea. And so now what going
to happen is GPU0 is going to compute
the gradients for everything, but GPU0
is now only responsible for updating the
parameters for the shard that they own,
right? And that's kind of the key idea,
right? We're going to distribute the
work of updating the parameters and then
we're going to synchronize the
parameters back. So let me show you in
in sort of much more gory detail how
this works and sort of the reason why
it's called zero overhead.
So step one right every GPU uh gets a
different data point let's say right I'm
just going to simplify all this batch
computation I have GPU 0 through let's
say four and every GPU gets a single
example and they compute a full gradient
on the example that they own now what
I'm going to do next is I'm going to
reduce scatter the gradients right so
I'm going to send the gradients that you
know um I'm going to collect in some
sense the gradients that each GPU owns
so GPU0 let's say is respon responsible
for this first quarter of the
parameters, right? So the parameters are
are the y-axis here and the x-axis here
is GPUs. And so what we're going to do
is we're going to reduce scatter to make
sure that GPU zero has all of the
gradient information from all the other
GPUs for the subset of parameters that
it is responsible for. Right? So now it
gets this G uh gradient information from
GPU 1 and GPU 2 and GPU 3 and that's all
reduced into GPU 0. Hopefully that's
clear. Now, now GPU0 has all the
information it needs to update its own
parameters because it has the optimizer
state corresponding to this first part.
It has a full summed gradient for this
first part. And now, so it's going to
take a gradient update on their part of
the parameters using gradient and state,
right? And so that now I have the full
updated parameters for this subset in my
GPU zero. And all I need to do is all
gather all of the parameter updated
parameters back in to all the ranks.
Okay. So there's many questions here.
I'll start here. Yes. When you say the
communication cost is the number of
frameworks that's per machine, right? Or
is that?
Sorry. Say say that again. The
communication cost being the number of
frameworks that's per machine, right? Or
is that total? Um so the question was uh
whether the number of crimes
communication cost was per machine or
it's total. Um here it's going to be
total because um so so this is going to
be like 1/4 of the parameter is going to
be sent three times to this machine and
then you repeat that four times.
Was that machine? That that was also
total. Yeah. Two times number of
parameters is total because each block
is going to have to be sent to every
other kind of machine.
Okay. Yes. So this question is not
unique to what you're showing here but
it made me think of it. So the outlines
that we showed seems to assume like
large largely assume independence of
parameters but we've drawn all these
like
diagrams that show the opposite you know
like we have connected nodes and all
that and it seems especially interesting
when we have when we're trying to split
these and update them separately. Uh is
does that create any issues? Okay, so
the question was Adam W seems to assume
parameters operate independently. I'm
assuming because you're saying like we
track like gradient sums like and then
we diagonally sort of update the
parameters, right? Um but we know that
that's not fully diagonal and so is
there a problem? Um there have been, you
know, better attempts um at improving
sort of Atom W to not just be diagonal.
There's things like KFAC and all these
other like second order style optimizers
that people have come up with. um they
haven't dethroned Adam even though they
do have their advantages and there's
some really interesting things that you
can do with these kinds of improved
second order preconditioning uh methods.
Yes. What is the reducing? What is the
rows that we're reducing over? Um so
you're asking like what is the rows of
this picture? Yeah. Yeah. So imagine
this is like parameters here uh in the
rows. So like GPU0 is responsible for
some number of parameters. So this is a
block of parameters up top. Um, and so
when we do reduce scatter, we're saying
take the gradients for example zero for
this block of parameters. Take the
gradients for example one for this same
block of parameters and then sum them
all and put them in rank zero. That's
kind of what we're saying
here. Cool. Okay. Um, and kind of the
key thing here is we're doing a reduced
scatter and an all gather, right? And if
you kind of remember what I was saying
before, well, a reduce scatter and a all
gather has the same cost as an all
reduce, right? And so there is a little
bit of a surprising magic thing that
happened here, which is that well, you
know, we were doing an all reduce before
on all the gradients to make sure
everyone's gradients were synchronized.
And that cost us two times the number of
parameters. But if we're kind of clever
about how we're doing the updates, well,
we can do a reduce scatter and all
gather. And in between the two steps we
can do some computation. Um and that
gives us the same amount of of compute
communication cost but now at least for
the optimizer state we fully sharted the
optimizer state across the model. So
zero stage one is in some sense free in
the bandwidth limited regime. Um and
gives you memory wins. Um yes
suppress the memory contribution of the
higher moments. Do people modify atom to
higher moments because
seems like it's um when what do you mean
by uh you can suppress the higher order
contributions right so uh for the first
and second moments the amount of memory
you
uh per per GPU is divided by yes so it
seems like you might as well show more
I see so so you're you're roughly saying
like you could track way more optimizer
state to rephrase what you're saying you
could have even more complicated
optimizer state because you can divide
that by the number of GPUs. Um while
this is true, um what's what we're going
to do next is we're actually going to
make the other components scale with
NGPUs. So that's going to make things in
some sense not free anymore, right? Like
optimizer state will continue to be the
bottleneck if we can divide everything
by the number of GPUs. So hopefully
that's a reasonable uh convincing
answer. Okay, so we're going to build up
stage by stage to zero stage three,
which is which is more complicated. Um
zero stage two is still relatively
simple. So now hopefully that optimizer
state sharding trick made sense. I I
think that's very cool. Um so now we
want to shard even more stuff. So I want
to shard the gradients across the
machines. Um so roughly we can do the
same kinds of trick as stage one. But
there is one additional complexity. Um
and so what what's the additional
complexity? Well, you know we can never
instantiate a full gradient vector,
right? If I ever do the full backwards
pass and I try to compute a full
gradient vector, um, I might go out of
memory, right? So I want my maximum
memory usage to basically be bounded by
this, which is like full parameters,
sharded gradient, sharded optimizer
state. And so what we're going to have
to do is when we do the backwards pass,
as we're computing the gradient vector,
we can't instantiate the full gradient
first and then do communication. What we
have to do is as we compute the
gradients backwards, as soon as we
compute like a layer's worth of
gradient, we're going to have to send
that over to the corresponding sort of
GPU that that it belongs to, right? Um
so this is kind of how it works. It's
roughly the same idea, right? So now um
everyone has their own batch component.
Everyone incrementally goes backwards on
the computation graph. And let's say
we're going to operate layer by layer,
right? So layers are sharted, you know,
atomically to different GPUs. Um so
what's what we're going to do then is as
we go backwards on the computation graph
after we compute a layer's gradients um
immediately call a reduction operation
to send this to the right worker right
so a layer belongs to some worker maybe
it's like GPU number two in this case so
we're just going to immediately reduce
that send that to the to the worker um
at that point and gradients are now no
longer needed um you know I don't need
to store the gradients on ranks 0 1 and
three so I can immediately free that um
and then now we continue this process
and So all the machines have their fully
updated gradients and now they have a
full gradient for their share of the
parameters. They have a full optimizer
state for their share of the parameters.
Each machine can update their parameters
and all gather the parameters back
together, right? Um this looks like it's
maybe more communication because you're
doing this kind of like um uh reduction
operation um every layer, but this is
only for a small amount of parameters,
right? It's sharded and so the full
communication remains the same. So zero
stage 2 has some more overhead because
we have to synchronize layer by layer
and make sure that the gradients are
properly sent to the right workers. Um
but the overhead is pretty minimal,
right? It's still very simple, fairly
straightforward. Now the last one of
these zero stage 3 is more complicated
for sure. Um but it allows you the
greatest win of all which is now
essentially everything is divided by the
number of GPUs that you have and you can
get the maximum savings uh possible. And
if you've heard of um you know FSDP
right you've probably used that in in
some aspect of your life in the past. Um
FSDP is exactly zero stage three. So now
you'll kind of hopefully today know how
FSDP um works. So the same idea applies.
We're going to shard everything
including the parameters. We're going to
do the same thing as zero stage 2, which
is we're going to incrementally
communicate and compute things so that
we don't keep these big vectors of
gradients lying around. Um, and we're
going to send and request parameters on
demand while we're going stepping
through the compute graph both for the
forward and backward passes. You know,
as we go through, we're going to send
things around on demand. Um, and of
course, the key is to do this with as
low overhead as possible. I think the
thing that's really surprising about
FSDP is not that this is possible, but
that this is possible with relatively
low overhead. Um you'll see kind of why
it's low overhead in the in the next um
slide. Um I I admit that this is maybe
not the the most uh friendly graphic to
start with, but this is I promise the
baby version um of SSDP. Uh the the next
slide is a little bit more more
involved. Um but conceptually this
actually explains everything. So what
we're doing is you know we're going to
have model weights and we're going to be
all gathering the model weights as we
go. So for each layer you know no single
uh GPU is going to have all the
parameters right. So I can't do the
normal thing of saying oh GPU zero go
ahead and run the forward pass. That's
not possible. So GPU0 let's say is let's
say it only owns you know the bottommost
layer. So it does that computation and
then it stops and says it requests all
of the the parameters from all the other
workers. So it stops and it does a all
gather which is right here. Um you see
there's a all gather step. It gathers
all the parameters. Now it has the
parameters that it needs to um do a
forward. So it can step forward and and
sort of compute the layer that it didn't
have before. And then now it can free
the weights. It doesn't need the weights
anymore. Get rid of it. Now I can all
gather the next layer. I can do another
forward. Free the weights. And I can
repeat this. Right? The activations have
to be stored. So the activation memory
here is is growing. Right? So that's
going to be a eventual problem. But if
we ignore activations for the moment,
this is great because I load a layer, I
do a forward, I free it, you know, the
memory overhead is very low here. Once I
get kind of to the end, now I can do the
same thing with a backward pass, right?
I can call backwards and every time I
move backwards through uh the neural
network, you know, I all gather for the
parameters that I need. You know, I can
do a reduce scatter to update, you know,
after the gradients that have been
computed. And now I can free the weights
or I can free both the gradients that I
don't need and the parameters. And at
the very end, you know, I've got a fully
updated uh model. And so we've got three
different operations that we've got to
worry about here. We've got an all
gather, we got another all gather, and
then we got another reduce scatter
basically to update um the model after
we take the uh gradient update step. So
conceptually this is just a a single
step beyond um zero stage two. But you
do kind of see that there is um sort of
more overhead. So the total
communication cost is now higher. Right?
We were kind of before we had two times
the number of parameters. Everything was
kind of free in some sense. Now it's not
right. There's total of three times
number of parameter communication cost
and there's going to be you know cost
associated with waiting for these
communication things to finish.
Um, but I think the really cool thing
about FSDP is it's actually surprisingly
low overhead. Um, you might imagine that
because we're doing this crazy thing of
asking for and sending parameters back
and forth all the time that you know
things will be really slow, right? Like
we have to be communicating all the
time. But you can do this this core idea
of overlapping communication and
computation. So you want both your sort
of uh you want your GPU to be working
while sort of the communication is
happening in the background almost like
pre-fetching so that by the time you
need some piece of information it's
already loaded up. It's already been
communicated to you and you're good to
go. Um and so I'll talk through this
example at the bottom here. Um but this
is kind of the key to making FSTP
actually uh somewhat efficient. So let's
imagine we have a computation graph that
looks something like this. W1 w plus w2
w0 times x some input let's say is y
right so some some very simple
computation graph like this and then um
you might run fsdp and you will get
actually uh computation and
communication that looks like this block
diagram at the very end here um so the
CPU you know it's nice that we did the
that uh insight systems example last
week because hopefully this diagram will
now be clear right the CPU is going to
basically dispatch a bunch of commands
um asking you know the the communication
part of the GPU to basically go and
fetch some some uh parameters. It's
going to dispatch things to the GPU to
say okay all right do some matrix
multiplies and it's going to run you
know far ahead in some sense of the GPU
right we've seen this when we were
looking at the profiler uh last week now
let's look at the sequence of both
communication and computation that
happens on device now um remember that I
need to sort of gather things on demand
so at the very beginning I have to make
sure that everyone has the weights for
uh layer zero or w0 here so I do all
gather zero and I'm going to wait for
that to complete and once that's
completed I can do a forward step on w0
I can sort of compute x * w0 let's say
right um at this point you know all
gather one starts at the same time that
all gather 0 ends so as I'm doing this
matrix multiply I'm basically already
starting to load the next parameters
that I need of course my communication
slower and so there is some gap but I
end sort of much quicker than sort of
the initial load so now forward one can
happen and in the background once again
I've started to to load you know
parameter number two and this yellow
slice here I'm now freeing you know the
parameters associated with forward one
and then now the other thing here is I'm
repeating computation w net0 is used
twice and so I don't need to communicate
this again this happens very quickly and
I can sort of uh do this very quickly
right I have forward two now already
loaded before sort of I needed it and so
there's no bubble here and then I can
free number two that's the entirety of
the forward pass and you see that the
gaps are relatively small here and we
able to do a lot of loads before the
compute needed to happen. And so by
doing this very clever thing of kind of
queuing the requests for weights um
before you actually need them, you can
avoid a lot of the overhead associated
with communication. And then now at this
point, you know, um of forward two, um
I'm done with the forward pass. I can
free weight number two and I start on
the backward pass. And you see that, you
know, all gather two for the backward
pass is already done. And so I can start
on backward two backward zero weight
zero is already stored. So that's done.
And then the high overhead here happens
in the backward pass because I need to
do reduce scatters and then all gathers
and so on and so forth. Right? Hopefully
you see this picture and you say, "Wow,
it's kind of surprising that even though
we're doing this crazy sharding, right?
Like if you go back to this picture, you
know, we've fully sharted the
parameters, gradients, and optimizer
states. Um, but the total bandwidth that
we need is only three times rather than
two times. So that doesn't seem too bad.
And sort of the actual, you know,
bubbles that we see are not horrendous,
right? The communication is is almost
being fully being utilized and the
computation isn't stalling for very
long. So, we're actually making pretty
efficient use of the resources that we
do have, which is
cool. Okay. Yes. Where do the get
prefetched to? It's like to my
understanding that like let's say the
GPU memory is like full where does the
weights get prefetched to? Yeah. Yeah.
So, so you need a buffer in which you
can store these weights. And so, you
know, the this picture is is not quite
right. Like you will have some overhead
that you need associated with reading
these weights for the current layer. And
also the other big elephant in the room
is I haven't talked at all about
activation. That's going to be like a
big chunk because you've got a big set
of activations for a full model uh that
is sort of living here in some sense.
Yeah. Cool. Um right. Okay. So this is
kind of distributed data parallel like
zero is in some ways the the way that
people do distributed data parallel
efficiently. Um and so there's different
stages and you know stage one is is
basically free right it's uh doing the
same communication pattern as uh naive
data parallel but you get to shard your
optimizer state that's great you might
as well always do it right zero stage 2
is twice the number of parameters so the
total bandwidth consumption is the same
but there is additional overhead in
having to do this like incremental
freeing of the gradients as you go
backwards zero stage three is more
involved you do three times number of
pram communication cost but it's not so
bad right like we did have some overhead
in the in the diagram that we saw before
but if you really cleverly mask your
communication patterns it's actually
pretty good and so people use data
parallel even for for fairly slow um
sort of links in your in your networking
pattern okay and this is also
conceptually very simple one of the the
advantages here is you know especially
data parallel doesn't care too much
about the architecture right I didn't
talk at all about how we actually
implement a transformer in any of this.
It's all very abstracted. And so this is
one of the reasons why, for example,
FSDP is so popular. It's very easy to
write a wrapper that parallelizes sort
of arbitrary neural networks um without
having deep knowledge or deep uh
introspection of what the architecture
um is actually doing. And so, you know,
here's some examples. I I worked out
some examples because I'm always sort of
running out of memory on my GPUs. Um,
and you can kind of see what's the
maximum size of the model that I can fit
on a eight eight times a 100 80 gig, you
know, node. Um, and so for baseline, you
know, you might end up with like, oh, I
can fit barely six billion parameter
model. Um, whereas I think if I use zero
stage three, you know, I'm able to fit
something like a 50 billion parameter
model. There's big savings um in my
ability to fit larger and larger models
by doing things like FSDP to to cleverly
save uh on memory.
So okay. Oh sorry there's a question.
Yes.
I guess I'm a little unclear as to like
what are the difference then once you
shard the parameters what's the
difference between that model? Yeah. So
model parallelism is really
fundamentally about making sure that the
parameters just like live in separate
let me see if I can find so they never
be communicated across. Yeah yeah yeah
like so in in some ways it's true that
we have sharted the parameters. So you
could call this a kind of parallelism.
Um but the whole point of model
parallelism is to make sure that the
parameters just live entirely in one
machine. We're not going to like try to
ship them across in various ways. Only
the activations are going to get shipped
across. Um and so you'll see very
different discussions in the model
parallelism section like the focus there
will be on communicating activations
rather than uh communicating parameters
and that'll be a big difference. Yes.
Let me see if the parameters are only on
why are why are you performing an all
gather?
So, so you're asking about
um this step like why are we doing all
gather to gather weights onto all the
machines? Is that when they're only on
one machine? Is that right? Yeah. So, we
need to basically put we need to take
the weights that live on one machine and
scatter or is it gather or scatter?
Sorry, I want to make sure I get this
right.
Um the terminology is a little bit
sketchy for me. So I want to make sure I
get
um
sorry. Yeah. So what we want to do is
the same as this, right? So each machine
is going to have um some parameter that
I want to sc gather across all the
machines um in order to make sure that
each layer is sort of properly uh sort
of replicated across all the GPUs.
Is that the right question that you're
asking? Or are you saying like is there
a simpler primitive that we could have
invoked? Like are you saying broadcast
is the right object rather than all
gather? I think maybe it's written that
way because of some exceptions about
layers not living on individual GPUs,
but I'm not 100% sure. I agree with you
that like broadcast should be able to do
uh the same thing if the the parameters
live on only one
machine. Okay, cool. Alrighty. Okay, let
me make
sure
where. Okay, got it. Okay, right. So, um
there is a key resource in data
parallel. Um and this is actually a
important idea that I want you to
remember. Um with data parallel, batch
size is actually a really critical
resource um in the sense that you can't
parallelize greater than your number uh
sorry than your batch size, right?
Because you can have at most one example
uh on each machine. you can't go to
fractional examples per machine. Um, and
so this means that you know there are if
there's limits to your batch size,
right? You stop being able to use data
parallel. Um, and there's diminishing
returns to batch sizes. So, you know, in
your assignment one, you may have played
with varying batch sizes, but you kind
of know that as you crank up the batch
size past a certain point, you start to
see sort of fairly rapid diminishing
returns to, you know, your optimization
rates. Um and there's lots of papers
written on this. OpenAI has a really
nice one um on something called critical
batch sizes um where they basically
argue that you know past a certain point
you have very rapid diminishing returns
in how much each example is contributing
to your ability to optimize. Like
basically the the intuition is that
below a certain point you have a lot of
gradient noise and reducing that is very
valuable but at a certain point you're
really fundamentally limited by the
number of gradient steps you're taking
rather than variance reduction. Um, and
so that basically means data parallel
alone isn't going to get you to
arbitrarily large parallelism. And this
batch size thing is a really important
resource, right? You want to essentially
you have a fixed maximum batch size and
you can spend it in different ways. Um,
and I'll talk about that later because
other kinds of parallelism also benefit
from having uh sort of bigger batches
and so you use your batch size in
certain uh parts. Okay. Um, and issues
are going to remain with data parallel.
um you know zero stages one and two
don't let you scale memory. Zero stage 3
is nice in in principle but it can be
slow and maybe more importantly and this
you know relates to the the earlier
question it does not reduce activation
memory right um I ideally want to like
cut up my model entirely and make them
live totally separately because then the
activation memory would also sort of be
reduced and so now I I want better ways
to split up the model so I can fit these
really big models um in these
GPUs and so that's going to bring us to
uh model parallelism. Um we want to
scale up in memory um you know without
changing the batch size and we want an
alternative axis where we don't need to
spend or basically have big batch sizes
in order to parallelize. Um and so what
what we're going to do is it's going to
split up the parameters across GPUs and
in some ways that's like 03. Um but
we're not going to communicate
parameters anymore. We're going to pass
activations around and that's going to
be different. Um and sometimes
activations are going to be much smaller
than parameters and that'll be you know
very good for us. So we'll cover two
different types of parallelism. Um I'm
going to talk about pipeline parallel
which is conceptually simpler um but
much more horrible implementation wise
and tensor parallel which is
conceptually maybe less obvious um but
honestly much nicer to implement and
more commonly used. Um and they're going
to correspond to two different ways of
cutting up the model. So I think
pipeline parallel is maybe the most
obvious way to cut up a neural network,
right? You know that a deep neural
network comes in layers, right? So if I
have layers, a very natural place to cut
a network is to cut it up at the layer
boundaries. And so each GPU is going to
handle some subset of the layers and I'm
going to pass activations around like in
this case each layer belongs to a GPU
and GPUs are going to pass activations
from from one to the other when in the
backwards case it's going to pass you
know the backwards gradients backwards
from GPU 3 to zero right okay so that's
cool that's great um what's wrong with
this picture well I think you should see
that most of your GPUs are idle most of
the time this This is actually quite
terrible utilization. Um, and so if I do
this naive kind of parallelism that I
described before, right? So if I have,
you know, each layer um having a forward
and let's say I have a single example,
that's going to result in a in a diagram
that looks like this. So different rows
in this picture um are different um GPU
uh different layers and also different
GPUs. And the x-axis here is time where
I'm going from left to right. So what do
you see? Well, you know, I first compute
my first layer at the very left here,
and then the activations get past the
second layer. GPU 2 wakes up, and it's
like, "All right, it's my turn. It does
its job, passes it to GPU 3, and then
GPU 4, and now the backwards passes can
begin." Um, and so on and so forth. And
you see kind of this gigantic what
people call bubble. This is a big
overhead where you're doing absolutely
nothing. Um, and you see that the GPUs
are active one overn. Um so in some
sense this is the worst possible
parallelism of I've added four GPUs but
I get the throughput of a single GPU
right um and so one thing you can do
is you know you can be a little bit more
clever about what you do and you can say
all right I'm going to have a pipeline
right I'm not just going to cut things
up in layers I'm going to have a
sequence of things that need to be
processed by each GPU so now let's say I
have a micro batch right so each machine
is going to handle sort of four examples
Um, and what I'm going to do is, you
know, I can finish my first example, my
first uh data point, and I can send off
the activations for that to my second
GPU as soon as I finish, and then I can
then get started working on my second
data point, right? And so now I've over
overlapped sort of, you know,
communication and computation. The
second GPU can start working while the
first GPU continues to work. And now the
size of the bubble can potentially be
reduced by having bigger batch sizes,
right? Right? And you can hopefully see
why I said before that batch sizes are a
resource. If you have a finite batch
size and you have pipeline parallel, you
can use that same batch size to make
your pipeline bubble size smaller, for
example, or you could use it to do data
parallel, right? So there's many
different ways that you can take your
single batch size and then split it up
into different ways. Okay, so now um
your micro batch size can control the
bubble time and in fact you know the
amount of uh the ratio of your your
overhead to the useful compute that you
have is the number of stages minus one
over the number of micro batches. So if
you have big big batch sizes pipeline
parallel could potentially be efficient
but as we said before you know batch
sizes are finite we can't just crank
that up to whatever value that we want.
So, you know, in general, pipelines seem
really horrible. Um, you know, why do we
do it? Why do we incur this cost of a
bubble um in order to, you know,
parallelize? Well, there's a couple
reasons. Pipelines help save memory um
compared to to data parallel. I mean, 03
will will also shard the parameters, but
this also shards of the activations,
which is nice. Um, pipelines can also
have good communication properties,
right? It only depends on activations.
It's also pointto-point. So it's
possible that depending on your topology
and depending on what you have,
pipelines might actually be very
favorable for the slower parts of your
network. Um and so you know pipeline
parallel is often going to be used on
your slower network links. So inter node
or um even sometimes um across different
sort of uh racks or across different
data centers you might do actually not
data centers across different racks you
might do pipeline parallel, right? Um,
one of the the examples of a thing that
I was recently told by by some Google
folks is, you know, they were saying
actually one of the big advantages of
TPUs is that we don't have to do
pipeline parallel very much because, you
know, all of our connections are are
much bigger, right? Like they have this
big tooidal mesh. They don't have this
limit at 256 GPUs where they're suddenly
going towards a slower network link
where you might want to switch to
pipeline parallel, right? So that's a
real world kind of example of when you
would start to think about pipeline
parallel. And so this is an example from
an NVIDIA paper. or I'll talk about this
paper in uh much greater detail later.
Um they've done some some really nice
work showing sort of performance
characteristics of different kinds of
parallelism. But you kind of see with
batch size 8 as you increase the
pipeline parallel size the number of
devices um your you know utilization per
GPU sort of starts to really drop off.
Whereas if you have a big big batch size
of 128 you can get away with you know
pretty good utilization um for
reasonably sized pipeline parallel.
Right? So batch sizes are really key to
hiding the size of the bubble. Um
otherwise you have
issues. Um of course you can do you know
different kinds of pipeline sort of uh
pipeline strategies. So instead of you
know having um these sort of like uh
standard uh patterns for scheduling the
bubble you can sort of cut things up
into into finer pieces um where you're
sort of assigning different stages
assigning different sub layers to
different device and you're doing
different computations at different
parts. You can then sort of interle the
pipeline better. And sort of an advanced
version of this that I want to spend a
moment talking about and this is very
very clever um is zero bubble pipelining
or I think in in uh DeepSeeks lingo I
think they call it dualpipe but the core
single trick um is the same. Um so here
if you think about it let's say we're
doing you know the backwards pass to
compute gradients you can split this up
into two different components. Um the
first part is about you know back
propagating the activations. Um so this
is you know as I go down sort of the
residual connections I need to compute
essentially the the derivative with
respect to the activations and then you
know as I sort of you know get to a
parameter I also want to compute the
gradient itself like how am I going to
update the parameters not just how do
the activation change with respect to
sort of the previous layers and so to to
give you a concrete example let's look
at this bottom left diagram over here
right so in this diagram um you see the
forward pass this is a single MLP so
we've got um multiply by a I do a
nonlinearity and then I'm just going to
output the nonlinearity, right? So this
is a kind of a naive, you know, single
part of MLP. Now let's look at the
backwards. You know, I have sort of the
the derivative with respect to the loss.
It comes in and then I can compute, you
know, how that's going to change um the
the x's the inputs to my MLP. So this is
in some sense the the derivatives with
respect to the activations here. And
then as I compute these, of course, I
can use them to compute the gradients
that I need to update my weights, right?
Um but the important thing is this part
this part of computing the gradients for
the weights this can be done whenever
right there's no sort of dependence of
this um and so I can rearrange the
scheduling for this computation to any
part of the computation graph and so
what you can do is you can sort of do
your standard pipeline parallel for the
parts that are serially dependent but
anytime you have to do these
computations just for updating the
parameters you can sort of reschedu them
wherever and so the key idea is you
start with sort of a nice um what it's
called 1F1B pipeline. This is a nice
optimized reducing the bubble size
schedule. Um and then you can take this
and what you can do is you can separate
you know this B which is this
computation of the the backwards part.
um and then W which is the computation
necessary to compute the gradient of the
weights and now I can do the computation
of the weights the W's where I would
have originally had a bubble right so
the parts where you know I originally
had these white um white sort of idle
utilization components I can now fill
them in with these W's right and so by
thinking carefully about what the serial
dependencies actually are you know I can
now have something really nice where I'm
getting actually good utilization out of
my GPUs um to To be clear, um this is
horrendously complicated, right? Like if
you actually want to implement pipeline
parallel in this way, you're going to
have to like intervene in how you know
your your uh autodiff is actually
calculating these things. You have to
have a cue that can track where things
go. Um I heard a a funny anecdote in a
conversation recently um from someone in
a in a frontier lab sort of training LMS
and they said you know actually there's
two people in the group that understand
how the pipeline parallel in our infra
works one person left and so there's a
single loadbearing person in our
training infra you know like there are
stories like this um pipeline parallel
is infrastructurally very very
complicated right it looks simple here
um if you if you're interested you I
encourage you to try and implement it um
it does get pretty hairy pretty fast and
I think that's a good note on which to
switch to the other kind of model
parallelism um because this is much
simpler and this is often you know very
cleanly utilized by a lot of frameworks
and a lot of sort of even people
training really big models rely very
very heavily or primarily on this kind
of model parallelism. So what other way
can we split up a model right? So if we
think about it um most of what we do is
matrix multiplies right in a big model
most of the computation is matrix
multiplies most of the parameters are
matrix multiplies or matrices um and so
what can we do well if we can
parallelize just the the map moles that
would be pretty good and so tensor
parallel is this idea that we can take a
big matrix multiply and split it up into
a set of submatrices that can be
multiplied right so if I have you know
this matrix multiply at the top right we
have X um and sort of uh X * A= Y. You
know what I can do instead is I can cut
up A into half, right? And then I can
also cut up X into half and I can
compute the submatrices. I can sum them
up and then I will get my answer at the
end, right? So conceptually pipeline
parallel is cutting along the depth
dimension like the layers. Um tensor
parallel which is what this is is
cutting up along the width dimension of
your matrix multiplies. And so we're
going to decompose into submatrices and
then do partial sums. Um so here's an
example of what it might look like in
MLP, right? We we have each GPU handling
a different submatrix
um of uh let's say a big MLP matrix
multiply and then we're going to have
collective communications to synchronize
um the activations as we kind of need
them, right? So what are we going to do?
So this is a MLP um and sort of the the
top half and the bottom half there's two
different paths. These are you know
splitting up the matrices. So I I want
to do uh this operation yals gel x * a.
Um I'm going to split up my matrix A
into A1 and A2. And then on the right
hand side I want to compute drop out YB.
Right? And then I want to return the
result as Z. So I'm going to also cut up
B. Right? So I've cut up both of my dig
parameter matrices into two parts A and
B. Um, and in the forward pass, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take my
inputs X and I'm just going to copy them
twice. Right? So each GPU is going to
get the same inputs and they're going to
operate on it with A1 and A2. Right?
They have the same kind of Oh, sorry.
They're the same uh row dimensions. So
it's going to be fine operating on them.
So X A1 and X A2 um is going to give you
some activations Y1 and Y2. Those are
going to go into B1 and B2. And then I'm
going to do an all reduce to sum them
up. That's exactly the figure I showed
you before, right? So you copy and then
you all reduce and you get the answer Z
in the backwards pass. Now it's actually
the reverse as sort of the gradients
come backwards in the backwards steps.
This G is going to be um the identity.
So I'm going to copy sort of the
derivatives on both sides and I'm going
to do sort of the backwards operation
all the way through. And once I get to f
um this is on all reduce, right? Because
I've got sort of two derivatives um sort
of coming in from both paths and then I
sum them back up, right? So this f and g
are synchronization barriers. In the
forward pass I do a single all reduce.
On the backwards pass I do a single all
reduce just at two different places um
in the computation graph. Right? So now
you can hopefully see how this is a very
nice way of wherever you have a matrix
multiply you can just cut up the matrix
multiply and sort of parallelize them
across different um
devices. Okay. Um and as you might
imagine this is actually somewhat
expensive. we have a synchronization
barrier that lives kind of per layer. It
needs to communicate um an activation
sort of like the the the residual
activation worth of stuff twice in a
forward backward pass. And so tensor
parallel this very simple idea um is
going to require very high-speed
interconnects. And so there's a rule of
thumb. It's a very simple rule of thumb
to remember which is that tensor
parallel is applied within device or
within a single node, right? So a single
box um of let's say Nvidia GPUs is going
to ship with eight different GPUs that
live in that same box, right? And as I
showed you at the sort of beginning of
lecture today, they're very very
high-speed connected, right? So those
eight GPUs can talk to each other very
quickly. Um and so it makes sense to use
something like Tensor Parallel that's
very bandwidth hungry um on between
those eight devices. So what we you will
typically see is that tensor parallel is
applied up to eight GPUs where the eight
GPUs live in the same machine um because
that gives you the least sort of drop in
performance. And so this is an example
um from hugging faces sort of
parallelization tutorial um showing you
sort of the throughput decreases of
different levels of tensor parallelism.
You see that there are hits right 10 and
12% hits to to uh throughput as you do
tensor parallelism. Um, but up until
eight, well, maybe this is manageable.
This is kind of the price you pay for
just being able to paralyze more nicely.
But then you go to 16 devices and you
get this like kind of astounding 42%
drop in performance. You go to 32 and
you see another sort of 65% drop in
throughput, right? And so you see
hopefully visually here that you really
want to stop at 8 for tensor
parallelism. That's really the sweet
spot because of the the kinds of
hardware interconnects uh you can get
your hands
on. Okay. So how do things now compare
to pipeline parallel right? Um well
compared to pipeline parallel we don't
really have to deal with this bubble
thing that we had before. We don't need
to consume sort of larger batch sizes in
order to reduce the bubble. Um which is
nice. And there's very relatively I
wouldn't say very there's relatively low
complexity in applying tensor parallel
right all you really need to know about
are where are the big matrix multiplies?
Can I split them up and make them live
on different devices? Right? The
forwards and backwards operations still
remain the same. right? Compared to
implementing something like zero
overhead or dualpipe pipeline parallel,
you're going to be in much much better
shape um doing this. So the con is that
it's much larger communication overhead.
Um you've got you know in pipeline
parallel batch size time sequence length
time sort of residual dimension
pointto-point communications per
microbatch. Um in tensor parallel you've
got you know eight times that per layer
and you've got all reduced
communication. um it's potentially a
very large amount of communication that
needs to be done. So you know the rule
of thumb as I said before is tensor
parallel is used whenever you have low
latency high bandwidth interconnects.
You're going to see you know two to like
16 depending on you know what kinds of
machines you have um of tensor parallel
out in the wild. And I'll show you
examples um as I talk through at the
very end here uh of examples of tensor
parallel. Okay. Um any questions of on
uh pipeline or tensor parallel before we
move on to the kind of third kind like
sequence parallel and activation uh
sharding. Yes. Are these
uh can they both be used simultaneously
or are they? Yeah. So the question was
can they be used simultaneously? Um the
answer is that yeah you do use them uh
both. So I think we'll we'll get to
examples later but I think the typical
thing that you see is you for large
scale runs you very often see tensor
parallel. Um pipeline parallel is often
used on top of that. I think the only
example I know of that does pipeline but
not tensor parallel would be deepseeek
v3 um as far as I know. So within a
single machine I guess you have like say
like you have like five different
machines you have like maybe the first
20% of the parameters are across the
each first machine tensor parallel one
and then that pipeline parallels into
the second machine would be the next
step. Yeah. So the the question was
there uh do you do tensor parallel
within machine and like pipeline
parallel across machine for example.
Yeah. So so you would do something like
tensor parallel within machine and a
combination of data and pipeline
parallel across machines for example
right. Um, and I'll show you the rule of
thumb later, but basically you do
pipeline parallel because your models
won't fit. Like if you if you could fit
your entire model, you just do data
parallel plus tensor parallel or, you
know, just maybe even data
parallel. Great.
Okay. Excellent. So then, you know,
we've been talking about memory and
memory is you know, in some sense a very
important part of parallelization
because we're going to be training big
models. Um and so you know when you look
at your memory you realize that actually
activations are a really big part of
your memory usage. So if you look at you
know uh standard kind of forward
backward pass I think this was one from
one of the pietorrch tutorials. um you
see that memory usage is very dynamic,
right? So I I'll just talk through this
because I think it's an interesting plot
in general, right? Um you always have
your parameters as you're training,
right? Because that's static, but you
know in iteration zero, you don't still
have optimizer state at all. So actually
you don't have that part of your memory
use. But as you do, you know, your
forward and backwards, you see
activation grows grows grows grows grows
as you, you know, accumulate all the
activations. And as you start your
backwards pass, right, your activation
goes down because you're freeing it as
you use up your activations and then
you're accumulating your gradient. So
your gradient memory usage goes up. And
the peak is actually somewhere, you
know, partially through your backwards
pass where you haven't freed all your
activations yet. Um, and you're still
building up your gradients. And so in
iteration two, you kind of see the same
thing here, right? And so, you know, the
point of this diagram is to say, well,
we've thought about all the other
pieces. We thought about the parameters.
We've thought about optimizer state.
We've thought about you know the
gradients. Um but we have not thought
about very deeply at least the
activations. And so let's do that.
Right. So the final complexity that I
want to talk you through is the
activation memory. So tensor and
pipeline parallel can linearly reduce
you know basically most things but it
can't actually reduce all of the
activation uh memory usage. And so this
is an example um from one of the NVIDIA
papers that's talking about you know how
do you reduce um activation memory and I
think one thing that's really
interesting to see is as you make your
models bigger and bigger so going from
left to right you see that you know a
parameter and optimizer state memory can
can remain the same if we if we
parallelize aggressively but activation
memory just kind of continues to grow
because some parts of it don't
parallelize very cleanly. So no matter
the number of devices you have um
actually you can't really get rid of the
growth of activation memory per device
and I'll and I'll show you why in a
moment here. Whereas I think if you do
some slightly more clever things like
recomputation um you can keep the
activation memory low and that's really
key to to paralyzing some of the biggest
models.
Okay. Okay. So what's the activation
memory per layer? You've kind of done
some of this you know transformer math
and and calculus before. So hopefully
you're you're now familiar um with all
of this, but we can compute what's the
amount of activation memory we need per
layer. And there's a handy formula here.
And this is the amount of memory you
need. It's SBH * 34 + 5 A S overH. Um
and some of these numbers are
mystifying, but actually they're not so
mystifying. Um you know, you can very
very much see that there's a left term
and then there's a right term. The left
term comes from, you know, the MLP and
like other pointwise operations. That's
where SBH * 34 comes from. These depend
on the size of of your residual stream,
right? The H. Um, on the right side, you
have a term that's actually, if you
multiply this out, A S^ squ B, right?
Because the H's cancel. Um, that's the
memory that you need for the softmax
term and and other sort of, you know,
quadratic terms in your attention,
right? Um, of course, if you use flash
attention, you can drastically reduce uh
and and use recomputation, you we know
that we can drastically reduce that
second term, right? Um so then let's say
we do tensor parallel right we do tensor
parallel everywhere we can. So we do it
in the MLPS we do it in the uh KQ
computations in um the uh in the
attention computation um we will end up
with something that looks like this and
this is looking pretty good but not
quite there. So activation memory per
layer divided by t which is the number
of sort of devices that we're tensor
paralleling over right. So if we're
dividing by 8, right, ideally we would
divide all the activation memory by 8.
But you see there's this straggler term
SBH * 10 that has not been sort of
reduced down. Um and you know if you
think about what these are, these are
the non-mapatmo components. So the layer
norm, the dropouts, the inputs to the
attention and the MLP, right? All of
these terms will unfortunately continue
to grow with size and they will not be
paralyzed very nicely, right?
And so the very last thing that we need
to think about is to take those simple
point-wise operations which thus far we
have not parallelized um and we just
need to split them up right um and
there's a very simple way to split them
up which is to say well if we're doing
like a layer norm right these layer
norms across different positions in the
sequence do not interact at all with
each other right like they just don't
care about um anything else um and so
what we're going to do is let's say we
have a 1024 long sequence we're going to
cut that up and then each device will
handle a different part of that layer
norm or a different part of that
dropout. Right? Those point-wise
operations can now be completely split
up across the sequence dimension. Um and
because you know now we're cutting
things up across the sequence dimension,
we're going to have to do some
synchronization to make sure you know
the the parallel computations that we
did will can get aggregated back again.
Um and so in the forward pass, these G's
they're going to be all gathers and G
bars are going to be reduced scatters.
And in the backwards pass, the two are
reversed. In some sense, there's sort of
a duality here uh between the two. And
what we're doing here is, you know, for
the layer norm, we've kind of scattered
things uh around. And so we're going to
have to gather them back together um so
that we can do sort of our standard
computation. And then now whenever we
get to the dropout, we want to scatter
them back out into the sort of parallel
components that we have. And in the
backwards pass, we're kind of doing that
in the reverse,
right? Okay. So hopefully that is clear.
Um, this is a very simple idea, right?
We're just parallelizing sort of the
very last components that we failed to
parallelize before. Um, and so now we
can sort of put all these different
pieces together and sort of get to sort
of the end, which is we started up here,
which is no parallelism at all. We did
tensor parallel, which allows us to
divide everything that's not a pointwise
op by t. And then if we apply, you know,
the sequence parallelism idea, we can
divide this component by t once more. Um
and then you know we can do things like
activation recomputation which is you
know the flash attention trick to remove
the second term. And the minimal memory
that you can kind of easily get away
with is going to be this thing on the
bottom which is SB8 H34 overt. Um and
this is often used um if you're looking
at different formulas for transformer
arithmetic on like how much activation
memory do I use? You know you often see
something like PH34 and then if you have
tensor parallel divide by T. um because
this is the sort of easy minimum that
you can get for that kind of a memory.
Okay, any questions on on uh sequence
parallel and activations? Yes, I was
wondering like the transformers like
stack on top of each other. I suppose a
combinational graph will grow more and
more like imaginative pip combinational
graph as like a
dag would that ever become the
communication between the engineers?
You're saying if we have something
that's a more complicated computation
graph than like a single linear chain,
will that become a problem?
It's a good question. I haven't thought
about that. I I would guess not. Like at
least for tensor parallel, this operates
purely layer wise. It doesn't really
care about the dependencies. Maybe for
pipeline parallel, there's opportunities
for increased parallelization if there's
more than one branch, but I'm not too
sure. this general,
right?
Yes.
Right. Okay. Cool. All right. So, um,
there's a few other parallelism
strategies that I'm not going to talk
about, um, just because in the interest
of sort of time and, uh, sort of
fatiguing you because I think I've
already dragged you through a whole
bunch of low-level details about how to
do parallelization. Um, so the first one
I want to talk about is uh, context
parallel or ring attention. You may have
heard the term ring attention before. Um
this is a way of essentially splitting
up both the computation and the
activation cost of computing really
large attention. Um where essentially
you're just going to pass keys and
values around different machines. So
each machine is responsible for a
different query and then keys and values
are going to sort of travel from machine
to machine in a sort of ring-like
fashion um in order to compute your KQV
uh inner products. And the cool thing
here is you already kind of know how to
do this because you've done the tiling
for flash attention. So you know that
the um so you know that attention can be
computed in this kind of online tile by
tile way. And that's kind of what's
happening um in ring attention. The
other thing um which now that you know
tensor parallel is pretty
straightforward is expert parallelism.
Right? Expert parallelism you can kind
of think of as almost like tensor
parallel in the sense that you're
splitting up you know one big MLP into
smaller uh expert MLPS. let's say um and
then scattering them across different
machines. The key difference with expert
parallelism is that the experts are
sparssely activated. And so you have to
think a little bit about routing and the
routing is not going to be um sort of as
predictable let's say as the alltoall
communication that we had um before in
tensor parallel because now you know
maybe one expert is overloaded your
networking is going to be a little bit
more complicated but otherwise
conceptually you're living in kind of
the same world as tensor parallel um for
expert parallelism.
Okay, so just to recap all the things we
talked about, um I've made a little
small table of the different kinds of
strategies that we have. You know, we
have DDP and 01. Um this is kind of the
naive data parallelism thing that you
do. Um here you have some overhead per
batch. You have no memory scaling,
reasonable bandwidth properties. Um but
you consume batch size in order to be
able to do this, right? You need big
batch sizes to have big data
parallelism. you have FSTP which is kind
of like a nicer version of 01 in the
sense that you can get uh memory scaling
but you're going to pay uh overhead
across sort of different layers right
and so now you've got higher uh
communication cost and you've got
potentially synchronization barriers
that lead to poor utilization pipeline
parallel you know is nice in that you
know we no longer uh have this
dependence on um on this per batch
aspects but and we can get linear memory
scaling But we have sort of another
issue which is this also consumes batch
size and it's horrendous to sort of set
up and use and so a lot of people like
to avoid pipeline parallelism if it's
possible. Then finally tensor
parallelism is very high cost in terms
of bandwidth and the amount of
synchronization you need to do. Um but
um this has this really nice property
that has no impact on batch sizes. So
it's like kind of the one parallelism
strategy you can use that has no cost in
terms of your global batch size which is
nice right. So we have to balance a
number of limited resources, right? We
have memory which is one resource. We
have uh bandwidth and compute which is
another resource and then we have batch
size which is kind of an unconventional
resource but one that you should really
think of as a limited thing that you can
spend on different aspects of these to
improve your efficiency.
Um and there's a very nice uh TPU
parallelism or TPU book let's call it um
from Google that I referred to um last
week but also actually they have a
really nice parallelism section and they
have this great figure that I wanted to
show you uh before I moved on to some of
the examples. Um so the key quantity as
I was saying before is the batch size
and depending on you know the ratio of
batch size to the number of GPUs you
have different kinds of parallelism
become optimal and so they use sort of
certain formula on how much
communication and computation you end up
doing um sort of uh for each of these
models. also this a simplified formula
um to sort of generate this plot and you
can kind of see if your batch size is
too small you have lots of GPUs and
really you know tiny batch sizes then
there is no way for you to be efficient
right you're always communication bound
which is this bottom half here and in
fact you're you're spending most of your
time on communication um as you sort of
get more and more batch size eventually
you can get to a point where uh if you
mix both FSDP so zero stage three and MP
which in this case is tensor parallel.
You can actually get basically to a
place where you're compute bound. So now
you're not, you know, spending um sort
of wasting your flops waiting for
communication. And then finally, you
know, if you get to a point where your
batch sizes are big, then you can just
get away with pure data parallel like
pure FSDP is going to get you into a
regime where you know your the time you
spend doing computation is higher than
the time you spend doing communication,
right? Right? So if your batch size is
big enough, you can just get away with
FSTP. Right? So this is kind of a cool
illustration of this idea of, you know,
why would you mix these? When would you
mix these? Why is batch size a resource?
Hopefully this kind of shows you in a
very visual way uh what this is. Okay.
Um and so when you put these all
together, you end up with what people
call 3D or 4D parallelism. Um I think
I've heard the term 5D parallelism
recently. Um I wasn't quite sure what
the what the fifth dimension was yet.
I'll have to to read up on that. Um, but
now you can put it all together, right?
The different dimensions of parallelism.
And this is a really simple rule of
thumb. Um, I originally sort of looked
it up and put this together last year,
but turns out it's still the same this
year. So you can sort of follow this uh
now. So the first thing you have to do
is you have to fit your model and your
activations in memory, right? If you
don't do that, you just cannot train. So
this is a requirement, right? So until
your model fits in memory, we have to
split up our model. So we're going to do
tensor parallelism and we know that up
to the number of GPUs per machine that's
very efficient that's very fast. So
we're going to do tensor parallel up to
that point. Now after that depending on
things like your desire to deal with
pipeline parallel and or your bandwidth
uh constraints you're either going to
use 03 or pipeline parallel across the
machines right until you can fit your
model in memory. Now after that point
well until you sort of run out of GPUs
you can now run the whole thing and your
only goal is to increase the amount of
total flops that you have on hand. So
you're going to scale the rest of the
way with data parallel because data
parallel is it works well on um low
bandwidth communication channels and it
is very simple right and so that's going
to give you a way of sort of using all
of your GPUs. Now if your batch size is
really small then there is a way of uh
trading um batch sizes for better
communication efficiency like if you
haven't consumed all of your batch sizes
of resource what you can do is you can
use gradient accumulation um on your
devices right and that'll let you
basically have effectively larger um uh
batch sizes even if you're memory
constraint and that will let you trade
your batch size for better communication
efficiency since you're synchronizing
less often um across machines. Okay,
simple rule of thumb. This will let you
train models with reasonable efficiency
um no matter what you're doing. Um and
so to sort of make this concrete, I'll
talk through a few examples at the very
end here. Um I'll flash through both
this really lovely paper um back in 2021
um from Megatron LM. Basically showing
you exactly these things um in pictures
and also a lot of ablations as well as
um uh some of the models from last year.
So this is a big table of how they
trained models uh going from 1.7 billion
parameters to 1 trillion parameters. Um
and they get great utilization on all of
these, right? You see percentage of
theoretical peak flops that they get and
it ranges from 40 to 52%. It's pretty
good, right? And so you can see tensor
parallel starts at one and then they
eventually go up to 8 and then it caps
out at 8, right? And they so they're
using tensor parallelism first and then
pipeline parallel stays at one but once
the models get big enough you know they
can't fit these big models. So t
pipeline parallel has to increase in
order to kind of comp in order to
compensate and then the data parallel
size basically starts out as big as
possible and then slowly kind of goes
down right because you know as we
increase the amount of pipeline parallel
this is now consuming in some sense the
batch sizes um and so you can't have
effectively as big of a batch size um if
they're being used in some sense for
pipeline
parallel okay so um careful 3D paralle
ISM is going to give you sort of linear
gains um in uh aggregate flops. So you
see um if you do uh careful 3D
parallelism, you see sort of very flat
uh overall achieved flops per GPU, which
is giving you, you know, if you add more
GPUs, linear scaling in the total
aggregate throughput. That's great. Um
tensor parallel 8 is often optimal. Um
you see this is the pipeline parallel
size and the tensor parallel size you
see going to 88 with a batch size of 30
or sorry batch size of 128 is optimal
even if you have a smaller batch size
you know tensor parallel size of eight
remains uh optimal and activation
recomputation um enables larger batch
sizes and remember that you know larger
batches can in turn help you sort of
mask overhead for pipeline parallel. So
activation recomputation even though
it's more flops can pay for itself,
right? We've seen that story play out
already um in uh flash attention. All
right. So the last part of this is
recent language models like what do they
do? So you know I've gone through a few
papers to look at examples of what
people's parallelization strategy is. Um
uh OMO uh in the DOMA paper they do FSDP
for 7 billion parameter model. um
deepseeek uh the the first paper does
zero stage one with tensor sequence and
pipeline parallel. This is you know the
the vanilla thing that I that I told
you. Um V3 actually does something
slightly different. They do 16 way
pipeline parallel um 64-way expert
parallel which is kind of like tensor
parallel. Um and then zero stage one for
their data parallelism
strategy. E which is another Chinese
model does once again zero stage one
tensor and pipeline parallel. Um, and e-
lightning because they're doing replaces
tensor parallelism with expert uh
parallelism. The final thing, if you're
interested in kind of state-of-the-art,
you know, distributed training with lots
of details, um, Llama 3's report is
actually really interesting to read.
They have a lot of detail about how they
do their networking, what sort of things
happen. Um, and you see sort of once
again the kinds of things I said before.
You see a tensor parallel of eight. Um
you see um CP or this is context
parallel. This is only relevant for long
context training which is this very last
step. So you can ignore that. Um you got
pipeline parallel and data parallel
happening um in these sort of first two
uh phases. You can also even ignore the
first stage here because that's kind of
the small batch size training that they
did in order to be stable. And if you
look at kind of their their rationale
for how they do their parallelism
strategy, you see exactly what I had
said before of basically all right you
want to do TP CP pipeline parallel and
DP in that order in terms of the amount
of bandwidth that you need where data
parallel can tolerate these like long
network latencies because you can do the
sort of asynchronous fetching of sharded
model weights, right? And so they're
using kind of the strategy that I told
you in order to train some of the
biggest models. Um the funny side note
about llama 3 um and you may have heard
this sort of in sort of not rumors but
sort of casual conversation with your
friends um is you know there's lots of
GPU failures when you train models at a
huge scale right um they had 148
interruptions from faulty GPUs um
totaling about 30% of the total
interruptions that they had they had
things like you know unplanned
maintenance of machines and that was 32
uh different things you know 32
instances of interruptions for their
training and so when you're training a
model this big, you know, I've talked
about the algorithms, but you also need
kind of fault tolerant architectures to
be able to deal with these kinds of
things. Um, and I've also heard, you
know, various stories of people saying
the even scarier thing is not actually
explicit model failures, but actually
data corruption. Like GPUs can silently
fail on you and give you garbage data,
completely ruining your run. Okay. Um,
and then the last one example is for GMA
2. And I wanted to end on this because
this is a TPU example. um you know they
do 03 which is roughly FSTP and then
they do model parallelism and data
parallelism right and so here you know
as I said before the sort of TPUs allows
them to sort of stretch model
parallelism a little bit further okay so
putting it all together um scaling
beyond a certain point is going to
require sort of multiGPU multi-node
parallelism there's no single solution
right so you want to combine all three
approaches to sort of leverage strength
and then there's simple and
interpretable rules of thumb for how you
might execute this parallelism in
practice
Right. Thank you.