So this is the second lecture on data.
In the last lecture we talked about
different data sets that were used to
train various language models. We sort
of did a historical overview from the
data sets that were used to train bird
all the way up to homo and everything in
between. And one of the things I wanted
to emphasize is that data doesn't just
fall from the sky. It exists often in
live services. They have to be
explicitly crawled or dumped and then
there's a bunch of processing that has
to happen and the processing involves
converting the raw HTML to text doing
all sorts of quality and language and
toxicity filtering, dduplication and so
on so forth. So in this lecture I would
like to take a deep dive into some of
the mechanics on how quality filtering
and dduplication work in particular. So
first we're going to look at different
algorithms for filtering which uh mostly
are model based. So you train a
classifier or train some sort of model
to filter. Then we're going to show that
this primitive can be used for all sorts
of different types of filtering. And
then finally we're going to look at some
algorithms for uh dduplication. Um so
this lecture will be a little bit
different in that it's going to focus a
lot on sort of classical big data
processing algorithms and there'll be
some fun math uh in there for some of
you.
Okay. So let's get started with
filtering algorithms. So the basic high
level picture here is that you're given
some target data
and which you don't have very much of
it. Suppose it's data that's high
quality and you have a lot of raw data.
So imagine this is common crawl and your
goal is you want to find a subset of
that raw data. It's called it t prime
which is similar to t. Okay. So this is
a pattern that you should kind of
recognize in basically any sort of
filtering uh pipeline.
Um and what do you want for this
filtering algorithm? You want it
obviously to generalize from t, right?
You don't want you already have t so
there's no point in getting exactly the
same data t. So there's has to be some
generalization
and also has to be extremely fast. So
you have to run it on all of the web for
example. So if this is running a huge
model that's going to be um might be as
expensive as training. So you don't
definitely don't want that otherwise you
might as well train.
So we're going to look at three
different ways that you can um implement
this highle abstract primitive.
Um so we'll start with training an
engram model. So this is something that
uh came up in the last lecture. So you
can train an engram model with canern
smoothing. Um you can use other forms of
smoothing but caner has sort of been
inherited from the you know you know
engram kind of modeling. um um
statistical language processing era um
and there's a particular implementation
that people tend to use in this uh space
called CANLM which is open source
originally developed for machine
translation um which implements can
conernnite smoothing. So you can go and
read about um it's it's it's pretty
interesting but um we're not going to
talk too much about the details here. Um
so this happens to be very popular in
data filtering. Uh there's no particular
reason has to be this one, but this is
just what people use. Um and the nice
thing about engram modeling is it's very
simple.
When I say fitting a model, you you
should think of this as just counting
the number of engrams and then
normalizing.
Okay, so just to go into a little bit of
depth here. So it's your starting point
is maximum likelihood estimation of
language models. So you have a corpus of
text and you want to estimate
conditional probabilities like p of in
given the last n minus one words the cat
and what you do is you count the number
of n grams
um and then divide it by the number of
you know the um n minus one grams of the
conditioning context. Okay so this is
you know very very easy um in principle.
Now implementing this efficiently is uh
takes a bit of work. Um but the main
problem is that there's sparse counts.
So many of the engrams are exactly show
up zero times even though they're very
reasonable especially when n grows. Um
and this was the whole point why engram
models couldn't really be scaled
appropriately because you hit the curse
of dimensionality.
So to mitigate this um you know some
people devised uh you know cannon
smoothing to handle unseen grams and
there's more details on this but roughly
this says well maybe if I don't have
enough data to support this count I can
sort of use a lower order engram. So you
know remove one word from the context
and count the number of times in uh
appears given cat um and then try to
either interpolate or back off um to
that. Um
okay so that's all I'll say about how
engram you know modeling works. Um I
think even in this era of neural
language model you know it's good to
know that how engram models work. So um
let's download
um the engram. So this is a a model
that's been trained on Wikipedia. I'm
just going to download it. Um and then
let's uh punch some sentences through.
So this sentence is Sanford University
was found in 1885.
Um this is actually a excerpt taken from
Wikipedia. So it should be you know
reasonable. Um and if you compute um the
the probability so you first compute the
log prop and then you compute the
perplexity by this uh normalization
um then you get you know 87 okay so you
know it's it's some number um and then
here's another example um you know this
is taken from the CS336 you know website
um so let's see how well it does So this
is a higher perplexity means that it's
less likely. Okay, kind of makes sense
because this stuff doesn't really
probably show up in Wikipedia. It's not
in, you know, it's not abnormally high
because it's still fairly good
well-formed English and many engrams
there, um, I think show up in Wikipedia
as well. Um, what about ESDF? This is
just gibberish. This gets assigned
higher perplexity.
Um and then there's the the the so this
should get assigned pretty high
perplexity but um for some reason this
particular engram assigns a a pretty low
perplexity. So you know it's an engram
model so it's not particularly clever or
good. Um but you know you don't need to
be the best model. You're just doing
data filtering to create a model. So
this can be very crude and and fast. So,
CCNET, which is um a paper out of um you
know, I guess it was Facebook back then.
Um uh they which we talked about last
time. Um
they um basically did uh this and
actually
okay that's fine. Um so they basically
looked at uh paragraphs of of text um uh
and those were the items they sorted the
paragraphs by increasing perplexity and
just kept the top 1/3 um and this is
what they used to create the first llama
um data set. Okay so this is you know
horistic but you know kind of you know
if you had to write down something
really quickly and this kind of makes
sense. Okay. So, NASA language modeling
is fast uh but um it's crude.
All right. Um
I feel like there was some
content that was I meant to go through
that's missing. Oh well, maybe it got
deleted. Um all right. So that's you can
fit an engram model um to your target
data and then you can use that to score
the raw data and choose the top uh
scoring documents. Another thing you can
do is fastex and this is in some ways
more uh you know popular um this is also
from you know uh Facebook they released
a lot of open source uh you know tools
um although klm I think was um yeah
created before before that um so here
they develop it for text classification
um and they this paper I mean this is
2016 so a lot of people were developing
all sorts of fancy neural models and
they said show that well this actually
almost linear classifier worked as well
and was much faster. Um so that's why
the software package actually became
very uh popular. So um the motivation
here um was that if you're doing let's
say bag of words classification. So you
have a a sentence of length L your vocab
size is V and you want to classify into
64 classes. Then immediately you have to
define this um V by K matrix um which if
V and K are both large then this gets uh
pretty big and you get into sparsity
issues um and the way it would work is
that you take your um your documents and
then you just do linear classification.
So that's that's fairly you know
straightforward. So the problem is that
the number of parameters is huge. So
fastex says, well, let me just do a a
linear um basically basically
dimensionality reduction. So instead,
I'm going to map my vocab space into a
hidden dimension which is smaller than k
um possibly smaller than k 16. And then
I'm going to classify from h. So notice
that there's when when you look at the
prediction the forward pass there's no
nonlinearity it's just a linear
classifier you can also think about as a
matrix factorization um if you want and
the number of parameters is greatly you
know reduced um so the implication I
think is uh you know reasonably um you
know optimized it's parallelized and
they use asynchronous SGD
um and um so here's um okay so The the
question is this is bag of words. Um and
you know we want to not just look at
words but we want to look at engrams. So
this uh paper also you know extends to
engrams in a fairly simple way. So you
take a sentence and you get some chop it
up into new engrams. Um and here the
problem is that the number of biograms
can get um you know quite large and
actually can be un unbounded. Right? So
remember when we talked about tokenizers
if you just chop up into words you're
going to get you know you don't know how
many words there are. So the simple
thing is that you just do hashing. So
you define some number of bins maybe 10
million but in this example eight and
then you just um you just hash every
biogram um into that. So you these the
cat maps to two and and cat in maps to
one and so on. Okay. So of course there
might be some
um collisions but you know you just live
with that.
Um I mean in some sense the the opt when
you minimize the loss collisions are
sort of accounted for. If there's like
two um words that have nothing to do
with each other then the weight is going
to somehow represent the maybe the
average of the two. And also note that
often we use fast
fast text classification with k equals2
classes. Is this document good or is it
bad? And in that case uh this is just
normal ba basically um binary
classification linear classification.
Okay. So of course it doesn't take too
much imagination to imagine well if you
can do linear classification you can use
fancier models such as bird or even
llama. The only thing is that it's going
to be slower and therefore you run into
this trade-off where if you use a giant
model to do classification, maybe you
should use those flops to actually just
train the model. So that's the only uh
concern because you know the web is very
large and remember you were filtering
the web down quite a bit. So you're
going to spend a lot of um compute on
let's say you're filtering like down to
1% of the web, right? So that means um
you know you have your classifier that
amount of compute you spend has to be a
hundth of you know taking a forward pass
through the data set.
Okay. So the final method I'm going to
talk about is this thing called data
selection for um language models using
importance resampling.
Um and here are the basic ideas that you
have your R it's a raw data set you have
your uh you know uh target data and then
I'm going to build an importance weight
estimator um which is um the analog of
um the language engram model or the fast
text classifier and then I'm going to
use that to um get a bunch of um
documents. Okay. So first just a kind of
a quick refresher of importance um
resampling I guess um so you have um
this shows up in many contexts like you
know particle filtering um um and you
know Monte Carlo methods um so you have
a target distribution so it's a
distribution not a data set where you
want to ideally draw samples from this
but you only have a proposal
distribution Q where you can draw
samples so for example if you have a
vocab of 0 1 2 3 2 3 um let's say this
is your target distribution and your
proposal distribution is uh is this.
Now what you do is uh you sample from Q
because that's the only thing you can
sample from. So let's say you get a
bunch of samples.
Okay. Um so notice that um Q has a lot
of more mass on zero. So you get a lot
of more zeros. Um and then what you're
going to do is you compute weights over
your samples by looking at this
importance um you know ratio P over Q.
So you're trying to make up for the fact
I sample from Q so I want to divide that
out or I really want P and um you
normalize
and get you you get a distribution
um over your your samples. And now you
resample
um and you uh that sort of balances out
the distribution. So now you see that
there's more threes because P had more
probability distribution on mass on
three.
Okay. So this is a fairly elementary um
but uh it's a building block. Now then
now we go to um how we do data
selection. So we have a target data set
not a distribution. And we have a data
set which is small and we also have this
um raw data set which we're going to
call the proposal data set dq which is
large. So
um you could let's just fit a
distribution p to dp fit a distribution
q to dq and door do the importance
resampling um that I we talked about
just uh you know two minutes ago.
Now the main problem is that um DP is
really small. Remember target
distributions is high quality data. You
don't have that much of it which is the
whole point. You're trying to get more
of it. So you don't have that much of it
and it's too small to estimate a good
model. So again this the the idea is you
just use hash engram. So this is
something that we already saw with fast
text as well. you uh you know take
whatever text you have and then you
essentially okay so you basically hash
all the um we're doing unograms for now
so you hash each unogram so and you um
um you basically count the number
estimate the probability of every um
hashed engram okay so in this case um
this the cat and the hat hashes to this.
Notice that there's some hash collisions
the and the hat hatch into the same
value but you know whatever this is all
crude um and then you just estimate the
probability of each of these um the
probabilities.
Okay. So then to evaluate the
probability of a new text um you
um you hash
um the new text and you multiply the
probabilities together. Okay, so I got a
little bit unlucky and the probability
is gets zeroed out. You can do some
smoothing if you want. So it turns out
in Python hash is non deterministic. So
every time I run this I'm going to get
something something else.
Um and the paper shows that this indeed
uh helps a bit. The gains are not you
know super massive but you know compared
to doing fast text which is the heristic
classification um the gains on the glue
benchmark using bird style models um
there is some um lift and the the
comparison with fastex. So the main idea
here is that modeling a whole
distribution is in some sense a more
principled approach right because you
want to sample data from um your
distribution and you have a different
distribution Q and now you're trying to
essentially compensate um and so this
could be better for you know diversity
because you're trying to match the
distribution whereas fast text you're
essentially trying to classify whether
something is is in the distribution or
not and it doesn't have any guarantees
about matching the distribution. Um
okay but it's it's also fast like fast
text and um both can be improved by
having better um models. So instead of
using linear models based on engrams you
can increase n you can um use uh neural
approaches as well.
Okay, so just to wrap up this uh part um
so we look at engram models, linear
classifiers and importance resampling.
Um but the general framework I think is
uh is something that maybe worth taking
away which is that the setup given a
target data set and a raw data set find
a subset that's similar to the target
and all these methods have the basic
recipe which is estimate some sort of
model based on the raw data and the
target data set which gives you a
scoring function and then keep examples
in the raw data set based on that
scoring function. usually high scores
are kept. So just to walk through this
in the KLM case um you know the score is
simply the probability
um of or I guess you know maybe the
perplexity um if you want normalized by
the number of tokens under the target.
Okay so R is not used here and then you
keep examples with score greater than
threshold.
Um and you can you can um you know
randomize a little bit around the
threshold if you if you want. So you can
also use a discriminative classifier
where the score is what's the
probability that this example came from
the target as opposed to the raw data
set and then you keep examples where the
score is of greater than some threshold.
And then importance resampling says the
score is the ratio of you know two
generative models which could be engram
models in this in this case. Um p of uh
you know the target distribution over
the raw distribution and to use a score
um this is really the importance weights
you resample with probability
proportional to that.
Okay, so at a high level all of them are
doing essentially the same thing. You
have you fit some sort of distribution
that tells you what looks like target as
opposed to raw and then you apply that
to the raw data set.
Okay. Uh maybe I'll pause here in case
there's any questions.
Yeah. So um on sort of like a high level
philosophical
thing we have an idea of what good data
is but we've kind of not talked about
what that's actually like
what what like a good document looks
like. So what this is doing is like
making sure that the words fit next to
each other when you have like another
like that you know one comes after the
other but it doesn't ensure that they it
makes any sense on like a larger level
or if you want that you just increase
the N and the engram. Yeah. Yeah. So the
question seems I think is that if you're
using an engram model, it's only looking
at local contexts and maybe that's not
great for assessing quality because if
you shuffle everything around, it still
looks good to the engram model. So
there's definitely um that danger that
it's very easy to adversarily game,
right? If you can construct you can
definitely construct um examples that
the engram model thinks is high. I mean
I showed you one the the happens to be
you know pretty high. Um but somehow on
average um you know you're doing okay
and in some sense maybe if a document
looks like grammatical English and it
looks like news or you know some
scientific paper um all you want to make
sure is that that model assigns high
probability to that. If you get some,
you know, bad examples, it's not the the
end of the the world. Yeah. So, we
should think about these as just like
filtering out like true nonsense web
pages that you show. Yeah, I would say
this is uh filtering out true nonsense
is I think a good way to to look at it.
As I go through some examples, I think
maybe it'll become a bit clearer that um
this is these classifiers are not just
used for quality and for some of the
other use cases. I think it's much more
maybe compelling why it should work.
Okay. So, um
so the same data filtering machinery can
be used on different tasks. So, I'm
going to talk about language
identification, quality filtering, and
toxicity filtering. So, language
identification. Um, the idea is that you
want to find text of a specific
language. Maybe it's English, maybe it's
Japanese. Um, and you could ask, well,
you know, um, you could just train on
all the languages. Why don't you do
that? Um, the problem is that it's, um,
can often be difficult to, um, you know,
do the curation and processing of high
quality data in a given language. And
and there's also, you know, the the
problem that if you train, let's say you
only care about, you know, one language.
Now, if you have data from all the other
languages, you're going to be spending
less compute and tokens on any given
languages on the given language. Um, so
this was a and that could hurt your
performance in that language. For
example, you know, Bloom, which was
trained in about 20 uh 22, I believe, um
was only trained on 30% English. Um and
as a result, the English performance
maybe was not as good as it could have
been. It was strong on other languages.
So there in a compute limited, you know,
regime, you're definitely at risk of um
compromising the quality of the of of
the language you care about. Now that
said, if you have enough capacity and
you're training huge models, then you
can definitely train multilingual models
and there's could be even positive
transfer between languages. So all the
kind of frontier models are are trained
on um uh heavily multilingual sometimes
even hundreds of lang like 100 plus
languages.
Um so
you know one simple way to do this is
fast text is um a toolkit for training
simple classifiers. It also comes with
some off-the-shelf um models and one of
the ones that typically gets used is
they have a language identification
um um model and this is just
off-the-shelf classifier. It supports a
lot of different languages and and it
was trained on um basically multilingual
sites including Wikipedia which has a
lot of different languages as
translation sites um and you know for
some reason Southeast European news. Um
so DOMA uses this um they basically run
the fast text classifier and keep pages
with English uh probability greater than
0.5.
you know. Um so let's try it out. So
there's this model um language ID that
you can just and download. Um and then
let's see how well it does. Um so the
quick fox jumps over the uh lazy dog.
Let's see where are the predictions. Um
okay. I don't know why. Okay, there we
go. So um
okay so this says English this is the
label English and the probability of
English is 71. Okay so I mean you would
have guessed it would be higher. It
looks pretty English to me. Um if you
duplicate the the sentence the
probability isn't you know changing
which is good. Um it you know saying the
same thing doesn't make it more English.
Um um there's some informal English. Um
which this is kind of weird. This is I
guess more English than the quick round
fox. Um German um actually gets
classified fairly uh oh sorry this is uh
German now. The label is German. Okay.
That is German. Um math gets classified
pretty weakly as as English. Um code um
does is um highest is like Russian. Um,
this is hello is apparently, you know,
Italian. This is French. Bonjour. Um,
that's that's good. Um, and this is, I
guess, a tricky one where I put in some
Spanish and also some English. And I
guess I favor the the Spanish in this
case. Okay. So, this gives you a sense.
I mean, it's always good to play with
these classifiers, right? Because just
because it's a classifier you can
download and everyone uses doesn't mean
it like works all the time. Um, so I
think obviously for short sentences, um,
it's less reliable because there's just
less information about what's happening.
Low resource languages is tough. Um,
there's a worry that for things that
don't really or dialects of English, um,
this could, um, be viewed as not
English. Um, I think if you want to
distinguish between similar languages,
that's also can be easily confused. and
code switching. I don't even know what
ground truth is, but it'll do hopefully
one of the uh languages.
Um so just talk through one case study
open web math was this uh this paper um
from two years ago. Um and the goal here
is to curate a large corpus of
mathematical text where here I'm saying
that you know let's assume that math is
a as a language. Um so first they use
some rules to filter then they train
canlam on this uh large data set of
proofs called proof pile and kept it if
the perplexity was below some threshold
and they they trained this fastest
classifier which we talked about to
predict mathematical writing. Um this is
a kind of hacky but um the they set the
threshold of a classifier if it's um
identified as math based on rules to be
relatively low and if it's not
identified as math according to rules
it's um it's uh needs to be higher. Um
and as a result they produced 15 billion
tokens and they trained some models that
do better that models that were trained
on 20 times more data that weren't
really specialized. So this is kind of
one of um nice examples of the the
utility of data filtering, right? You
could train on all this data, but if you
care about let's say a particular domain
like math, you can just go out and get
more of it and target that data set. And
if you train on that, you can be much
more data efficient.
Okay, so let's talk about quality
filtering. So quality filtering
obviously is something that is um
doesn't really I mean it's a catch-all
for um a bunch of things and what is
quality um so remember that some papers
uh explicitly don't use modelbased
quality filtering um but more recent
papers have just kind of given in and
say well um I mean it just works a lot
better um um so GBD3 um we talked a
little bit about this last time trained
a quality classifier by taking positive
samples from the highquality sources
that they had or rather the non-common
crawl sources they had and negatives are
just common crawl. They train a linear
classifier
um and keep documents stochcastically
based on this this score which is
something that just turns numbers um
basically sort of sharpens the you know
the the threshold um and uh the llama
first llama paper um they use pages
referenced by Wikipedia so not Wikipedia
as positives negatives are just sampled
from common crawl and then they keep
documents that are classified positive.
I don't think there was actually
sampling in that which is interesting.
Um 51 was another paper that um their
philosophy was kind of you know
interesting. Um they really wanted high
quality data that looked like textbooks
and they wanted to train a very small
model. Um so they trained on synthetic
data but also filter data. So for the
filter data what they did is they took
the Python subset of the stack. Remember
the stack is this pre-processed data set
coming from GitHub of code and then they
defined a prompt which effectively asked
um GP4 to determine the educational
value for a student whose goal is to
learn basic coding concepts and then
they prompted GP4 and classified 100k
um documents from this Python subset and
that became the positive examples. They
train a random forest classifier on
these examples where the embeddings fed
into a random classifier were from some
pre-trained cogen model and then they
selected data from R that is classified
by the um you know classifier. So they
run the classifier then over all of our
and then get um that data. So this is
kind of interesting because there is a
random force classifier and in this case
where does t come from? Well t doesn't
exist ap t comes from prompting gpd4
with some prompt. Okay, so this is
something that you'll see more
increasingly as the models get better is
that instead of you know looking at
sources like well maybe books one is
great or maybe web Wikipedia is great.
Um now if you have a good model you can
just ask the model to um for the type of
data you want. maybe I want more
chemistry data or I want more
mathematical data that you know does a
lot of proofs or elementary math or
something and you just let the language
model um uh a fairly sophisticated
language model give you t and now once
you have t you turn the recipe that
we've been talking about so far
so the f1 results um again looks uh good
so they had a baseline where they just
took the python subset of a stack which
was this R and the performance on human
eval which is a coding data set was only
12% after 96k steps of training and then
they trained the exact same model
architecture on this new fancy data set
and it was already at 17 after 36 um so
they declared success.
Okay, so these are some examples of of
uh quality filtering. Um any questions
about quality filtering?
Yeah.
LM and not using like
Yeah. So the the the point is that you
can why can you get away with um using
GP4 here because you're using it only on
um to create a thousand 100k
examples
um and to create and then using that to
distill a classifier which is much
faster and the 100k is much less than
the size of R which is you know hundreds
of tens or hundreds of millions Don't
worry.
Okay. So, let's talk a bit about
toxicity filtering. Um,
so I'm going to talk about how the DOMA
paper um does toxicity filtering. So,
there's this data set called Jigsaw
toxic comments. Um and this came out of
a project where they were trying to help
people have better discussions online.
So they buil wanted to build a
classifier that could um identify when
there was problematic content. So they
took the data uh comments on the
Wikipedia talk pages and had annotators
annotate them with you know toxic severe
toxic obscene threat insult ID hate. Um
and so the Dolma folks trained two
fastex classifiers. one um which is
basically um uh you know correspond to
hate and the other one is correspond to
NSFW
um and so here's some examples of the
you know of the you know data set um so
let's download the model um and try it
out. So the first example
um you know are you threatening me for
dispute neutrality? This gets classified
as um safe for work um because I mean it
seems fine. Um and the second one is
flagged as NSFW
um
you know and these sentences are both uh
fine. Okay. So, just give you a a sense,
you know, I don't want to show too many
of these examples, but um you get the
idea. You can play it on with your own
time.
Um okay, so that's all I'll say about uh
filtering.
So, now let's talk about dduplication.
So, there's two types of duplicates.
Exact uh duplicates. And the thing to
realize is that the web actually just
inherently has a lot of exact duplicates
based on u mirroring. So if you just
look at project Gutenberg um
you know you'll see that you know the
same exact site gets mirrored on a bunch
of different URLs. So if you're just
crawling as common crawl does um it has
no way knowing that these are mirrors.
It just get you the exact same content.
Um and then there's neoduplicates which
is basically the same text that differ
by a few tokens. And we're going to show
you algorithms that deal with um you
know both. So neoduplicates
um when does this happen? Well, you have
terms of service and licenses like the
MIT license. This thing shows up I don't
know how many times on the web. It's
just copy and pasted everywhere. Uh
maybe there's even I don't know maybe
people take it and actually change some
things or they mess up copy and pasting
and um remove a comma or something. Um
that's all possible. Um and then there's
uh cases if you look at these these data
sets um you know near duplicates are it
just gives you an idea of what new
duplicates might look like. Um,
sometimes you have this article where
like someone's just seemed to have
paraphrased best actor in a negative
role for most impactful character, but
everything else seems the same. Um, this
is just like missing a a comma here. Not
really sure how where that comma went
off to, but um, you know, there could be
like just annotator or processing
errors. Um, and then this one's kind of
interesting. I mean there's clearly this
very uh kind of ad um like a text which
um they just replace Canada with USA um
and some other flight. So this probably
is generated from some sort of template
system where they slotted in entities.
Um so you know these narrow duplicates
are obviously different but obviously if
you train on tons of um you know this
once you have this document this one
doesn't give you that much value. Let's
just put it that way. Um so in extreme
case so if you look at C4 uh remember C4
was filtered based on the set of rules
that looked for sentences that looked
like English. um you'll see this um
sentence which is indeed English that
shows up an astonishing 61,000 times and
for whatever reason if you actually
trace down where this comes from um not
the MIT license oh I have to what okay
do I should I accept these cookies okay
fine um there's this like random product
from Amazon that has graffiti mass
drawings And um you know there's this
text and apparently this is for whatever
reason I you know I don't even know how
there's 61,000 copies of this but that's
that's what it is. And and so the idea
is that this text isn't necessarily bad
right? It's perfectly good English but
you don't want to like take 61,000
epochs over this. I mean it's just you
know kind of pointless. So dduplication
is sort of complementaryary to quality
filtering. Quality filtering says this
piece of data I don't want to ever train
on it. Dduplication says well this is
might be fine but I only want a small
number of these rather than 61,000 uh
copies.
So there's been work uh showing that
dduplication makes language models
better. Um the first most obvious thing
is that you can train more efficiently,
right? Right? Duplication reduces the
number of tokens and if you haven't
thrown away information then you um can
save a lot of uh effort and then the
second is that um you can also avoid
memorization. So we haven't really
talked about this but language models
trained on data can memorize that data
which is bad for um you know copyright
or privacy reasons because it can
regurgitate the training set and
dduplication is one tool. It's not
definitely not perfect, but it can help
mitigate uh some of these um risks.
Um okay, so here's how to think about
dduplication in terms of design space.
So first you have to think about what is
the unit that you're dduplicating? What
is an item? Is it a sentence? Is it a
paragraph? Is it a document? The second
question is how do you match? Do you
what is considered a duplicate? Is it
exact match? Is it a fraction of common
sub items? Um and then the final thing
is what action uh do you take? Do you
remove all the instances or do you
remove all but one?
Okay. So, so the key challenge and this
is a um algorithmic challenge is that
fundamentally dduplication is about
comparing items to other items. Right?
Quality classification. You can take an
item, you can classify it as high
quality or not. Dduplication is
fundamentally a parise thing. And
remember, these data sets are large. So
you can't if you're trying to do
something quadratic, that's kind of a
no-go. So you need some sort of linear
time algorithm to scale um but still do
something that's pair-wise.
Um so the building block of all this is
hash functions. So hash functions just
as a review is a function that maps an
item which could be a sentence could be
a document to a hash value which is an
integer or string and the value is much
smaller than item and the thing that's
relevant about hash functions is that
you could potentially get hash
collisions. So which means that you have
two distinct items that map to the same
hash value. So in general if you've I'm
sure you've all I guess all of you have
used dictionaries or hashts hash
collisions are generally bad but later
we'll see that they're actually can be
good in some limited doses.
U there's many types of hash functions
um which tradeoff between efficiency and
collision resistance which means uh
don't collide. There's cryptographic
hash functions which are used for
security sensitive applications like in
in Bitcoin. You really don't want
collisions because otherwise that means
someone might steal your um your money
or it could compromise um things. And
then there's things where um but these
are slow um but then there's hash
functions which are generally used for
hash tables that are not collision
resistant but you know fast. And so
we're generally going to go with the
latter category um because we want
things to be fast and um this the we're
not doing cryptography here.
Okay. So we're going to use this thing
called murmur hash which takes strings
and returns you know values but you can
use a bunch of other hashes as well. Um
okay so let's start with exact
dduplication. So here's a simple
example. the item is just a string and I
want exact match and I want to remove
all but one. So here's a bunch of items.
Um and what I'm going to first do is uh
compute um a mapping from hash value to
the list of items with that hash. Um so
and then once I have that I keep one
item from each uh group. So each group
correspond to a hash value. Um and in
the case of exact dup um exact match um
assuming there's no hash collisions then
um you basically do a exact ddup. So
hello shows up twice here and then now
it shows up once and of course hello
uppercase exclamation point is just a
completely distinct item because we're
doing exact.
So this the nice thing is that this is
very you know simple. It's clear what
you're doing. It's high precision, so
you're never gonna throw away anything
that you didn't um uh that you didn't
need or you needed. Um but the con is
that you it doesn't work for near
duplicates.
Um and the other thing is that's nice is
that you know this is very simple to
implement. We kind of wrote this in a
map reduce way and you can scale it and
paralyze it fairly easily.
And this is something that uh C4 uses
actually to prepare their data set. So
their unit is of dduplication is three
sentence spans. They use exact match and
they remove all all but one. Um so one
thing that is always kind of bothered me
but I know no one else seems to care is
uh that um when you you're looking at
three sentence spans, right? So you have
this document and then you have this
three sentence span um and if it's
marked as a duplicate you're just going
to you know you know do surgery and take
that those sentences out and so the
resulting document might not even be
coherent but then people say you know
who cares and move on.
Um okay so there's another um way to do
uh dduplication that is less map
reduceuced but more kind of like hasht I
think the you know bloom filters are you
know some of you might have seen but
just uh just to go through it because I
think it's kind of a cool method um so
this is you know efficient and um it's
approximate so you get it's more
efficient but it's um you know obviously
It's not always doing the exact thing
but you know we're we're very have not
we we are not you know being too picky
here. Okay. So it's uh the nice thing is
a very memory efficient. Um you can
update it but you can't delete. Um and
it's it's basically a representation of
set where if you ask for set membership
and it returns no then it's definitely a
no. But if it's returns yes then you
know most likely if you set your
hyperparameters right it's yes but you
know there's a small probability that
you have
of of no like you have a false positive
um and then you can you know set your uh
your parameters to drive down the false
positive rate if you like. Okay so just
to uh walk through what this looks like.
So suppose you have five items, the cat
and the hat. And um later we'll test out
with is some items that don't show up in
the the set. Um the first thing is
you're going to define a hash function
that maps to m bins. m is going to be
eight here. Um so to build the bloom
filter um we're going to do you know
something fairly simple. you just um
you make uh you know a bit array um with
a number of bins and then go through
every item hash it the hashes to two so
I update the second item um cat hashes
to seven update the seventh item in the
hat okay so I just um you know populate
this bit array and the bit array I don't
keep track of the item so I have no idea
if I have a false positive or not um
Okay, so let's just sanity check that um
every item that I put in is actually in
the item. So to query it, you just uh
compute whether that item um hashed is
in the table. Um and indeed everything
should pass. Um and now
um let's look at the nonite items and
see um how they fare. And you'll see
that you know some of the non items you
get a zero which is what you want. Um
but some of the non items the bloom
feather says oh actually it's in the in
the set. So the number of mistakes here
is is four. And if you compute the false
positive rate which is the number of
mistakes over the total number of times
um the procedure produced um you know a
a positive then the false positive rate
is in this case you know 444 which is
pretty bad. Um now of course this is a
bin 8 and if the bin were to grow then
this would get better. In fact it grows
the error probability is one over the
number of bins. Okay. So, but you look
at this and say, well, that's not really
good because if I want the error
probability to be, you know, um 10 to
the minus 10, then I need a lot of bins
and that's not going to hurt on memory.
So, there's a more clever solution here,
which is to use more hash functions.
Okay, so let's say I use two hash
functions and I'm going to essentially I
still have the same, you know, bit
array, but for every item now I'm going
to
use hash it twice. So the under seed
zero gets hashed to two. I'm going to
pop it in. And then um the with seed one
is going to hash to five. So I'm going
to pop it in there. So every item gets
hashed into K not necessarily distinct
but hey K slots. So then I go through
the cat and then I fill up this um you
know table.
Okay. So now I um when I do the querying
I take an element and I going to return
one if the table set was set to one for
all K hash functions.
Okay. because if I put it in, I have to
set K bits. And so if I'm testing, I
need to check the K locations and um
check that they were all set.
Um
so indeed all of those pass. And now
let's look at the
um
so the number of um you know mistakes
now is three um and the false positive
rate um decreased. So, you know, that's
great. So, of course, this is a toy
example, but you know, you can really
drive down the false positive rate with
um modest memory um you know, uh spend.
Okay, maybe I'll uh pause there before I
go to um analyzing this a bit more, you
know, formally.
Okay, so let's let's think about what
happens more generally. Um,
so let's say we have a thousand bins.
Um, we have 10 cache functions and we're
going to hash um 100 items. The question
is, you know, what is the false positive
rate? And the way to think about this is
that I'm going to consider a test input
that's not in the set um that would is
going to hash into a particular location
like I. Okay. And then I'm going to so
um I'm going to now consider putting
items the n items into the boom filter
and see what is the probability that it
hits I. If anything hits I then that um
is is a is a bad sign. Okay. So let's
warm up here. So let's say I'm just n is
one. I'm just inserting one element and
k is also one. So I'm only using one
hash function. So now the question is
what is a chance that there's a hash
collision um between i and whatever
element I'm putting in. And the answer
to that is just one over the number of
bins. Right? Assuming everything's kind
of independent. um
um that's uh going to be you know 0.001.
Okay. So now um I'm still n is still one
um but I'm get to use k hash functions.
So then I essentially
if um I'm going to
uh then the the criteria is I have to
miss not just one time you know but you
know k times.
Okay. So this is a probability I miss
once. So one minus that is the
probability I I hit and um and then that
raised to k times is the probability I I
um have hit you know um on k and then y
minus that is the probability I um you
know uh have to miss k times.
So now the probability here uh goes down
you know uh a little bit.
Um okay so now um if I'm inserting n
items
so I'm asking the probability that the
test bin
um is is one after n. So now instead of
missing k times I have to miss k times n
times. So then basically it's this
expression but just k * n. Um and
finally
um because the test item is something
that um I am
you know also hashing. So I get sort of
k chances you know to miss. So the false
positive rate actually this is what kind
of helps the K really helps is that I
can um you know drive down the false
positive rate with with with K. So that
becomes um you know f goes from 63 to
01.
Um the you can actually look at the
expression f here and compute the
optimal value of k um given a fixed you
know ratio um as this is a sort of
asmtoic calculation and then you find
that um this results in k is scaling as
order m over n. So the number of hash
functions you should use is on order of
number of bins over um the number of
items you're hashing. And if you do that
then f uh um turns out to be um you know
0.5 and the false positive rate is 0.5
to the to the k. So you see that in this
particular case I wasn't optimal um
because the optimal value is actually k=
6 and the false positive rate is 0.08
as opposed to um 0.0
sorry 0.008 rather than 0.01.
Okay. So you can read more about this.
There's some lecture notes that allow
you to trade off the compute um the
memory and the false positive rate.
Okay, so the bloom filter has some
hyperparameters that allow you to
control um whether the um you know what
your desired false positive rate is, how
much memory you have, how much compute
you're willing to put in and so on.
Yeah.
went down.
So you're saying that the optimal K, you
know, went down. Um,
and so why does the F go down?
Um, so the,
um,
let's see. So if a K goes down, um I
think it's not monotonic,
right? So if you use a very um I think
if you use a very large value of K,
that's actually pretty bad because then
you just fill up the you know the bloom
filter. Um and if you use too small,
that's also not very good either. So I
think there's a sort of optimum and
whether it goes down or up depends on
which side you're on.
Okay, so in DOMA um they set the false
positive rate to um 10 um to the minus5
and they use a bloom filter to do their
exact uh dduplication
um
and they did it at the paragraph uh
level.
Okay, so that was exact dduplication
and the problem with exact dduplication
is that it doesn't capture some of these
near misses where morally it's a
duplicate but um we are not able to
detect it. So now how do you do
approximate set membership? Um and to
talk about approximate set membership
you need a notion of a similarity
measure. So one common one that's used
is jakard similarity. So the jakard of
two sets A and B is the ratio of their
intersection over the union. So as an
example if I have 1 2 3 4 and 1 2 3 5.
Um if you compute the jakard um the the
intersection has size three the union
has size five and therefore the jakard
is 6.
Okay. So we're going to say that two
documents are near duplicates if their
jakard similarity exceeds some some
threshold. And generally the threshold
will be you know fairly high like n9 um
if you want to only you know match if
you're like missing a comma or
something. Now notice that there's
nothing semantic about this. you could
be um you know missing a word like not
and of course that changes the meaning
completely or some content word but um
this is just trying to get documents
that look fairly superficially um
similar.
Now the the algorithmic challenge is how
do you find near duplicates in linear
time. Okay. So to work up to that we're
going to try to rewrite the jakard
similarity which again is a pair-wise.
You can't compute jakard of one element.
You can only compute it if you have two
elements. And I'm going to try to write
it in terms of a hash function which you
can compute in terms of one element.
Okay. Okay, so there there's a cache
function called minash
um which has the nice property that the
probability of a hash collision is
exactly jakard ab right so normally
remember you think of hash collisions as
you know to be avoided at all you know
costs you you really don't like them but
here um it's not that you want more hash
collisions it's just that hash
collisions are something that you want
to control for you want just the right
level of hash collisions
governed by the similarity. So the prob
again to just state it probability the
similarity is equal to the probability
of um collision. So the more similar two
things are the more they should collide.
So that's the the intuition.
Um okay so so minash is defined as
follows. You take a set and you hash um
all these elements. Remember these
return numbers and you just take the
minimum element.
So you know it might at first glance if
you haven't seen this it's like kind of
not obvious why uh just taking the min
actually gives you this property of
expectation equal to the chard. Um but
the argument is actually fairly you know
simple. So the way to think about it is
that you have your five items and you
have two sets and I'm going to look at
um this sort of carous matrix
representation. Um so A has 1 2 3 4 B
has 1 2 3 5
um and now the random hash function
um induces a permutation over the items.
So permutation might be three, two, one,
four, five for example. This hash
function right there. And now let's look
at which item is first in A.
Um and which item is first in B.
Okay. Um so that corresponds to the you
know the item corresponding to the
minimum hash and the item
each item has the same probability as um
you know being first because it's the
hash function you're assuming has you
know it's it's random.
So if one, two or three are first then
the the minash is actually going to be
the same right because the minimum um if
these are you know first um the minimum
here is um equal to the minimum you know
here right but if the minimum if the
first uh the minimum hash is four or
five then the first in a will not be the
first in um B and the min hash will be
different. Okay. And then now you can
say see that the probability of the min
hash being equal is exactly 1 2 or three
which is identically exactly the
intersection.
Okay. So if you're in the intersection
and that item is first then you're going
to get a collision. And if you're not in
the intersection,
then that one being first, you'll not
get a collision because you're going to
get the min for one of them and you're
going to get some other value for the
other one.
Okay.
All right. So, um you can check this
empirically if you don't believe me. Um
so, generate a thousand. Um I guess
we're running this on A and B. Um and
checking what's the probability that the
you get a collision and it turns out the
estimated jakard is 6. It's not exactly
6. I think there's some rounding but you
know it's it's pretty close.
Okay. So now we've taken this chicard
similarity which is paraphase function
and reduced it to some probabistic
um you know uh unary function um just on
on item. Um, but this is actually, you
know, we're far from done because now we
can hash our items, but a collision
doesn't tell us that these two are
similar,
right? Just like more likely that more
similar things will be hashed together,
but we want something a bit stronger
here.
So, this is where locality sensitive
hashing comes. Um and so right now so
far we just have a hash function that um
takes two um you know hashes sets and
the sets will collide if with
probability jakard.
Um but we really want A and B to collide
if and only if ideally if uh the jakard
of A and B is exceeding some threshold.
So somehow you have to sharpen the
probabilities, right? You want to say
that if the jakard is over the
threshold, then with almost like
probability one, they're going to be
hashed together. And if it's below this
threshold, then with basically
probability zero or very small. Um so
you know, how do we do this? Um it's
sort of taking kind of the same trick,
which is use more hash functions. Um,
and here the construction is you're
going to break up your N hash functions
into B bands of R hash functions. So,
for example, if you have 12 hash
functions, um, and three bands and each
band would have four hash functions. So,
you have H1 through H4, H5 through H8,
H9 through H12.
Okay? And then we're just going to
declare that A and B are going to
collide if for some band all of hash
functions returning the same value.
Okay, so if I have A and B, I'm going to
hash uh using all 12 hash functions for
both A and B using the minash. And now
I'm going to say if this band, for
example, if the hash values for H1, H2,
H3, H4 all agree, then they're going to
collide. or this band or this band.
Okay, so there's a sort of or and or
structure which is the key to you know
making sharpening the probabilities
around the threshold.
Okay, so um now we just have to you know
do some analysis to calculate what is
the probability that a and b uh collide.
Okay, so similar I'm going to use sim to
refer to the jakard.
similarity.
Um so
um okay so I'm going to say let's say I
have jakard similarity of uh 0.8 eight.
In that case, I'm going to have five
bands. Each band has um 10 hash
functions. So, a total of 50 hash
functions. Um so, what is the
probability of a fixed band you know
matching?
So, probability of fixed band matching
is simply you know 0.8 to the R,
right? Um because the probability of
hash a single hash function is just a
jacard which is 0.8.
And now what is the probability of that
sum band matches? Well, it's a
probability that um you know the that
one fixed this is the probability that a
fixed band um doesn't match and this is
the probability that you know all of
them don't match and then so this is the
probability that at least one matches.
Okay. So now you see the probability of
collision is you know 04 um you know
three.
Okay. So it's kind of reshaping this
probab umility. Before if you have one
hash function if B and R is one then um
the probability would be of collision
would be 08 and now it's uh you know.3.
Okay. So you know that's but let's um I
guess here's a picture you should have
in your head. So on the x-axis is
similarity and what we want is the
mapping from similarity to probability
of collision to look something like
that. If the threshold is the desired
threshold is you know 0.5 then I want
everything down here to be you know near
zero and everything up here to be near
one. So let's see uh what this looks
like. I'm going to set um
um
for various similarity values. I'm going
to set B equals 10, R equals 10. And
notice that what this happens is that it
squashes down some of these low
probabilities and then it sharpens some
of these high probabilities.
Okay. Um but you know, maybe I want to
make this a little bit sharper. Um, so
what I'm going to do is to increase R
from 10 to 20. And what that does is
that moves the curve to the right um to
make it harder to match and also
sharpens the threshold. So if I do that
then you'll see that now these
probabilities go up and now um these
probabilities are much smaller. Right?
So in before um even a 7 probability uh
some 7 similarity had um you know a
probability of 0.24 which is you know
kind of high. I really don't want this.
So I want to squash this. So in
squashing that I can now get it down to
you know 07 which is you know pretty
good I guess. Um, but now I've also
squashed uh some of these probabilities
and I the goal isn't to shift everything
to the right otherwise I might as well
do exact do duplication.
So now there's another trick. If I
increase B which is the number of
buckets or bins
um then I can
um essentially get these probabilities
like 0.9 to be in the 90s uh now and
these probabilities are still fairly
low. Okay. So this picture shows that as
you increase B I get to shift this curve
to the left. So increasing R will
sharpen the curve and move things to the
right and then increasing B will um
shift the curve to the left so that you
can with appropriate setting of B and R
you can get your like really sharp
sigmoid.
Okay. So just an example of what this
looks like in practice. So there's this
um paper that we saw last time that uh
uses a near duplicate uh near
dduplication
um using minash LSH um and uh their
values um b= 20 and r equals uh 450. So
so this r is large which means that they
want a really um sharp threshold. So um
there's a formula which you can um
compute which um says the threshold is
um.99.
Okay. So that means um for every 100
words you can only allow basically one
word to be you know different. So this
is fairly you know strict dduplication
and uh the probability that a
um you know fixed band matches is um you
know this to the r which is point um 05
and then the probability of collision is
um 0.64.
So one thing that's kind of interesting
is that um I'm computing the probability
of collision at the threshold. So in
some sense you know that should be
somewhere in between 0 and one. And it
turns out that it converges to 1 - 1
over e which is you know around you know
6ish.
Okay. So around the threshold, you know,
you could go either way, but as soon as
you go above the threshold, you have
very high probability of being in a
collision and below the threshold, you
have very low probability of being uh in
a collision.
Okay. So um so with that, I'm going to
you know summarize. Um
actually maybe I'll ask uh if there's
any questions about dduplication.
Um so dduplication makes you run faster,
avoids memorization. You can do exact
dduplication
um with bloom filters or you can use
minash LSH to do approximate
dduplication.
Yeah. Um so I have a question like are
most of the duplicates functions are
like based on exactly like duplicate but
if I like rewrote the text like other
since like synthetic data is like
authorized I was wondering how do we
dduplicate for that use case? Yeah. So
given that synthetic data is on the
rise, how did you duplicate using um
something that's like uh you know
paraphrase um sensitive? So there are
some papers uh for example 70 duplicate
didn't mention that look at essentially
embedding. So um that uh can allow you
to get a more semantic notion of um
similarity or did you um and and this
all fits into the same you know
framework because you know in some sense
LH LSH was devised to find approximate
nearest neighbors and so all you have to
do is have a embedding and that can you
embed all the documents and you can find
nearest neighbors in that space. Um
obviously there's a higher cost if
you're going to run an embedding to um
to embed your documents and also
you know we are sort of working in a
regime where documents are you know the
the near duplicates are like really near
duplicates. Um I think you have to be
very careful if you're doing some sort
of more fuzzy duplication. you can throw
out a lot of your data um if you are too
permissive.
Uh another question. So we know that all
the better. I wonder if there's any
situation where you actually have to
duplicate data since it's like so high
quality or you want to be repeated.
Yeah. So the question is uh well if the
data is high quality maybe you do want
duplicates and that's actually right. Um
so in a lot of language modeling papers
there's sort of the mid-training regime
where you have a bunch of high quality
sources. You actually want to take
multiple epochs over high quality data.
Um so the dduplication is more I would
say for kind of the pre-training where
you have all this stuff and you have
60,000 copies of some random thing you
just want to like clean that up. But um
I think the optimal thing to do is well
clearly not I don't know what the
optimal thing to do is but um it's
probably if you have documents that
occur a lot of times you could also
signal that there's more importance to
it and maybe the right thing to do is
like taking the number of the count and
I don't know taking the square root or
log or something so that it shows up um
doesn't proportionally show up in your
training data. But it's you acknowledge
that it's um important enough to go take
more epochs over it.
Okay. So let's summarize. Um so this
lecture was mostly about giving you
algorithmic tools. So we look at engram
models uh linear classifiers and
importance resampling as ways to do
filtering. And with filtering um you can
do language identification, quality
filtering, toxicity filtering, anything
I guess where you have a targets
data set and you want to get more of
that data set, then you can apply these
tools. Or if you don't have a target
data set and you have a strong language
models, you can prompt that language
model to synthesize a or synthesize or
um filter down a you know a lower
quality data set to get to t and then
you get a fast classifier that uh you're
and you're off to the races. And the
second we looked at dduplication
which um is important um
for reducing the amount of compute you
you're spending on you know kind of
you're wasting essentially um and the
algorithmic tool here is is hashing u
because hashing is what allows you to
take these kind of pair-wise notions of
similarity and collision and turn them
into unary functions which allows you to
have this linear time, you know,
property. And, you know, we saw some
sort of clever methods where, um,
basically using multiple hash functions
um, and using these kind of andor
constructions allows you to kind of
shape your your criteria in in ways like
the LSH example. So now you have all the
tools um, you know, now in some sense if
you ask how how you teach data, this is
kind of only the beginning. um the you
really have to spend time with the data
looking at it, filtering and training
models and that's how you build um your
intuitions over what works and what
doesn't. So hopefully you'll be able to
do that uh a bit in assignment uh 4.
Okay, that's all for the data lecture
and next week uh we're going to start
doing um reinforcement learning and you
know alignment which is will be our last
unit.