So today's lecture is going to be on
data. In the previous lectures up until
now, we've discussed how you train a
model given data. So we've talked about
the architecture, we've talked about the
optimizer, tokenization,
um scaling laws, parallelism, that's all
given a fixed data set. And now we're
going to talk about what data do we
train on. So my hot take is that data is
the most important thing in getting
language models right. So Tatsu might
disagree with this. He thinks scaling
laws is the most important thing. But
but here's my justification. Let's see
what companies actually disclose in
their papers. So if you think about all
the openweight models llama 3 and even
deepseek they obviously fully disclose
their architecture
and in the papers they actually talk a
lot about um the training and how um the
training works but basically don't talk
about the data. So if you look at the
llama 3 paper which is has a lot of
details about a lot of things um this is
basically what they say about their
data. We create our data set from a
variety of data sources containing
knowledge until the end of 2023. Now to
be fair, they talk a bunch about how
they filter the data at at least at a
high level, but obviously this is not
really u much information about um um
the data set.
And there's some reasons for this um
secrecy. One is competitive dynamics um
and the other is uh they don't want to
get sued. uh more than they already are
I guess. Um
so you know data is uh before foundation
models I think data was clearly
recognized to be important um because
you need to annotate data to drive
supervised learning. Now even though
there's less annotation involved there's
still the data work um and a lot
involves a lot of curation and cleaning.
So somehow we haven't moved much. Um
data is fundamentally this kind of long
tale of problem and I think the reason
that it um people in think about it so
much is that it actually is very
scalable. If you think about building a
model that does all different types of
things, you can easily hire a team of
you know several hundred people who work
on different aspects of data like
multilinguality code. um if you're
multimodal you can do um different types
of uh you know images and so on. Whereas
architecture there's one architecture
you have a small team that defines it
and that's it. Data is very paralyzable
if you think about how are you going to
allocate uh resources in your um
language modeling development team.
So um there's multiple stages of
training. So there's pre-training which
is the focus of this uh majority of this
class. um and you train on raw data
usually from the web. There's um
mid-training
um which is where you curate a smaller
set of high quality data documents um
aimed at targeting particular
capabilities such as math or code or
long context. And then there's
post-raining where you fine-tune on
instruction following data or chat data
or you do reinforcement learning to get
the model to be actually something that
you can talk to. This is where typically
things like safety also fit in. So, but
in practice the lines are blurry and
often in you know the more recent models
there's more stages but you know one
does not know exactly what is there. But
the basic idea I think is clear you
start with large amounts of low quality
data and then you um sort of uh train on
smaller amounts of high quality data
towards the end. Okay, just a bit of
terminology that you've seen. So base
model typically refers to the checkpoint
that you get after pre-training and
mid-training and then struck models are
after post-training. So let's take an
example of what this looks like. So this
is from um AI2 which has been releasing
a bunch of open source models. So we
know exactly what's in the data set. Um
so pre-training this is a typical
pre-training data mix at least for open
source uh models. Um those so there's
some web pages from this thing called DC
on baseline which I'll talk about later.
There's code academic papers there's
math um and Wikipedia and there's about
uh 3.9 trillion uh tokens here. So now
if you look at mid training um you see
actually uh a bunch of the same sources
but you know they're filtered down. So
still DCL on baseline uh but it's
filtered down from 3.7 trillion which
was the majority of that data set to 700
billion. Um there's some flan data sets
which I'll mention later still
Wikipedia. Um we like Wikipedia I guess.
Um and then there's some new data sets
that are synthetically generated. Um and
might as well toss in the GSM8K training
set. Why not? Okay. So that's about 10
billion uh training tok to tokens. And
then there's a separate paper called
Tulu uh which does actual you know post
training and here's the various data
mix. So there's like uh basically chat
um data from various sources and a bunch
of synthetically generated data that
captures different aspects.
Okay. So
so what are all these data sets? Um how
are they chosen and processed? Um so to
set expectations that not disappoint you
um uh later um there's not really a good
I think as you can might imagine uh you
know formalism or principle for deciding
these things um I think this is maybe
not that surprising given um the nature
of this class even for architectures we
didn't really have a good principle but
for data in particular I think data is
something that's I think hard to teach
because what do you mean by teaching
data So basically I'm going to talk
through the different data sets that
people have used over time, talk about
where they come from, some of their
properties in hopes that you can use
your inductive powers to figure out some
sort of a um intuition for what makes
good data, what doesn't. Okay.
So
um I'm going to start with pre-training
um and then then I'm going to talk about
mid-training and post- trainining but
most of it's going to be on
pre-training.
Um I'm going to start way back in 2018.
So this is the BERT model uh which some
of you might still um remember. Um this
is a big deal. So Bert was trained on um
you know books and Wikipedia. So let's
dive into what that um exactly you know
means. Um I think the data sets often
not really I think discussed uh very
much and um because people look at the
model and the eval capabilities. So
there's this website called Smashwords
which came about in 2008 allows anyone
to go publish an ebook. So last year
there were about uh you know 500,000
books and so in 2015 there's this
actually vision language uh paper that
essentially scraped a smashwords and
created this book p corpus consisting of
self-published books that were uh priced
at zero. So they got uh 7,000 books. Um
and this has since been taken down
because it just violated the terms of
service. So back in 2015, you know, it
was sort of the wild west. People didn't
uh think that, you know, AI and AI
copyright wasn't really a much of a
thing as it is now. Um so that's the
books corpus if you ever, you know, see
that. Um it's old data set, but it's it
sort of um I think represents the
importance of books that has sort of
continued. Then there's every Wikipedia.
Everyone knows Wikipedia. Um, just for
fun, we can just point at a random
article. Um, okay, sure. This is a this
is a random article from Wikipedia. Um,
if you click again, you'll get a
different random article. Okay, so
here's a build a random building in
Indonesia, I think. Okay, so this was um
it's been around for over 20 years and
there's a lot of different articles in
different languages. Um I think it's
important to you know explicitly say
kind of what's Wikipedia is. So it
doesn't contain any original thought. So
everything is coming from cit that's why
there's citations of actual um
um you know original primary sources. So
there's supposed to be no opinions or
personal web pages or anything. um and
it's based on notability which is um you
know means that multiple sources must
have covered it. So I think this already
gives you a kind of a sense of what's in
Wikipedia, what's not. Clearly there's a
lot of valuable content maybe in the
tales that wouldn't be in Wikipedia and
there's a lot of opinion that might be
useful that's also not in Wikipedia like
recipes are not in Wikipedia and and and
so on. Um so anyone can edit and the
content um but in practice a small uh
major small number of people contribute
the majority. So this guy had five
million edits. I think he probably used
some um some tool. So Wikipedia is this
website. Now every once in a while
there's a dump um that gets that's gets
produced and you can go download your um
you know some zip file with all the
Wikipedia content. Okay. So just one
aside is that you know Wikipedia we
think of as very high quality sources
reli re reli well maybe reliable more
reliable than average internet article.
Um and uh but there's this thing that
everyone should know about which is
relevant to data is um data poisoning.
So the idea is that um this is Carlin
has a series of you know wonderful
results um how showing that everything
is broken. um you can they show that you
can inject malicious edits right before
these periodic dump so you know when the
dump is is coming and so you inject this
edit so that it goes into the dump but
before the edit is rolled back so it's
you know I thought it was pretty clever
and we know that if you can control the
training data then you can
um basically get the model that's
trained on such training data to do
various things for example ascribing
negative sentiment to trigger phases
like a iPhone. Okay. So a adversary
might be able to leverage this process
um and inject whatever they want into
something like Wikipedia even if you
have this roll back policy. So I think
since then u this has been some patch.
So I don't think you can literally
exploit this. But in general, I think
it's important to realize that the data
that models are trained on comes from
the broad internet where attackers and
anyone with various incentives have
actually quite a bit of control over the
behavior of the language model and it's
very hard to have oversight into this
process.
Okay, so Bur was trained, that was a bit
of a digression, but Burr was trained on
books and Wikipedia. Obviously back then
people didn't really care about uh data
uh poisoning for language models um as
much. Um and I think Burr, you know,
seems very old, but this was like kind
of a big transition between uh training
on documents rather than sentences in
contrast to the billion world word
benchmark that we talked about last uh
last week. Okay, so that was 2019 or
2018. Um so GBD2
um collected a data set called web text
and the idea here was that well you have
the web and it's kind of large and
probably low quality. How can we quickly
get a diverse high quality subset? So
the insight was that well if you look at
Reddit posts there's a bunch of links
that go out and these posts can get you
know karma points. So why not take the
links that um uh have are on posts with
more than three comma points. This
resulted in 8 million pages, 40
gigabytes of text
and um that's what they used to train
GPT uh you know 2.
Okay. Um now they didn't release um
besides the paper they didn't release
the data set. So there's been since an
um you know open replication of web text
that's um often used um in language
model research.
Okay. So now let's talk about common
crawl. Um I think hopefully by the end
of this you you'll whenever someone
talks to you and say well I language
models are trained on the internet you
can call them out and say you know
that's just uh false and what does that
even mean? Um so let's talk about common
crawl which is maybe an academic
approximation of the internet. Um so
common crawl was established in 2007.
Every month they re write a web crawl.
Um so there's been about a hundred
different web crawls over the last um
you know however many 17 years. Um the
crawl itself isn't actually that
expensive in compared to language model
training. You know you can rent some you
know a AWS machines um and just get it
done in like less than two weeks. Um, so
the last crawl was uh last month and
just to get a sense of what this uh this
crawl looks like. So here's some
statistics. Um, so there's about um, you
know, 2.7 billion pages that were were
were added. Um,
and each crawl
there's there's 100 crawls. Each crawl
uh might have slightly different web
pages, but there's some overlap because
there's for it's not clear what the
heristics are, but you might imagine
that sites that are rapidly changing,
they crawl multiple times and sites that
don't change very much, they don't crawl
as much. And there's a explicit attempt
to diversify.
Um so crawling, just to very briefly
talk about this, um they use an open
source library. you start with a set of
seed URLs which is actually quite a
large number. So it's not like one
website that somehow you you crawl the
web. It's actually quite hundreds of
millions um and you basically maintain a
queue where you have the crawl frontier
and then you have a bunch of machines
that um look at that frontier and go
crawl um from there. Um so basically
you're doing like a BFS of the web but
there's a lot of uh systems and you know
dealing with the fact that some sites
might you have to be um little bit
careful about crawling. Um so there's
questions of you know which pages do you
do you download? You have to respect
robots.txt. You don't have to shouldn't
overload the server. Um and if you've
already crawled a site when do you go
back and crawl it again? Um and then
there's a problem that URLs are dynamic.
So some URLs are very long, multiple
URLs might lead to the same content
which leads to a lot of uh duplication.
Um so when common crawl uh crawls the
the produces data in two formats. One is
a work file and this is the raw HTTP
response that you get um which is often
HTML uh for well HTML pages. This does
get converted into text into a format
called wet and this is obviously a lossy
process HTML to text it to loses
information. Um one note is that um this
is not the only way you can use their
web file which is text or you can start
with a raw HTML the work file and do it
yourself. And there's a a few tools out
there um in your you know assignment
you'll be um uh trying out different uh
tools or or at least using doing the
HTML to a text conversion yourself. Um
and this does make a difference. So um
this uh the paper from data compat line
which I'll talk about a little bit later
uh did this ablation where you look at
different um HTML to text converters and
using the raw web files is actually four
points a whole four points lower than
using traffic flow tour for example.
Okay so there's some low-level details
here. Um one other thing about I'll say
about common crawl is that um this is
deliberately not meant to be a uh you
know comprehensive in terms of crawling
the entire internet. I think part of
their policies is to be kind of gentle
and you know polite. Um so um for
example not all Wikipedia articles are
even in in common crawl.
Okay, maybe I'll pause here just to in
case people have any questions about um
data so far.
Yeah. Common crawl do any like
sensitive?
So the question is does common crawl do
any filtering of its own on sensitive
content?
Offensive content.
Yeah, I think um by default they're very
permissive because the idea of what is
offensive or not is like a fairly high
level semantic decision. So there's
definitely a lot of uh offensive content
in in common crawl and you know harmful
content. Um there might be kind of life
filtering. I mean there's some sites
which might be like plain illegal or or
something. They there might be some you
know uh block list. I'm not sure about
the exact details.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is can a website
uh be flagged when they don't want to be
you know included. Um and the answer is
yes. Uh well yes there is a way. So if a
website can include a robots.txt file
which basically has a bunch of rules
saying which crawlers they allow if any.
So um if you look at the robots txt
let's um
so this is
uh robots
robots.txt.
So for example, New York Times disallows
um uh okay for Google bot it disallows a
bunch of stuff and then um there's
different rules and you can see all your
favorite uh you know um you know LM
provider. So it turns out that um many
of the um not all these are LM um you
know pro developers but it it turns out
that most of the frontier model
providers or developers have their own
crawlers just because common crawl is
actually turns out to be quite sparse in
terms of coverage even though it's quite
big but the internet is a is a very big
place
but but there's no
formal way of ensuring that robots txt
is is a kind of a guidance. So there
might be folks that are not respecting
robots txt.
Um yeah over here and then how does the
brower handle like embedding media or
like images? I guess those are just sort
of ignored like uh so question is how
are images handled? So technically
common crawl does it's just like has a
URL and gets the raw response. So
sometimes the response will be text and
sometimes it will be images. I think
most of common crawl it's sort of biased
towards text because that's but
occasionally you'll get like you know
other stuff. Um of course you know there
you could develop crawlers that
explicitly go after media
over there. Do we have any idea what
fraction of copy crawl any of the other
sources are copyright material that's
not quality? So question is uh what
fraction of common crow is copyright
material um I'm going to talk about
copyright later um but I would say that
most of it's copyright um um and that's
a complex topic so I'll touch on it
briefly later
okay let's move on so common crawl is is
big and I think even on the first day of
lecture I showed you that if you look
just look at random samples from common
crawl it's really no
Um so there's uh been a lot of attempts
to filter common crawl. Um one of the
earliest attempt is called CCNet. This
is from uh Meta. Um and uh the idea is
that they wanted a generic procedure
that could take um common crawl and
return high quality you know data sets
and in particular they were interested
in the multilingual coverage. Um so they
had a bunch of horistics. Um so they
removed uh duplication. They ran
language identification which is
basically a linear classifier uh to to
keep only examples of a target language
whether it be English or or German. Um
and then this is sort of the key part is
that to filter on quality they look at
documents that look like Wikipedia under
um a five gram model. Um so they take
Wikipedia text they train an engram
model and then they use that to score uh
documents and the idea is that Wikipedia
um as you'll see has been used sort of
as a surrogate for high quality data and
using that you can get more things that
look high like high quality where
Wikipedia serves as a surrogate for um
high quality and as we discussed
Wikipedia obviously doesn't cover
everything. Um uh so this is also not
going to cover everything. So they train
um a bunch of bird models at the time.
Um
um and they show that they outperform
only training on Wikipedia. Um so um and
CCNET uh is a bit confusing sometimes
because it refers to both the tool which
is a function of a filtering function
but also the data set that they release
from the paper.
Okay. So, uh meanwhile, um Google was uh
doing some stuff as well. So, they
released this uh C4, which stands for
colossal clean crawl corpus. Um and it's
sort of a um I guess the same insight
that you want to take common crawl, you
might you want to leverage this large
text somehow. Um this paper actually by
column raffle
uh is more famous for introducing the T5
model. Um but it actually introduced the
C4 data set which is a main
contribution. It's a long paper. Um
and the observation is that you know
common crawl as we mentioned earlier
doesn't have um is most of it is not
useful in natural language. Um so if you
let's say you start with one snapshot so
that's 1.4 trillion tokens already. They
decided to use just heruristics. Um so
they keep uh lines that end in
punctuation. Remove pages with fewer
than three sentences. Remove bad words.
You can look click on this to see the
bad words. I'm not going to show that
here. Um they remove brace which is
interesting which clearly re removes a
lot of code. I guess Python may might be
kept um and some like boilerplate text
um and they only kept English. Um they
got a lot of tokens out of that. So
it's kind of interesting. You see the
sort of trade-off here is that whereas
CCNET used a model based approach to
filtering to make it look like
Wikipedia, this is entirely rulebased.
So the advantage here is that there are
sentences that don't look like wiku but
nonetheless are wellformed sentences
that would end up in C4. On the other
hand, there are sentences that might be
just very spammy and also wellformed
sentences that might look fall into C4.
So it's it's kind of interesting that
there's this sort of complimentary
nature. If you use modelbased,
it's only as good as the p your ability
to curate positive examples that are
representative of what you want. And
when you want a very broad set of data,
it's often can be hard to um get that
coverage because well, that's the whole
point. You're trying to um get a lot of
uh you're trying to curate a diverse
data set in the first place.
Um they also created a web text like
data set where um they
um took uh pages from
uh open web text links. So this is
remember open web text you was open
reproduction of web text which was used
to train GPT2.
Um they looked at links from Reddit
posts with um greater than three karma.
um even if you they use 12 dumps they
only get 17 gigabytes of text. Web text
was 40. So this suggests gives you a
sense that common crawl is quite
incomplete, right? Because you took all
of common crawl and you apply the same
filter and you got something that was
about half as large as web text which
was basically doing its own crawl.
Um but nonetheless this was useful for
improving a bunch of NLP benchmarks at
the time. And if you look at uh you know
now going back to C4 if you look at what
um its composition is um you see that
there's well there's Wikipedia in there
um there's a lot of uh patents and um
news and and so on.
Okay.
All right. So we've talked about um
common crawl and different ways to
filter. Now let's talk about um more now
we're sort of entering the GBT3 era.
There's a bunch of models um and data
sets which will allow us to get into um
you know some other ideas here. So GPD3
data set there's common crawl which was
processed web text uh 2 which is
essentially the same idea as what they
used for GPD2 this mysterious uh set of
uh books corpra books one and books two
um and Wikipedia
um so the result was I have about 400
billion tokens um which by modern
standards is actually quite uh small but
at that time was quite impressive. Um so
the comic uh processing was they train a
quality classifier to distinguish u web
text high quality web data Wikipedia and
books uh from the rest. So basically the
idea of quality classification is that
you identify a bunch of positive
examples and then you try to look for
more stuff like that in a larger pool.
So this is what they determined to be
high quality and then they wanted to get
more of this. Um
and
um so yeah that's it. Um so the pile
uh came shortly after. So in particular,
Eluther um AI was this organization that
um kind of re bounced up in reaction to
GPD3 and the how closed everything was
and they were trying to reproduce open
source uh language models. Um and this
was a largely a kind of decentralized
discord driven volunteer effort um where
everyone was just like tossing in um
data that they felt were high quality.
So they curated 22 high quality um
domains. So you have um some common
crawl, open web text, sackchain,
Wikipedia, archive and and so on. Um
here's some more statistics about the
the general you know weight. So this is
still if you look at it quite you know
diverse. Um, and it's it's interesting
to think about, you know, technically
the web common crawler could have most
of this uh stuff assuming that you can
crawl. But often um you'll see that
people will
go and sort of special case different
types. for example they want to get more
Wikipedia is handled differently or um
you know like you know mathematics is
handled differently
um so if you have prior knowledge about
what's good data then you can just go
out and use it directly okay so this was
um actually more data than GPT3 was
trained on um
so um
so they used uh Uh they also noticed
that work was better than wet. So they
used this different tool just text to
convert it. Um
so there there's a PubMed central um
which a lot of papers which is nice. So
you know man there's a mandate that says
um NIH funded work has to be the papers
have to be open access. I think uh in AI
we're sort of uh sort of take it for
granted that things show up in archive
but that's not true for many other
fields. Um there's archive of course and
then there's um you know Enron emails
actually uh which is a old data set um
uh which came out of a subpoena after
the whole Enron ship sank. Um and why is
this in there? Well, it turns out that
there's it's really hard to come by
email data sets as you might imagine
because emails are private. So, this is
really the best thing we have. So, um
you could might imagine there might be
some bias in terms of uh the the email
knowledge of these this language model
that's trained on that. But that's um
something to think about. Okay. So, um
just diving into some of the the
different sources here. So project
Gutenberg uh was started um a long time
ago it's mostly English books now
there's about 75,000 books and the main
biggest uh you know draw of this is that
these are books that have copyright
clearance which mostly means that
they're in the public domain um 75 I
think 75 years have passed since um it
was published so now anyone can use it
you know freely um but there's I think
some books in there that are technically
not in public domain but it's okay um to
use. There's a data set PG19 which is
books from project Genberg um and this
was a paper that was trying to benchmark
um you know language models on long
context. So the you know appealing thing
of books is that you have really long uh
context compared to news articles or
even papers. Yeah. So based on what you
said data set is it possible that the
meteoric rise of X AI is because they
have access to like mining the tweets
data for training their models with
let's say other AI models scanned which
means that like they have access to
better understanding influence of spoken
human language more and therefore in the
long run it's really Google and X are
the only big companies with access to
like tons of tons of human generated
data with like natural language yeah so
so I think the general question is well
the the narrow question is you know does
X have an advantage because they have
access to tweets and for example any of
these big platforms Google has YouTube,
Meta has you know Facebook. Um so there
are you know uh restrictions on what
data companies can use even if they have
the data. Um uh so it's not that
literally the you know Google can train
on all of its you know like your Gmail
or something. I don't think that's the
the case. Um that said, um it is true
that companies will have distinct
advantages and access to certain types
of of data that might be you know uh
public. Um so I think public um doesn't
mean that anyone can train on it. For
example, YouTube is you know public but
Google has special access to it. Um so I
think the broader question is um will
companies that have access to special
data you know win essentially um and by
default the answer is yes because I
think that you know data is is sort of
the name of the game now interestingly
you know obviously anthropic has a
really good model and they don't have
like a particular secret source at least
I don't know of so it is not everything
but uh over time I think um this is my
opinion is that I think you know you'll
see perhaps more differentiation and
more uh you know specialization and as
companies leverage the resources that
they have.
Um okay so that's project Gutenberg
books three was uh this this project
that um produced a lot of books from
this shadow library. Um it contains
books notably from famous authors and
since then has been taken down due to
copyright infringement. So this was part
of the pile. Um and so just a note about
shadow libraries. Um these are uh
there's a bunch of different you know
libraries that basically disregard
copyright and bypasses pay walls. Um
this is basically you know illegal. Um,
and they've there's been lots of takeout
orders and lawsuits and so on, but
usually these controls are circumvented
because they just put them on, you know,
servers in different countries. Um, and
you know, the proponents say that it
makes free what's really should be free,
but you know, obviously the law thinks
uh quite differently. In particular,
LibGen has um four million um you know
books which is a lot of books uh
compared to project which has only
75,000 books um and it has been revealed
that meta train models on libgen uh for
example and there's a big you know
lawsuit about it
um so uh moving on stack exchange is uh
is a collection of sites most
prominently it's uh It's Stack Overflow
which it started with but has grown to
other areas like math and literature. Um
there's some reputation and badges to
incentivize uh participation. Um all of
you probably have used uh you know Stack
Overflow so I don't need to um well just
for fun. I like always looking at random
examples. Um,
okay.
So, here's some this is a page that
basically gives you random stack
exchange. So, um I don't know if these
are any uh good but here's a question
and here's some some answers. Okay. So,
I guess this is pretty familiar stuff.
Um so one thing to note is that if you
look at um these type of this data it's
really kind of like looks like a QA data
set right um so which is kind of what
you expect in um for instruction
following capabilities and real
applications so I guess the sort of the
lesson here is that you know by training
on you know web data or a large in
pre-training a lot of it is just
documents which don't look anything like
what you would a user would type into a
chatbot. But there are subsets of the
pre-training data that look remarkably
similar to what a user would type
coupled with the response. Um and this
is why you know the lines are a little
bit blurry between what is uh
pre-training and what's uh you know
post- training. Um the cool thing about
stack exchange is that there's also
metadata like comments and votes which
can be used to filter. Um and the data
dumps are you know are you know provided
although I think I think right now this
is if you use it non-commercially it's
fine but if you um are a commercial
entity then you have to pay uh for a
license.
Okay. So in GitHub which everyone here
knows about um
and this is a I think the primary means
in which you get code for language model
training. Um
so um this is help and code is generally
helpful for you know programming of
course but it has also been um I think
thought to be helpful for reasoning and
other uh capabilities although I don't
know what's if there's a paper that
makes that more rigorous. So here's a
random GitHub. Okay, maybe this doesn't
work. Never mind. It used to work if you
a random GitHub repository. And the
reason I'm doing this is that I think
the GitHub repos that you visit and the
Wikipedia pages you visit are distinctly
not a representative sample and by
sampling randomly it gives you a sense
of what's actually in this data set. So
when you look at numbers like oh god
GitHub has you know however many
millions of uh you know repositories not
all repositories created equal. a random
repo might uh disappoint.
Um, okay. So, there's 28 million public
re repositories. And one thing that's
interesting is that, you know, GitHub,
what is a repository? It's a directory.
And some of it's code, not some of it's
not code. There's also notions of issues
and commit history and all this other
stuff. Um, and there's also a lot of
duplicates. So in order to take GitHub
which is all this raw um you know data
and make it like trainable tokens
there's actually a lot of work that has
to go into think about how you want to
best um you know do that.
Um so GitHub archive is uh this snapshot
of all the GitHub events that have
happened and you can access it using
Google uh you know big query. Um so the
stack is uh you know a project that
fortunately produced this opensource
version of code based on GitHub. So they
took all the repository names from
GitHub archive and git cloned 137
repositories um commit kept only
permissively licensed ones um and remove
duplicates and the result was 3.1
terabytes of code. So the nice thing
about code is that often but not always
the license is made more clear compared
to web pages where the license is almost
never made uh clear.
So if you think about this this is sort
of you you see that there is the live
service there's a website GitHub that
you go to you know every day and then
there's the snapshot which gives you
sort of raw dump and then there's the
processing that happens that turns it
into an actual trainable data set. So
when someone comes to you and say I
train on GitHub then you'll have to ask
them you know what exactly does that
mean? Um what was the pre-processing
steps that were uh taken
okay so um that was the pile although I
guess I took a little bit of liberty and
digressed into the different components
of the pile. Um so now moving on. So now
we're in 2021.
So uh Deep Mind um also came on to the
scene. They the first large language
model they trained was Gopher on this
massive text data set um which was um
the Gopher model actually was not very
very good. Um but the data set um this
the paper does a great job at describing
the data set. So massive text contains
massive web which I'll talk about a
little bit later. There's uh C4 um and
then books news, GitHub, Wikipedia.
There's no details about how those were
processed. Um and as I said mentioned
before um this is obviously doesn't is
not reproducible. It's fine. You train
on GitHub but you know how exactly was
the data processed. Um so massive web um
you kept English and here again like
CCNET they used quality filters that
were based on manual rules. Um and they
had rules which you'll implement in your
assignment that look at things like you
know 80% of the words has to contain at
least one alphabetic uh character. Um
they also used uh Google safe search for
uh toxicity uh filtering. Um, and I
think in those days, one of the main
arguments for using manual rules is that
you didn't want to be biased against the
model because models, um, the only
models that they can run is very weak
models and weak models don't really
understand the page and they're just
going to have, you know, probably, um,
pretty awful bias. Um and also there was
a consideration that um this type of
filtering can you know um filter out
kind of marginalized data from
marginalized groups that didn't look
exactly like you know Wikipedia. Um but
as you see later this sort of has
flipped and now everyone's doing model
based uh you know filtering.
Okay. So their data set was 10 uh
terabytes of of text um which is I guess
you know maybe like let's say five four
or five trillion uh tokens just an
estimate although Gopher was only
trained on 300 billion which is not very
many tokens I think that's the same
maybe it's around the same number of GP3
um so in 2022 we have llama um so the
data set for llama was um common crawl
process with CCNET.
Um and
here the classifier here there's a
subtlety here. Remember GPD3 was
classify whether it looked like
Wikipedia
page or not. Lammo was class trained on
classifier which predicted do you look
like a page that was referenced out of
Wikipedia or not. And I guess the idea
is that Wikipedia will site uh high
quality pages and most of those pages
might not look like a Wikipedia article
but nonetheless are high quality. So
again the kind of this link structure
which we saw in the GBT2
uh web text is kind of showing up here.
Um they also included C4. Um why not?
They use GitHub. Um they kept permissive
licenses filtered based on some manual
rules. um Wikipedia, project Gutenberg
and books three which got them in a lot
of uh trouble um and uh you know archive
um sack exchange so they got 1.2
trillion tokens
um so they didn't release the data set
but you know uh together reproduced this
um this uh data set in something called
red pajama which now you can go and um
you have the data processing code and
the the data which you can um take out.
So this was a reproduction. So this was
clearly not optimal and cerebrus did
further dduplication and ended up with a
billion primer subset. There's also repa
v2 which uh is a little bit confusing
because this is something else. This is
essentially um uh taking common crawl
snapshots and producing 30 trillion
tokens with all sorts of different
quality signals. Um so this is a
resource for doing uh research on how to
filter based on um the quality signals
that are computed.
Okay. So that was llama. Um and then the
refined web um was another paper and
here the thesis is well remember how we
saw the pile there was web data and
there was all this other stuff. And
their point was like well maybe if we do
a good enough job filtering the web data
that's all you need because technically
you know the internet has everything in
some sense. If you think about it, if
you can access it via a computer and
it's connected on the internet, then
maybe that's uh good enough. Um
and uh so the refined web um let's see
if we can want to look at some new
examples here. Um the data uh is an
hugging face and it kind of looks like
you know this uh okay this is okay the
resolution is probably not large enough
to okay anyway uh scrap that
um they use for extracting content
because as we noted is is better than
just using the wet files that uh common
crawl provides. um they use gopher rules
um and they made a point of we're going
to avoid MLbased filtering to avoid
biases
um and then they did some fuzzy
duplication
okay so they had a five trillion token
data set which is you know quite large
but um they only released 600 billion of
it
fine web from hugging face was started
as a replication of refined web but um
they tried to improve it. So they used
all the common crawl dumps I think at
the time. Um did some filtering. Again
this is still using manual rules. No
model based filtering. Um and they did
some dduplication and did some you know
basic anonymization. So they got 15
trillion tokens out of this. So this is
still a um I think a really nice data
set because it you know dealing with
common crawl is is is going to be a
pain. But this is sort of a I would
consider fine web as a lightly uh
filtered um data set that you can
further do model based filtering on.
Okay. So um jumping ahead. So AI2
um put out has a series of models called
OMO. um their initial model was trained
on um the DOMA you know data set and um
this is a composition. So we have common
crawl, we have the stack which we talked
about which has code C4 which you know
um you know Reddit um A2 has a um
semantic scholar. So I think this is
derived from from that project Gutenberg
and Wikipedia and you know about
um so the Reddit uh comes from this this
project which um uh but they include
sort of the submissions and the comments
um separately so you don't have this
thread structure. I think this project I
don't know if it's still uh I guess it's
no longer exists anymore. So I think
around 2023 all these sites like Stack
Exchange and Reddit realized wait people
are just taking our data and um training
models and making money off of it. So I
I think that sort of uh uh came to a
stop. Um so we have 40 million academic
papers um from Semantic Scholar which
craw crawls a bunch of different you
know sites and then we have our usual
suspects. So the common crawl processing
which is um uh fairly I think I would
say standard um so they use language
identification to keep only the English
part um quality filtering again they in
DOMA they uh for training initial model
they avoided model based filtering um
and then toxicity filtering they here
you they use a classifier um and then
they who did dduplication. So three
trillion tokens came out of that. Um
and then in the same year, so this was
last year. So there's a paper uh data
comp um which was a collaboration from
multiple different organizations.
Um here what they wanted to do is
foremost define essentially a
competition for creating data sets. Um
and so they wanted to set up basic
infrastructure.
So they define a standard data sets
which you can essentially try out
different data processing algorithms. Um
so they process common crawl um all the
dumps to produce DCM pool which has 240
trillion tokens. So that's a lot of
tokens but as you know common crawl is
is not the highest quality by on
average. So that's going to get filtered
down quite a bit.
um they had a particular recipe for
filtering down that data set into which
is called DCM pool into DCM baseline and
here they were very aggressive in using
a quality filter. So this is what it
looks like. They do some rule-based
filtering basic stuff and then they the
main thing that's interesting is that
they took this uh fast filter that uh
filtered DC alum pool into don baseline.
So they they only kept I guess um you
know 1.4% of the total data set.
Okay. So what do they do for this model
based filtering? So again in quality
filtering you define your positive
examples negative examples in trainer
classifier. So the positive examples um
come from two sources. There's this uh
open Hermes data set. So this is mostly
GPT4 generate instruction data. So this
is kind of interesting. They're using
actually instruction data to curate
pre-train data. So not they're not
explicitly in training on instruction
data but they're looking for data that
looks like instruction data. Okay. And
then Eli 5, which is um basically this
subreddit um called uh
Eli 5 ask me uh like I'm five. Um and uh
this is what I guess the data set look
like. Um
okay, what's the point of wasting the
first two plays with a rush? Okay. Um
so um these are sort of like you know
questions you might ask to a a chatbot
for example. Um negative examples are
just uh sampled from refined web which
is it's not lowquality data but it's um
it's you know not as curated as these
other two sources.
Okay. So um the result is that they took
the CLM baseline which is 240 trillion
tokens and reduced it to um 3.8 trillion
tokens which is you know it's still a
good sizable chunk. So then they train a
fastex classifier
um on these u and run it on all of DCM
pool. Um and here's a one of the results
tables. Um so the benchmarks here core
includes a bunch of standard um language
modeling you know uh benchmarks like
hello swag and so on. Um and uh they
show that using this classifier they
actually outperformed um the refined web
by you know 3% and a bunch of other
things by you know one or two%. So this
is the model. This is the procedure they
use to create the the the D cell
baseline which they then you train a a
pretty reasonable model from there. Um
it is worth noting that after this
happened the second OMO model um if you
remember they started training on um you
know DCLM you know baseline as well. So,
so I think this era of we're going to be
unbiased and try to not use model to
bias, I think has kind of largely gone
away because I think people realize that
well, if you use models in the loop, you
can just like do a much better job of um
getting high quality data and and at
least for you know uh increasing
benchmark scores.
Okay, so um the final
um pre-training data set I'll talk about
is Neatron CC. So this came out of
Nvidia which has been doing some work on
training the Neimotron models although
more recently they've been doing like
post-training um and data curation. So
um their main thesis is that DCLM great
data the baseline is great data set um
but it filters very aggressively
remember it filtered down all the way
from you know 240 trillion tokens to 3.8
8 trillion tokens. Um, and if you want
to train on more, you know, uh, um, you
know, train larger models for longer,
you need more tokens because, um, this
aggressive filter training 3.8 trillion
isn't really enough to sustain let's
say, you know, like a 400 billion model
training run. Um so the first thing they
interesting they realized is that um
they did ablations for HTML to text but
not just based on the the quality but on
how many tokens were left. So they're
really trying to get not throwaway
tokens and it turned out that just text
rather than Traffa would actually keep
more tokens. So they went with just text
and then they used a bunch of different
techniques to do quality filtering. um
they prompted their gigantic neatron
model to essentially score documents
based on educational value to soda into
a faster model and use that to train. So
this is a filter based on you know uh
what a language model thinks is
educational value and they also use the
DCM classifier. There's a sort of a
interesting way that they uh ensemble
they basically ran all these classifiers
and look at bucketed their scores and
then from each bucket they sampled a
bunch of um you know data set. So it's
not just taking the top because I think
they were trying to make sure they have
good coverage over um um different
um experts kind of opinion on the notion
of quality. Um they also did this thing
which is interesting. They use the
language model to not just filter but
also rephrase data sets. So for
highquality data sets uh sorry this is
backwards. For lowquality data sets they
basically use a language model to
rewrite it into something that looks
higher quality. Um so obviously there
could be mistakes there but you know in
the grand scheme of things maybe you
know it's no worse than training on
lowquality internet data. And for high
quality data sets, uh they use the
language model to generate task things
that look like tasks. So you take a
Wikipedia article, you ask a language
model to create essentially input output
pairs where the input is might be a
question, outputs an answer or the input
might be you know summarize this
document and outputs a summary or um the
input is extract the key information and
the output's key information. So this is
again trying to get at the idea of well
eventually at instruction
uh at at instruction tuning time we want
to be able to um you know follow
instructions so we might as well start
get a head start on this. So they got
6.3 trillion tokens out of that which is
more than uh three trillion tokens
almost double um which is I guess pretty
good because I mean all of this is
coming from common crawl but they were
able to essentially double the um maybe
not quite double but almost double the
size um you know for reference you know
llama 3 is trained on 15 trillion quan 3
is trained on 36 trillion which includes
I think multimodal data so you know 6.3
trillion at this point is not like
enormous but for open you know source
models with data sets it's you know
pretty decent. Um like most of us 6.3
trillion is more than enough for
training um even to do one epoch. Um
this table shows that um basically on
average they show that their neotron CC
data is better than the DCLM data which
is has been shown to be better than fine
web at least on benchmarks. Um and then
they actually have this one trillion
high quality subset that's even even
better.
Okay. So any questions before I move on?
I know this was a lot of like random
specific details about different um
models of data sets, but hopefully this
gives you a sense of the type of things
and hopefully you can kind of see
different patterns um whether to use
models to filter or not, whether you're
um using
um links out of um high quality pages or
using the pages themselves um and so on.
So yeah,
talk about like English data sets. I was
wondering if like multilingual data
sets. Yeah, good point. So the question
is what about multilingual data sets? Um
I've sort of focused on English because
that's where primarily all the a lot of
the research done is done. Um but
obviously common crawl does have
multilingual data and there's
multilingual uh data sets that are you
know produced as well.
Okay, maybe interest of time I'll move
on to to copyright. So this was an early
question that was asked um how much of
the web is copyrighted? So let's just
understand what copyright is really
about. So nowadays there's a lot of
lawsuits um around generative AI mostly
around copyright.
Um so in general the copyright law falls
under kind of intellectual property law
and the goal here is to incentivize the
creation of intellectual goods. That's
why copyright law even you know exists.
Um and there's many types copyrights,
patents, trade marks, trade secrets. Um
so copyright law is the one that has
been is most relevant for training data
and this goes back to the 1700s in
England. Um but in the US um since 1976
there's been um the copyright act which
has essentially has established what
copyright you know means and this is
formally it's a applies to original
works of authorship fixed in a tangible
medium of expression. Um and so you know
it's original work. So if you are just a
collection it's not copyrightable like
telephone directories are not
copyrightable unless there's some
creativity in their selection or
arrangement.
Um so copyright also applies to just
expression not idea. So you can't
copyright a you know an an algorithm you
can copyright the um you know the code.
Um and one thing that has been uh what
this did is that um before copyright
only applied to things that had be you
know published and now it's just this
looser notion of fix in general um
copyright has sort of increased in scope
um and you know registration are is not
required for copyright. So this is
different from patents. If you invent
something, you don't register, then you
have no claim to it. Whereas copyright
is you put something and you throw it up
on your website, it's it's copyrighted
even if you don't explicitly um you know
write the um you know copyrighted. Um
but there is a you know thing that
registration is required um before a
creator can sue someone for copyright
infringement. But you know the bar for
registration is also only $65 opposed to
patents which are you know can be
thousands. Um it now lasts 75 years and
then the copyright expires and becomes
part of the public domain. So the all
the classics and most of ku project
Gutenberg is um has been gone out of
copyright. Um so you know the thing that
maybe people might not realize is most
things on the internet are actually
copyrighted. So whether something
copyright isn't really the issue. So the
issue is whether you can use it and
there's two ways you can use it. You can
either get a license for it or you
appeal to the fair use clause. So, if
you're going the license route, um you
can either go um sign a contract with
the the creator uh to get a license to
use the data in some terms and this is
essentially what does with you know for
example Google and Reddit have um this
you know relationship and effective
license says don't sue me um
um there's a special type of license
called a creative comments license which
allows the free distribution of
copyright work. So creative comments all
that itself is still copyrighted just
that you have a license that enables it
to act like if it was in the public
domain. So a lot of things are like
Wikipedia for example is all um you know
creative common license and a lot of
YouTube videos are also creative
comments and this was created um almost
I guess 20 years ago to essentially
bridge the gap between public domain and
copyright. Um, and the idea is that you
want people to be able to use the stuff
without waiting 75 years.
Um, and there's cases where the creator
is actually happy for people to use the
their, you know, content, but it's just
most of the time it's just not clear
because they haven't said yes or no. Um,
so now many model developers license
data for training foundation models. for
example, Google and Reddit, Open
Shuttertock, Open Sack Exchange, and so
on. Okay. So, um if you have money, you
go get a a license. Um if you don't,
then I guess you um have to say you're a
poor academic and then maybe they'll let
you use it. Um okay. So, if you But the
problem is that you can't get a license
to like the internet, right? Like who do
you go to a random website? like who do
you even go talk to? So the only way you
can use it legally is to you appeal to
fair use. So fair use um
uh says basically even if something is
copyright and you don't have a license,
you can still use it under some
conditions and the conditions determine
are determined by um the purpose and
character of the use. So, for example,
if you're using it for educational uh
rather than commercial or you're
transforming the work in some way rather
than just like copying it and hosting it
on your website and pretending it's your
own, that's going to help you. um the
nature what the work is. What if it's um
fictional? That's um
um
it's more likely to be um you know uh
actually if it's sorry factual it's more
likely to be uh fair use like for
example the telephone book you know you
can't really copyright um you know
things that are closer to facts. The um
whether if you use this just a snippet
that it's more likely to be copyright uh
fair use. Although for language models
that doesn't really apply because you
probably want to train on all of it, not
just a snippet. Um and then effect on
the market. So for example, if you're um
using the work to essentially displace
the creator, then that's going to be
seen less favorably than if you're using
the work to do something completely
different. So if you obviously watch a
movie and write a summary of it, it's
fair use. If you reimplement the idea,
that's fine. Um there's a big long
decade fight over whether Google books
when they show snippets whether that's
fair use or not and eventually it ruled
in favor of uh of Google. Um it is also
worth noting that copyright isn't just
about verbatim memorization. So it turns
out that plot and characters can be
copyrightable. So even if you have um
essentially very little engram overlap
but you take Harry Potter the character
and you essentially develop it then
that's uh that is a violation could be a
violation of copyright. But on the other
hand if you parody it's might be fair
use. So these things are quite you know
subtle and it's copyright is all about
the semantics and the economics and the
kind of content. So it's a very
complicated uh topic. Now so what about
for training?
So
one thing is like copyright is you know
the copy is in the name copyright. So
even the first step of training you
copying the data is technically already
a violation even if you don't do
anything you know with it. Um you could
argue as many have that uh training ML
model is transformative
um because you know it's definitely far
from just like you know copy and
pasting. Um this does make I think
open-source
um models with open data bit challenging
because if you want to train a model and
you also want to show people your data
and you host that data that could be in
violation of copyright. Um people have
also made arguments that um you know the
machine learning system is interested in
the idea not the expression right you're
training all this data because you're
trying to extract the you know how
language works and general knowledge
rather than uh interest in a particular
work but of course the learning
algorithm has been uh sorry the models
can often memorize and you can extract
um data training data from the models
quite easily. Okay. Um, and there's also
this, you know, problem that, uh,
language models can definitely affect
the market regardless of copyright.
Okay. One, I guess other thing to note
is that even if you have a license and
if you can appeal to fair use for a
particular work, you still might not be
able to legally get the data because of
terms of use. For example, YouTube um
has a lot of creative comments videos,
but if you write a script that goes and
downloads uh videos from YouTube, that
is against the you YouTube's term of
service. So, there's another gating for
these uh platforms. And there's a bunch
of um you know uh works that you can
kind of read about later.
Okay. So, let me quickly go on in the
interest of time. So, um this section is
going to be a bit shorter. Um and I've
sort of collapsed mid-training and
post-training together because the
boundary is not often quite clear. Um
often now we're thinking about less high
quality in general but focused on how do
you instill particular capabilities
although you know even in pre-training
we were already thinking about you know
quality classifiers and high quality. So
again the the line is not quite clear.
So one thing that I think is um which we
haven't really talked about in this
class is uh long context. So uh models
if you look at the top models have quite
a bit of context. Gemini I think still
has believe I think llama 4 might
advertise a 10 million uh million
context but you know the context lengths
are quite large and
uh transformers um scale quadratically
with the sequence length. I mean we saw
in inference lecture you can get around
that but still you need some I think
full attention to get the uh the best
results and clearly you don't want to
start at the beginning training on long
context um so what people do is they add
it later so that's why long context
extension often shows up at mid training
um because you don't want to uh waste
cycles training on long context uh if
your model is not very good. Um so
there's multiple ways of uh of doing
that. Um but since this is a data
lecture I'll talk about um you know
books and um and and math are two
sources that have been used to do
context extension. Basically for context
extension you just need to create data
that has long uh range dependencies and
some of this data can also be you know
synthesized. Um
so uh people also look at um tasks. So
there's a bunch of works that
essentially convert um data traditional
NLP benchmarks into um a standard format
that they can be fine-tuned on. So
supernatural instructions is one such uh
data sets that was um leveraged the
community to come together and create uh
1.6 six uh thousand um tasks um and they
sort of standardized into a you know
prompt u FLAN was around the same year
um it was came out in 2022 but the paper
was in 2023 so 2022 was a year of let's
take all the NLP tasks and shove them
into um instruction following you know
format um and so
so this you One I think advantage of
this is now you have a language model
that can solve all your favorite NLP
tasks and you benefit from transfer
learning. This is kind of a lot of the
thinking about like you know going back
to T5. Um but uh one problem with this
is that often the the prompts that you
have are very templatized. If you look
at the supernatural instructions, um
some of it is not supernatural um
because they're they're sort of like all
look kind of the same. So that sort of
motivates um you know these instruction
following data sets. And since 2022,
there's um there's been sort of this
expectation that language model should
just be able to answer any sort of
one-off task that you give it. So the
notion of even task sort of disappears.
Um so a lot of the work in the open
community has been based on synthetic
data starting with uh you know alpaka uh
which uh use this idea of self-instruct
to prompt a language model to generate
um examples which you can then use for
you know fine-tuning. Um there's vicunia
which used these uh conversations that
had been shared by users on shared GBT
which is deprecated. Now you can uh get
language models to chat with themselves
seated with some questions and that
creates some um you know synthetic data.
Um
and you can also have these uh you know
evol instruct um methods that
essentially take questions and make them
more complicated. Um there's uh other
ways of um you know taking this one
takes common crawl um and then uh uses
it to essentially look at identify quiz
sites and then extracts QA pairs using a
language model. Um and then this is open
hermes which we saw earlier from the
DCLM work is just a glomeorration of
different um data sets. uh llama 2 chat
we don't know what the exact data set is
but they used uh annotators to
essentially write highquality
instruction data um and
they claim in this paper um that this
was better than using the millions of
examples from open data sets um which um
and uh but they could have even saved
more you know money by um using
um you know by less annotation and more
just like RLHF which we'll talk about um
later. And finally um the last data set
that I'll mention just came out um
pretty recently. Um so the llama neatron
postraining data uh this consists of a
bunch of there aren't that many details
about this data set but the data set
really so you can go and look at it. um
they have a public data sets like wild
chat and then they synthetically
generated some data from all the models
that are you're able to generate uh data
from they also include reasoning traces
thanks to R1 um and um so if you look at
this um you know this this style this
data you you can kind of divide it into
a few buckets right one is A lot of the
early work was just okay there's GPD4 um
this is the sort of the easiest way um
to generate synthetic data. The problem
with that is that for academic research
is fine but you know it is against the
terms of open AI to use GP4 to create a
data set then you train a competing
model. Um whereas uh these um openw
weight models have more permissive
licenses which mean that you can
essentially distill from them and do
whatever you uh want. There might there
might be some restriction on llama but
um but I think broadly speaking I think
they're more permissive than open AI.
And then finally, if you are really, you
know, paranoid, then you can actually
just hire annotators to create um high
quality instructions, which is obviously
more expensive and slower. And there's
also this uh you know worry that
annotators might actually use GPD4 to uh
create your data. So you have to be
careful there. Okay. So to summarize,
um so the key lesson is, you know, data
just doesn't fall from the the sky. you
have to really work hard to get it. Um,
and it's important to think that out
there in the world there's these live
services like GitHub, right? And
first you have to to use it, you have to
first get a dump of the raw data, but
you can't train on the raw data. It's
too big or too noisy or it has it's not
even tokens. Um, and you often have to
process it. And that's where a lot of
the you know horistics that we saw for
quality filtering duplication kind of
fit in. Um this was sort of touched on
earlier. Data is really the key
ingredient that essentially
differentiates you know language models.
I think all of the language model you
know architectures there's some you know
transformer style. I think uh largely
the transfer these architecture is so
kind of general purpose that the
behaviors aren't really going to be that
different. It's really the data that
drives um the quality there assuming you
can like train uh and fit the data. Um
there are some you know legal and
ethical issues here. We talked about
copyright but there's more much more to
be said here. And then finally if you
think that this whole field is a mess,
you're right. It's very heristic. um
which means that there's many
opportunities to hopefully improve that.
Okay. Uh that is it and I'll see you on
Thursday.