Let's get started. Um, so before
proceeding with today's lecture, I just
wanted to kind of orient since we're us
a little bit since we're at the end of
the quarter now. So this is the final
lecture that either I or Tatsu will be
giving. So now let's begin today's
lecture. Uh so last time Tatu gave an
overview of RL from verifiable rewards
and he talked about policy gradient
algorithms such as PO and GRPO. Um this
lecture we're going to deep dive into
the mechanics of policy gradient gpo. So
we won't necessarily cover new material
u but just to take the existing material
and go a bit deeper show you code um and
some some math as well. Okay. So just to
kind of remind us uh what we're doing.
So we're doing reinforcement for
language models and in reinforcement
learning um you have to define the
states and actions and rewards and so
on. And just to be very clear I think
this hopefully should be obvious uh by
now but just to uh state um the obvious.
So the state is the prompt plus the
response that you've generated so far
and each action is generating a
particular token. the next token. Okay.
Um the reward
is essentially how good the response is.
And for the purpose of this class, we're
going to focus on outcome rewards where
the reward is a function of the entire
response. Um we're going to focus on
rewards that are verifiable. Um so the
computation is deterministic. Some
function just returns a reward as
opposed to having to ask a human. Um and
in this setting, you know, typically in
reinforcement learning, you see notions
of, you know, discounting and
bootstrapping where it's multiple turns
where you're getting and that really
makes sense when you have rewards in in
in the middle. If this is more of kind
of a um you just generate a bunch of
factions and you see if your answer is
is correct. So that obviously introduces
a bunch of difficulties because it's
very sparse and delayed reward but it
also simplifies I think some of the
conceptual thinking around this. So, so
for example, you might have a question
math problem and then there's a you know
chain of thought you think for a while
and then the finally the language model
might generate um therefore the answer
is three miles and then the reward would
have to extract the three miles and see
if that matches some ground truth.
So in reinforcement learning typically
people talk about the transition
dynamics. Um it's very important. Um in
this case u in the language model
setting it's very simple. It's just the
plus operation. You just append the
action into the um the state. Um this
has a number of important implications
because you can because you understand
the dynamics of the world you can do
planning aka you know test time compute.
And this is something that you know
roboticists would only dream of. If they
had a transition dynamics of the world,
they could simulate and they could do
all these things. Um, in language
modeling, we can do that, but not true
in general reinforcement learning. And
the other thing to kind of realize is
that the notion of state is is really
made up, right? If you think about
reinforcement learning in context of
robotics, the state is the joint angles,
the position, maybe an image or
something. It's really much grounded in
the real world. Whereas language models
the state is just tokens that the
language model happens to generate and
this introduces a lot of flexibility.
Um it introduces a lot of degrees of
freedom where the language model can
kind of make up its own scratch pad in
order to derive at the final answer.
Whereas often a robot is very much
limited by the external world in terms
of what states are even achievable. So
the issue here isn't about reaching any
state which is often the a challenge in
you know robotics and control. You can't
even reach the state here. You can reach
any state you want by just writing down
tokens. But the challenge is making
uh sure that these tokens actually lead
to some ground truth answer that's you
know correct.
So I think it's worth reflecting on it's
all reinforced from learning but the
intuitions and what's hard and what's
easy kind of changes in the language
modeling setting. Okay. So the policy in
this case it's just a language model
action condition on the state which is
the prompt and response given so far.
This is often fine-tuned from an
existing pre-trained language model. Um
and then there's multiple names for this
roll out episode trajectory. Um you in
this outcome reward setting you have
start with a state you generate a bunch
of actions aka tokens you get a single
number which is a reward and then your
objective is to maximize the expected
reward where the expectation is taken
over prompts which the environment gives
you and also the response tokens which
your policy pi uh that you're optimizing
gives you.
Okay, so hopefully that's uh you know
makes everything kind of very grounded
and you know precise.
Um
okay, let me know if you have any
questions about this the setup.
Uh so let's now talk about policy
gradient. Um which is a whole class of
methods for learning the policy uh which
essentially start with a policy and try
to improve it using gradient methods.
Um, so for notational simplicity, we're
just going to let a denote the entire
response instead of a single action. Um,
because we're in the outcome reward
setting, it doesn't really matter. You
can just think about the the actions as
being all generated at once by the
language models. Um, and then you get a
single reward at the end. Um, okay. So
remember, we want to maximize the
expected reward with respect to the
policy pi. So just expected reward is
integral over the distribution over
states times uh policy of action
sequence given state times reward. Um so
this is pretty straightforward and
policy gradient says do the obvious
thing you want to optimize something
let's take the gradient. So you start
taking the gradient um so the gradient
uh only touches the the policy and this
is the
um you know key trick um I think it's
like the policy gradient um theorem some
people call it but it's really just the
the chain rule for log um so this
basically gets rewritten as a pi and
then the gradient of the log and And um
I'm going to rewrite it in terms of
expectations. So expectation is um
hiding basically the distribution over
SNA here. Okay. So this form should be
very familiar. So this is the gradient
of the expected reward. Okay. So naive
policy gradient basically says I'm just
going to sample a prompt from from P
sample a response from A and then I'm
just going to update the parameters
based on whatever's inside this
expectation.
Okay, so think about if you're doing
SGD, you look at the, you know, the
expected loss and you just sample a term
and you just evaluate and you know go
with that. Um, so interpretation
this is essentially the same as SFT
um except for everything is weighted by
the reward. Okay, so in SFT a human
being writes down A for you and you just
mimic A and um update the parameters to
maximize the probability of that action
and now A is generated by the model and
now but you get to hit it with a reward.
Okay, so uh just as a kind of an
intuition building. So suppose that the
reward is either zero or one. Is it
correct or wrong? So in this case the
naive policy gradient is just going to
only update on the correct responses. So
r is going to be zero for the actions
that lead to incorrect responses. So
those are going to be completely
ignored. And then on the correct
responses r is one. So you just
essentially sample you select the
responses that are correct and you just
do sftt on this. Uh the only difference
is that um the data set is changing over
time because after you do an update now
you have a new policy and you generate
the data set based on that policy and
you iterate and so on. But this is very
natural. Um
um and you know the only challenge here
is not the only challenge the main
challenge is that people talk about uh
policy gradient as being high noise or
high variance. So in stocastic gradient
descent if you're doing supervised
learning this is also can be the case um
that your gradient is very noisy um and
typically if you use larger batch sizes
and just kind of keep on going then it
sort of empirically seems to work out.
Reinforcement learning is a kind of
whole another level in terms of noise
and variance that you have to deal with.
Um so in in particular if you look at
this setting where you have zero or one
as a reward think about solving a hard
math problem right so this in this
setting is a sparse rewards the rewards
are sparse which means that very few
responses are going to get reward one
most are going to get zero. So if you
have a bad policy and you roll out and
you generate actions,
most of your rewards are going to be
zero, which means if you look at the
gradient, you're basically making a zero
gradient update. So if you're in a
setting where your policy is so bad that
you're not able to get reward at all,
then guess what? You're not making any
gradient updates and you're you're sort
of stuck. So that's a pretty bad setting
to be in. At least in supervised
learning, you're at least making an
update towards something. You're
guaranteed to make an update towards
something. But in reinforcement
learning, in sparse rewards, um that's
not true anymore. Uh question,
why is the data set changing?
So the question is why is the data set
changing over time? So if you think
about um this is your objective
function. So you're going to optimize.
So you iterate each iteration you're
going to compute the gradient um and
then update the parameters. So the
gradient computing a gradient involves
um
um you know sampling a response and and
then updating. Okay. So now your
parameters are different. So the next
time you sample response, it's going to
be might be different now because it's
coming from the new model and and if you
sample multiple responses, those
responses that's going to be a different
data set from a different distribution
than where you started. So your data set
hopefully is going to get better over
time. So intuitively even if you have
this sparse reward as long as you can
get some of the easy questions correct
and you can get some reward you can
update your model and you hope that the
model can generalize beyond those
examples so that next iteration when
you're sampling and solving a slightly
more difficult questions you're going to
get a bunch of responses that happen to
get the right answer and now your data
set will have higher and higher reward
you
over time.
Okay, so this is in contrast to
reinforcement learning with human
feedback where you use par references,
you estimate a reward model and the
reward model is generally a bit more you
know continuous. Um it's going to assign
essentially a numerical value to every
response how good it is. This is quite
different than um the sort of verifiable
reward setting where you it's sort of
like correct or incorrect. Um and notice
that I mean I'm sort of emphasizing this
point that it's all reinforced
similarly. It's all even kind of within
the scope of language models. Sometimes
you even use the same algorithms like PO
but the intuitions for um and for maybe
how you set the hyperparameters
um will and how you tune the model will
be kind of different. Yeah.
So I notic that the rewards are sparse,
right? So you don't update the
parameters if the reward is zero. Is
that correct? Then should we just like
set it to likeative one so it goes the
other direction so we can use those
rewards?
Yeah. So the question is well in this
case um if the reward is zero then you
don't update the parameters. Why not
make the the reward like minus one? So
at least you're kind of pushing the
model away from those incorrect
responses. This is something that will
happen automatically when we uh look at
you know baselines because um there this
is just a simple naive policy gradient
where you're updating against the
rewards. We're going to show that
there's much better things than just
using the reward. Yeah. Um question I
think yeah question and then I think
there was a question over there. Yeah,
we know the reward only when we uh
what's the whole response the last word
of the response.
So the reward is a function of the
prompt and the response the whole
response.
Yeah. Yeah. And we know the response is
correct or not only when we generated it
completely. So we we have
only on the last token or
so so so yeah. So you're getting at
sometimes you have reward before you
even finish and uh so the other type of
reward is called process you know
supervision or process rewards which
allow you to um basically keep track of
how well you're doing. Um there there's
things you can do there and generally
that's better if your process reward is
good. Um for simplicity right now I'm
just assuming it's a outcome reward but
absolutely if you have reward earlier uh
you should always evaluate the reward as
early as you can if you trust it. The
problem with process reward in language
models is that you just don't it's
really hard to get a good process reward
because unless you it it's unless you're
completely going off the rails it's hard
to tell like how well you're you're
doing. Um
is there another question
same same question like what's the
reward model here that that we are
working with so how are we getting zero
and one for that
so so question is what is a reward model
I'll show you some examples of this yeah
but you can think about the reward model
is um which I think for your assignment
you're implementing basically the
language model generates some stuff and
then you parse the the answer out and
you check the answer against your answer
key and you return one if it matches and
zero Otherwise,
okay, so maximize expected reward policy
gradient sort of does the obvious thing.
Naive policy gradient uh sorry does the
obvious thing. Um but you have this high
noise and variance problem. So the a key
idea um in you know policy graining
methods is using what is called a
baseline. And so recall that this is the
expected reward. If you could actually
compute this expected reward, you'd be
pretty good um because then you could
just uh compute that. But um you you
can't. So you instead use um unbiased
estimate uh which usually means ripping
off the expectation sampling at SNA and
ripping off the expectation. This is
unbiased estimate. Um but uh its
variance can be pretty high. Okay. So
just to give a toy example to appreciate
uh what I mean by kind of high variance.
So suppose you have just two states. So
two prompts if you want S1 and S2. And
from S1 you have two possible actions.
A1 gives you reward 11. A2 gives you
reward nine. And you from state S2, A1
gives you reward zero and A2 gives you
reward two. Okay. So S1 fundamentally
gives you higher reward and S2 just
gives you lower reward. And of course
the best policy would be in S1 you want
to choose A1 and S2 you want to choose
A2, right? Um so you don't want S1 to
and going to A2.
Um but you notice that this nine is
actually bad larger than uh this this
two. So you can end up in situations
where each state think about this as
like a really s1 as being a really easy
question and s2 is maybe a harder harder
question. Um so you uh just because
something gets high reward doesn't mean
you absolutely should be you know
updating aggressively against it. So if
nine is greater than two, so if you're
doing naive gradient updates, you you
might pick S1 going to A2 and it's like,
wow, this is great. I'm going to get
nine times the gradient. And then I look
at S2 A2 and I say, well, that's only
before two. Uh, so I'm pushing up that
less. when in fact you know if you look
at the whole picture it's clear that
that's maybe just locally not doesn't
really make sense. I mean I would stress
that in expectation if you look at
overall states and actions it all works
out the math all works out but um but
you have to look at kind of everything
to uh you know get that.
Okay, does this example make sense?
Yeah. So why would you choose A2 with
the first screen? Because A1 already has
11.
So the question is why do you choose A2?
Um so you're going to choose whatever
your policy decides, right? So in your
policy when you're starting out, you
don't know which is higher reward. So
you're just going to maybe choose
something random, right? So if you
happen to choose A2, um then you might
upgrade that and get reward nine. I
mean, it's actually worse because you
say, "Wow, reward nine, this is great."
and you the more you choose it, the more
you're updating against it and then you
sort of get stuck in this local optimum
where you you can't even choose there's
no probability of mass left on A1 um
because you've updated against A2 so
much.
Okay. So, so here's a key idea behind
baselines is that you're just going to
maximize the baseline reward. Instead of
expected reward, we're just going to
subtract off some B of S. Okay, call the
baseline, you know, function. So this is
just the expected reward um shifted down
by a constant expectation of B of S. And
the the beauty of this is that this
quantity doesn't uh depend on the policy
pi. So even if you expand it out you'll
have a x you know integral over p of s
times pi a given s but integral over a
given s is just one. So this is just you
know it doesn't depend on the policy at
all
right and so of course optimizing
expectation r is identical to optimizing
expectation of r uh minus this because
it's just a constant.
Okay. So that's the whole idea of you
know baselining it preserves the sort of
optimization problem. Um and now if you
do sort of naive policy gradient on this
new objective then basically uh you you
sample a s you sample a and then you're
just looking at you know this this
difference.
Okay.
So notice that this is true. This works
for any BFS as long as BFS doesn't
depend on A which you know it's not in
arguments or can't depend on A. Um then
this is valid.
So now the question is well over all
possible functions B of S which one
should we use? And let's just revisit
this two-state example just to provide
some intuition. Um I'm going to make
some kind of uh
assumptions. you assume you your initial
policy is a uniform distribution over
all SNA and your your gradient of your
policy initially is is one just to kind
of ignore that for now. Um so if you
look at the the variance over your your
your gradients um you'll see that some
of the time you get 11 sometimes you get
nine and sometimes you get zero and
sometimes you get two and the variance
is 5.3.
Okay. So if you define a baseline which
is um 10 for S1 and one for S2 then
let's see what happens. So you subtract
off the baseline from these reward
values. So for S1 you subtract 10. For
S2 you subtract one. So now the baseline
variance is a lot less. It's only 1.1.
So we reduce the variance from five to
one which is uh is pretty good by just
subtracting a baseline which again
doesn't affect your you know end uh
results in expectation.
Yeah.
So I think there's the assumption that
like this expectation of B of S doesn't
depend on the policy pie. Um so I was
wondering like if it is okay still for
us to initialize like you know B as
let's say like the initial the very
original frozen policy.
Yeah. Yeah. So good question. So B of S
is not supposed to depend on policy. But
your question is can I just take an
initial policy and set B of S to
absolutely. So it's one of these things
with reinforcement learning you have to
be a bit careful of is what's constant
and what's not. So you can always take a
frozen um model and say that's a
constant and as long as your expression
doesn't depend on that that's actually
treated as a constant like you're not
differentiating through it then it's all
fine which means also that if you are
sampling and you're performing the
update um that you have to kind of keep
a old copy of that policy because if old
if that thing is changing now you could
get into these weird settings where
you're Not actually it's not actually a
constant anymore.
We like what what if we initialize
as the policy from the last step the
last reading step
instead of like a very variable.
Yeah. So so you can you can do this. So
typically what you do is you essentially
have a policy. kind of a an old policy
or you know anchor for for a while or if
you're doing PO you have a value
function and then you kind of hold it
for a while and then you do some updates
and then you kind of update it on so um
I mean in practice is what you do um
part of this like it can't depend on a
is really like for the theory kind of to
work out um but but in you know practice
there's you know there's all sorts of
things that people do.
Okay. So what we showed is that at least
for this example uh anecdotally you can
define some baseline that reduces uh the
variance. So this is kind of giving you
hopefully a concrete sense of the power
of a a baseline and the lower variance
you have the faster the convergence. Um
okay so you might wonder what is the
optimal uh baseline to use and if you do
some some math uh realize there's
actually a very kind of nice closed form
you know solution for this um this is
written for one parameter models if it's
multi-dimensional I think you have like
some coariances um uh and this is just
expectation of this uh derivative squar
time r divided normalized by the same
expression without the r. Okay.
So, so this is in general kind of
annoying to compute um especially if you
have uh high dimensions um and because
this thing is going to be some sort of
like you know you know coariance um so
typically what people do is you just
ignore this uh this stuff and you say
well I'm just going to try to uh I'm
going to set baseline equals expected
reward divider uh given
Okay, so this is not optimal but it's
kind of like a you know good heristic
and even this is uh you can't compute
this right because anything with
expectation you can't compute you can
only estimate but this is now I think a
good guiding principle for what you want
your baseline to be it's the expected
reward given your your state
okay so just to recap we said we have
the naive policy gradient u we can
introduce this b baseline it's valid for
any um b of s and now we've come to a
conclusion that maybe this is like a
good choice if we can try to get a
handle on expected reward given s
okay so this particular choice has
connections to advantage function so um
in reinforcement learning um you
typically have a value function which is
the expected you know reward reward
given a state. Um, and then you have a Q
function which is expected reward given
a state and I've taken a particular
action. Um, and note here that Q and R
are the same because we assume outcome
rewards and um, A has all the actions.
In general, R is going to be like the
returns from that state rather than just
a single reward. Those two are same for
now. And the advantage function is just
defined as the difference between um the
reward I would get if I took action A
and sort of if I you know average over
uh possible actions A. Okay. In
particular it's asking it's measuring
how much better is action A than the
expected value that I get from S. What
is the advantage of taking A as opposed
to just just going along with a
baseline? Oh no, sorry baseline is
ambiguous. We're going with a policy.
Okay. So then if you uh look at um B
equals this sort of heristic form that
we talked about earlier then um
then the baseline reward where you just
subtract off B of is identical to the
advantage.
So you can interpret you know the
baselining if you have the the advantage
sorry if you have this sort of um this
choice of baseline is uh identical to
optimizing the the advantage.
All right. So, so that's just to give
you some intuition behind what this um
this baseline is doing. In general,
um we are probably going to deviate from
that because we can't estimate any of we
can't compute these expectations
exactly. So, we're going to do something
else. Um so, in particular, we're just
going to I'm just going to let delta
denote whatever um thing we put in. um
to the estimate. So all of the methods
um are going to basically take the
gradient of the log policy and times
something that's going to be based on
the reward. Okay. Okay. So all the
algorithms you you see you PO GRPO
um have this sort of form where you're
basically you rolled out and got an
action and now the question is how much
do you want to move towards that action
and it's going to depend on um you know
the reward.
Okay. So you can put the reward here
then that's not your policy gradient.
You can do reward minus some um estimate
of um the expectation
um uh and you can also do divide by the
standard deviation which is what GRPO
does which we'll see later okay but this
is a sort of the general form and so the
the exact form of GPR isn't that
important uh because you know next year
there's going to be GRPO2 or whatever um
and but the all this like policy
gradient stuff is Um I'll be giving the
the same lecture next year.
Okay.
All right. Um speaking of lecture, you
can check out um Chelsea's deep RL class
for a few more u you know derivations
and intuitions about RO in general.
Okay. So any questions about policy
gradient and baselines and advantages?
Yeah, just for the baseline like a
baseline reform. That's what
so what's the definition of a baseline?
Baseline is any function that b of s
which only depends on s and not a that
you're uh essentially sticking into um a
policy gradient algorithm.
You can think about it that way. So
basically you update policy grain will
update based on this and baseline is
whatever function you choose there.
So those of you have seen kind of
control variants this is basically the
same idea from you know statistics.
Okay. So now let's try to dig a little
bit uh you know deeper. We're going to
um actually define a simple model, a
simple task, and actually walk through
some code um that may or may not look
like uh assignment 5 and um and we'll
try to hopefully do some runs. Okay, so
a lot of this exposition is based on the
GRPO, you know, algorithm. So this this
slide I might have to update next year.
Um but but it's sort of trying to
generalize it beyond the particular
choices here. Um so GRPO remember what
Tatsu uh said last time the it's sort of
kind of interesting lineage where you
had PO and then people did DPO and GPR
GRPO is a kind of um you know
simplication of PO um as opposed to kind
of algorithms you start simple and then
kind of grow in complexity
but really I think GRPO exists
in 2024 as opposed to you know in 200
I think it was 17 or something when PO
was um introduces because the language
model setting provides some kind of
natural structure that motivates GRPO.
can't really do gpo um naturally I think
in you know classical RL settings with
like the robot trying to walk um and and
the the particular thing is that in the
language modeling setting you have a
prompt you can generate bunch of
responses from that prompt and this
gives you a natural group structure to
compute the essentially the baseline
which turns out to be the average over
the rewards right the whole point is
that you're trying kind of minimize the
the variance and the group is a kind of
a natural comparison set. That's why
this is kind of relative. It's relative
to the group. Whereas if every roll out
looks different, there's no natural
group structure. Then GRPO doesn't
really make sense and you have to find
something else and that something else
generally tends to be a value function
which aggregates over all the possible
states and actions. And here this case
you kind of have an empirical estimate
over all the possible responses without
considering everything because of the LM
setting. Okay. Okay. So here's the
pseudo code. Um we're going to you know
look over it in actual Python in a in
just a second but I'll just flash it up
here. Um okay so let's define a simple
task. Um so you know I wanted something
simple enough where I can actually train
a very simple model on my laptop without
um and running a language model
transformer wasn't going to I mean I
don't have a fancy laptop so that wasn't
going to happen. So here's a simple task
sorting n numbers. So the prompt is n
numbers um and the response is n numbers
that are hopefully sorted. So now you
have to define a reward to complete the
definition of the environment and the
reward should capture how close uh to
the sorted ground truth the response is.
Okay. So immediately you actually see
one of the interesting things in
reinforcement learning is that you can
define a reward in you know different
ways. So, for example, you can define a
reward, which is like one if it's sorted
and zero otherwise, which is presumably
what you care about, but you're going to
remember the sparse reward problem. If
you start out with a policy that doesn't
do anything, you're mostly going to get
zero um reward and you're not going to
really make much progress. So, um let's
define a reward that gives partial
credit. So, we're gonna define reward
that returns the number of positions
where the response matches the ground
truth. Okay, so um you basically the
code looks like this. You um look at the
ground truth which is the sorted of
prompt and you just count the number of
positions where um the response matches
the ground truth.
Okay, so the reward for um the correct
answer is four because four positions
match. um if you have this um thing that
doesn't really solve the task um then
reward is one because I think uh you got
lucky and you put a two in the you know
second position and you have this thing
which also um
uh is not solving the problem but you
know you kind of look at this and say
well it's it's really trying um and
again you get a one because uh the zero
is in the right position. Okay, so
that's one reward you could use. Uh
maybe you're kind of unhappy with this
because, you know, this is pretty far
off and this is closer, but yet they're
all getting reward one. Um so let's
define alternative reward that gives
more partial credit. So what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to give um one
point for each token in the prompt that
shows up in the response.
Okay, so at least you'll you know output
the tokens that are in the input. Um not
too much to ask, right? So for this
particular example, I get inclusion
reward of four and then I'm going to get
one point for each adjacent uh pair in
the response that's uh sorted.
Um
so that's a three because there's three
pairs adjacent pairs and the reward is
the sum. So that's seven.
So, if you're kind of paying attention,
you realize that this reward is actually
has a loophole in it. But I'll let you
figure that one out. Okay. So, now this
particular um very wrong answer gets a
reward of three and this one gets a
reward of six because it's really trying
its best and we give a lot of partial
credit for our algorithms.
Okay. So, so that's the task and you
know in general we're going to go with
the second reward function. Okay, so the
task is clear that's an environment.
So now let's define a model to solve
this task. And so we're going to define
a really simple model. Um we're going to
assume the prompt and the response
length are fixed um and of the same
length. when I was trying to iterate on
um examples, there was one I was doing
some sort of, you know, dynamic thing
and it was just like annoying to do. Um
so I've simplified it. Um I'm going to
try to capture positional information
with separate per position parameters
because obviously position is the kind
of the name of the game here um or
position matters for sorting obviously.
And um one thing I'm going to do is
decode each position in the response
independently. So this is not an R
regressive model. I'm just going to
encode the sequence and I'm just going
to output all the tokens separately. Not
what you want to do um generally in in
real life except for I guess in some
speculative decoding. Uh it's can be
helpful to do this in limited doses. um
but it makes the the code a lot cleaner
because this auto reggressive generation
that's a part which was uh getting
really hairy so if I simplify it okay so
here's the model so um so I have
embedding matrix I have um for each
position I have a matrix for basically
transforming the
um uh the for decoding and a matrix for
um sorry encoding and then decoding
okay So
um that'll be easier to explain as I
look at the forward pass. Okay. So I
start with a prompt. Um I'm going to use
this notation in general to denote the
dimensions of the of the tensor here. Um
so there's a batch dimension which is
the number of examples and number of
prompts and then a position dimension
which is obviously the position I'm in.
Um so I'm going to uh generate
responses. So this is inference. Um so
let's walk through this. Um so just some
you know terminology. So I have a batch
size which is the number of prompts
here. Each prompt has a particular
length three. Um number of responses per
prompt. I'm going to generate in this
case two. And the response length is
four in the sorting task. You know this
response length is going to be identical
to the the prompt length. Okay. So, uh
so first I'm going to um pass the
prompts through the model to get logits
um which is going to give me for each
prompt and each position a distribution
over tokens. Um so what this looks like
is I'm going to embed the prompts um
into this dimensionality.
Um now I'm going to transform
using the per prompt position matrix and
I'm going to collapse it. So using you
know in
sum um I have batch position dimension
one and then um this weight is per every
position I have this dim one to dem two
transformation and I'm going to end up
with batch uh dim two. Okay, so I've
kind of summed out the position and dim
one
and then given that vector for each
prompt I'm going to for each position um
apply this matrix and get back uh a
vector and then finally given uh a
vector for each position in prompt um
I'm going to convert that into a logit
over my vocabulary.
Okay. So, you know, pretty I mean this
is kind of a you know simple model I
made up. I don't know if it um is
actually any any useful but anything
useful but it fit this sort of did this
toy example.
Okay. So now I have logits um and this
is just kind of shenanigans to deal with
the fact that torch moment needs uh
something flattened. So I'm going to
essentially uh basically flatten this
into a batch times position by vocab.
I'm going to sample num responses and
that's going to give me batch position
um number of responses which I'm going
to call trial is that dimension and I'm
going to um you know basically rearrange
things to make it so that it's for every
prompt for every trial I'm going to get
a sequence of examples.
Okay. So maybe I'll pause uh just to
check that everyone's, you know, with
me. So this is this is nice. Um
um be this is usually where you would
call out to a VLM, right? And do the
inference. I'm just doing this here
because it's like a very simple model
and I can just everything is just like
matrix operations. Yeah,
your responses are going to be very
close by, right? You're kind of sampling
from the same logs.
Responses are close by. the uh the
responses are going to be close by. So
we're sampling um numbum responses
independently from that distribution.
So they're definitely going to be
similar. But that would be the same as
if you sample from a language model as
well. The only difference between a
language model is regressive and this is
independent.
The point was shall we change the
temperature basically?
Yeah. So you could change the
temperature. You can do various things.
Uh I'm trying to be kind of faithful to
the um the the algorithm.
Okay. So I get my responses. I can
compute a reward over all these
responses. And um this basically uh goes
through and for every prompt and every
response I just call this reward
function which we looked at earlier. Um
nothing too interesting there. Um, and
um, sorry, this is, you know, a little
bit long. Um, oh no. Okay. Well, this
part is going to be far less interesting
because I thought I fixed the random
seed. Just generally, you wanted a
little bit more uh variance in the
rewards. Um, anyway, so the rewards all
happen to be three. So, this is going to
make uh some of this other stuff kind of
less interesting. Um but nonetheless
I'll go through the computation here. Um
so um there's this function called
compute deltas which takes the rewards
and converts them into the the delta
that I'm going to use for my updates.
And uh the framework is there's many
ways many choices here which uh some of
which you'll explore in your your
assignment. Um so for example if you can
just return delta equals the rewards
um
you can
um you can center the rewards. So you
can compute the mean over all the
responses for each prompt. So this is
what this is doing and then you can just
subtract off the mean that gives you
center rewards. And to answer a question
from earlier, this is where if your
rewards look like one and a bunch of
zeros, your average is going to be like
point, let's say 0.1, which means that
if you subtract that, now you're going
to end up with a bunch of minus ones and
something that's uh slightly below one.
And therefore, you're going to perform
updates on all those negative examples
as well.
Okay, so that's century rewards. And
then you can do this thing in uh gpo
where you um normalize. So you center
the rewards and then you divide by the
standard deviation and add something
small so you don't divide by zero just
in case and you uh return that.
Okay.
Um so one thing to notice is that what
happens if all your rewards are five for
example.
So rewards is just going to be five. So
you're going to make a bunch of updates.
Centered rewards is going to be all
zero,
right? So that means you're not going to
make any updates. So this is kind of
interesting to think about. If you have
an example where your policy is going
generating everything is the same
reward, then you're actually not going
to make any updates on that example. And
the intuition, you know, it might or may
not make sense depending on what you're
you're trying to do, but the intuition
is that there's no, you know, gradients.
You're not there's in terms of relative
comparison between that group, there's
no reason to favor any particular um
example more than other one. So, you're
just going to abstain and hope that some
other examples um give you some signal.
And the normalization means that if all
your rewards are let's say 10 versus all
the rewards are you know if you multiply
all all rewards by 100 then um the
normalized rewards is kind of invariant
to the scale of the reward. So I think
that's the you know good thing about
that. Um just for fun there's another
thing which um the JRPO paper didn't do
but you know you might think is um kind
of a cool thing to do. So you can zero
out any reward that isn't the maximum
for each batch as well.
Um so the idea here is that often in
reinforce learning sometimes you really
get into these local optimum where if
you assign too much partial credit then
the um the policy is going to sort of
latch on to that and go after the
lowhanging fruit um instead of the kind
of you know the thing that would give
you more reward. So you could try to
kind of uh just say well if it's not
getting you know the maximum reward then
I I just don't want that. It's kind of
all or nothing thing.
Okay. So um so so far what we've done we
generate a bunch of responses we compute
rewards and these deltas
which allow me to provide the update.
Now I need to look at the other piece
which is the log probabilities of the
responses because remember in the
gradient um policy gradient I have delta
times the gradient of the log um policy.
So this part is also fairly you know uh
straightforward.
Um I pass this through the model. Um
convert the logits into log props. Um
and then there's some shenanigans to um
because a prompt is doesn't is only
batch pause and responses has a extra
dimension in there. So I'm just going to
kind of upcast the um the these log
props to that higher you know tensor
dimensional tensor and I'm going to
index uh you know log props using the
responses. So the responses basically
for every batch uh trial position
specifies the index into log props that
I I need to get. So this is batch trial
pause vocab and this is batch trial
pause with an index and that will give
me batch trial pause.
Okay. Um so this gives me so logits that
are returned by the model give me a
distribution over all the vocabs for
every position and u prompt and now I
have log props for the particular
responses. So these are log props for
these particular responses I got.
Okay. So now uh we want to finally
compute the loss and the loss is just
going to be um and here there's another
set of choices here. So I'm trying to
present this as kind of a um a menu of
sorts. So the most naive thing is um
this is naive policy gradient. You just
take the deltas and the log probs and
you just multiply them together in
average. Okay.
Um so uh this is log props. Remember
batch trial pause and deltas is batch
trial. And this is because it's outcome
reward. Uh you only get um there's no
position dependence on um the deltas. So
basically every position gets the deltas
get broadcasted to every position. If
you had process reward then this deltas
would be kind of per position as well.
Okay, so that's the naive thing. Um just
a kind of interlude
um to make sure uh that we kind of into
this idea of freezing parameters. So um
later we'll see in gpo you see these
kind of ratios right? This kind of
relates to this idea that you have a um
probability of action given s and you're
dividing by some kind of um you know
other model and and it's really
important that you kind of remember to
freeze and not differentiate through p
old. So just give a kind of toy example.
Suppose I have a single parameter W and
that drives um both the the probability
um think about this as a policy and also
there's like a old value which um in
this particular iteration is just the
same thing. And now what happens if I
compute the ratio and do a backward
pass? What would the gradient be?
So I'm dividing P by P old. So the ratio
is going to be one and the radian of one
is
zero. So where are the
okay so it's it's zero which is
obviously uh not very helpful.
Um so the way you do this properly is
that you have um your P as usual and
then anything you want to kind of treat
as a constant you put in wrap in this no
grad and then this allows you to get the
value of but not the whole computation
graph and you just divide by that and
now the gradient is not zero. Okay. So
just like a kind of be careful when
you're um because in RL as opposed to
when you're doing pre-training there's
many different values that all you know
depend on different uh either old or not
old parameters.
Yeah
discount like an outcome when we go back
to the secret I guess you probably have
a hypothesis that like the last 100
tokens first.
Um so the question is why don't you
discount do some sort of discounting
when you have outcome rewards. Um
so and maybe the last 100 tokens matter
more than the first 100 tokens. Um I
think that is less not so clear. I mean
certainly like the last tokens where
you're generating the literally
generating the answer is important but I
think the the problem is that in
reinforcement in general you have to do
credit assignment right there's
certainly decisions early on that matter
um in fact they even matter more than
what you get because if you basically
have the right strategy then the stuff
that happens at the end maybe just
follows follows out and the the hard
part in reinforcement learning is that
you don't know where to do the credit
assignment. especially when you have a
sparse reward. So I think in this
setting we're just going to smear the
credit all over or the blame um all over
the place.
Okay. So with that kind of interlude
um so this is important for computing
the gpo loss. So imagine we have an old
model okay with um old so this is an old
checkpoint and um using this old model
we're going to compute the log
probabilities of the responses so that
gives us the old log probabilities and
now um
um let me just skip the unclipped
version so this is the GRPO
uh loss okay so let's step through it so
it's the clipped version. Um, so you
look at the log props and you divide by
the old log props, which remember should
be a a constant. Um, actually I I sort
of didn't follow my own advice. I don't
think I wrapped the old log props in
with no grad, but anyway, you know how
to do that. So you look at this ratio
and then that ratio gets multiplied by
delta.
Okay. And um and so if you contrast with
the naive thing, you're just multiplying
log problems um times delta. So this is
basically the same thing except for I've
divided by all log products which is
constant. So you know the I'm just
scaling the gradient. But now there's
the other part which is I'm clipping.
And the reason I compute this ratios in
the first place is that I'm going to
clip um the gradients between 1 minus
epsilon and 1 plus epsilon. So this is
to make sure that the ratios don't go
too out of whack. And I'm going to also
multiply these clip ratios by delta. And
I'm going to take the minimum and you'll
return. And there's a negative sign
because I'm talking about rewards and
convert that into a loss.
Okay.
So, so this is just following the kind
of the math in the you know GR J paper
and in the assignment you'll see this
kind of explanation of why this makes
sense. So if your updates are within the
you know the clipping range then you
just get the kind of the standard you
know update but if you sort of your
ratio is outside then your your the
magnitude of your updates are going to
be bounded by 1 minus epsilon and 1 plus
epsilon.
Okay.
So there's also this KL penalty which
provides additional regorization.
Um and uh so
so the just a kind of a quick um you
know little math exercise here. So
remember the definition of KL between
two distributions. It's your sample from
the first left distribution and it's log
over the left over the right. um rewrite
that as you know Q over P um with a
negative sign um and then so so if
you're doing you know KL penalty you
could just you know use this directly
right but um there's this
and if you want to estimate the KL you
can just take uh strip out the
expectation and you get a unbiased
estimate
um turns out that this particular
estimate that uh can have you know lower
variance where you just do q over p
minus the log minus one. So it looks a
little bit weird but you can sort of
check that this is identical.
Everything's equal because expectation
q over p is just one. So this part is
just one and you subtract one which is
zero. So you're just left with this
original term. So the math works out and
um the inside just gives you a better
estimate of the KL than doing this kind
of naive thing. So a lot of cases when
you're trying to find these estimates of
the expectation
um you're just trying to find um an
unbiased or sometimes even biased
estimate that has lower variance than
just doing the naive thing. So you kind
of try to rewrite the inside to um so
that it reduces the variance.
Okay. So just a quick implementation of
the kale penalty. This is pretty um you
know straightforward. The only thing you
have to pay attention as you're summing
over the last dimension but taking the
mean. So you're summing over the vocab
but you're taking a mean over batch
trial and position.
Okay. So just to kind of summarize the
so far the components that are needed to
introduce the actual algorithm um you
generate the responses
uh given a particular fixed model from
the responses you compute the rewards
and you know the deltas and in the case
of GRPO and friends um these don't
depend on the model it's just like a
function of the you know responses
and um in you know if you think about
kind of architecting this system
sometimes the reward is very simple it's
just like a oneliner exact match
sometimes the reward will um involve
like an agent like executing an
environment and doing all sorts of crazy
things so this could be you know
expensive or cheap operation um um but
it's independent of the the actual model
unless you have like LM as a judge which
case that's another model um
simultaneously you can compute the log
props of the responses. Um and then you
compute the loss from the log probs and
uh you know the deltas that you got
here. Um and you combine them either
clip or not clip or you normalize or you
uh sorry that's that's up here. So you
either clip or don't clip
and then you take a gradient you know
step.
Okay. So let's try to put this all
together. So this is the the full
algorithm which is essentially a
implementation of what's in here in
code. Um
so there's some boiler plate I'll just
skip over. So I'm going to define you
know some trivial data set here. Three
prompts of length three each.
um and then define the model
um optimizer
um and then I have this there's multiple
loops here and you know grplo PO so
there's an outer epoch loop um and
here um if I'm doing a sometimes if I'm
using the doing a kale penalty then I'm
going to kind of freeze the model and
have that as a reference so I can
regorize um towards that. Um and then
otherwise I sample the responses. So we
talked about this you compute the
rewards you compute the deltas depending
on you know what variant flavor you like
um and if you're uh doing the you know
the kale penalty then you also need um
you know to compute the log props under
the reference model um and um
if you're doing not the if you're doing
some sort of clipping um then you need
to
um compute also the log props under you
know the old uh you know the current
model
and then you take a number of steps
given the responses. So the idea here is
that um you know often response remember
inference is expensive you generate and
you want to do a bunch of gradient steps
with respect to the responses. Okay, so
this inner loop is basically taking a
bunch of steps with respect to the same
set of responses. And to do that, you
compute the log problems, you compute
the loss, um if you want, you can add a
kol penalty, which sometimes helps,
sometimes doesn't really make a
difference. Um and then you um just
optimize.
Okay.
So, so that is um you know maybe I'll
stop and ask answer any questions people
have about the setup here.
So the big picture is that you have the
outer iteration which you ignoring the
KO penalty because that's there's
another wrinkle I'll mention later. So
you generate a bunch of responses and
then you quickly do a bunch of
iterations on them and you generate a
bunch of responses and do some
iterations. That's kind of the basic
idea. Um now there's an additional thing
which if you have the kale penalty then
you actually regorize towards a
reference model which is changing even
slower than this outside model. So the
the way this is written is actually
slightly different than um the GRPL
code. In the code, you actually have
three loops. I only have two because I'm
sort of just updating the reference
model. Um you know uh you know a little
bit kind of infrequently
and I'm also not doing you know this
part.
Okay. Okay, so there's a there's a few
implementation details, but hopefully
you could kind of get the rough shape of
what this looks like.
So you actually have kind of three
models. You have the reference model
that you're doing KO regularization
against and then you have the old model
which you're using to compute these like
kind of importance ratios between the
current model and the old model which
you're also freezing and then you're um
you know kind of updating
uh you know the current model online.
So one kind of annoying thing about the
reference model is that you actually
have to um store a whole copy of the of
the model which is um can be you know
just doubles your memory. The old model
is actually a little bit, you know,
better because you just remember if um
in the code you actually don't have to
copy the old model, you can just
generate a bunch of responses and
compute the log props on those responses
and just store the log probabilities
because those are going to be you're
dealing with the same responses in an
inner loop. So you don't have to store a
whole copy of the model. You just have
to store the log props.
Okay. Question.
Why don't we do K divergence between old
policy and the latest policy instead of
So question is why don't you do the kale
penalty against uh the old instead of
the reference. Um
the way to think about this is that um
you
let's see so remember how we said we
define objective function in
reinforcement learning and we optimize
that. It's sort of a little bit of a lie
um because really you just define this
objective function so you can compute a
gradient and the gradient you you
compute and you update for a while um uh
but then your kind of objective function
changes right so um so really you can
think about um let's say uh
so this point you fix a reference model
and then you write down this nice
objective function which is um um let's
see if I I don't have the full
expression here but um
you know the expected reward with all
the you know the the um
expected reward and then the KL you know
penalty um so if you change that too
quickly then it's I guess the more you
change that then the less you're
actually like optimizing that objective
function. Um
so so that's I guess maybe one kind of
reason. Um I mean honestly I think you
know empirically um you know you it's
sort of a gradient because depending on
how you how many steps you take here and
how often you can make it either more
like um pi old or less like pi old. Um I
mean you sort of have two kind of
mechanisms for regularization. One is
the clipping thing which is applied to
pi old and then the k which is applied
to py ref.
Okay.
Yeah. Question
for the first iteration of for the most
inner loop isn't pi theta old equal to
pi theta is it like small to do that? So
the first iteration pi old is equal to
pi theta.
So you're essentially going to well
you're still performing an update.
Uh you're just scaling by some remember
pi old is from the point of view of the
update is just a constant. Um and I
guess the point only thing that matters
is that you're not going to get clipped
because the ratio is one. So you're just
going to guarantee to make an update.
So yeah, it it's fine.
Okay, so maybe just just kind of round
this out um a bit.
So uh actually so I'm run some
experiments. So you run the same piece
of code that I uh presented. I'm going
to do 100 epochs. Number of steps for
epoch is 10. Um and we see um this kind
of learning curve. Um so just to maybe
walk through what this is uh doing. Um
so on epoch0 we have this prompt the
responses it generates a bunch of stuff.
Um you score them you compute the reward
and then you compute the you know the
delta. In this case it's identical to
the reward. So I'm going to update
towards the threes a little bit more
than you know the twos. Um, and then you
see, um, you know, this prompt, you
know, kind of the same thing. This one,
um, I'm still going to update against
all these,
um, towards these, uh, responses even
though they all have reward three. Um,
and then let me scroll down and see what
happens. um you know eventually
um
you see that
um I'm getting reward three um but you
know this is not you know looking I mean
it's not really sorting is a short um
answer it's it's producing numbers which
are sort of more or less in the prompt
but um not really uh sorting let's see
if it how it does at the
So it's it's not terribly great. Um
um I actually haven't looked at the
other examples, so it'll be uh exciting
to see what happens here. Um so here
we're using the centered rewards. Um and
see the the mean reward is getting
higher. So it's like, you know, past
three instead of two, which is uh is
promising. Um so let's look at this this
run. So notice here that um I generate
some examples reward
is two and three but because I'm
centering I'm sort of giving pushing the
model towards the ones with reward three
and away from the ones that have reward
two. So this is what centering uh is is
doing. Um, and if they're, you know, all
the same, then centering doesn't really,
um, is actually going to be a noop.
Whereas before I was performing updates,
um, which is which is kind of silly, I
think, because if you think about it,
I'm sorting one, two, three, and here
all the responses are, you know, equally
bad. So updating towards this, these
don't really maybe make as much sense.
Um, let's see towards the end how this
does. Um,
so still not I guess it's not great, but
it's got a little bit higher reward. I
probably need to tune this a little bit
more. Um, but at least it's getting um,
you know, reward four here for getting
the right numbers. And 01 is, you know,
it's not the most unsorted. Um,
um, here I'm I think it's sort of
getting the permutation right. And here
I think it just gets stuck. Um, and at
this point you see all the deltas are
zero. So like more training isn't really
going to help on this batch. But if you
regenerate, uh, maybe you'll get some
fresh samples and be able to update. So
you can see that it's kind of like the
partial reward is is sort of
double-edged sword, right? Because I'm
giving you four points. So it's like
it's, you know, it's good reward. Um,
but I still didn't solve the problem,
you know, completely. So I think you
have to be careful with uh you know
reward dishing out reward. And then
finally the standardiz the normalization
here didn't really do all that much so
I'm going to skip it. Um, one one thing
to I think note is that if you look at
these loss curves, um, you think, well,
this looks kind of good, but why is this
like looks pretty bad even though the
reward is going up? And this is goes
back to kind of my statement that
minimizing the loss is a little bit of a
lie here. Um it's not like we were min
minimizing one loss function that you
can measure over time because the set of
responses is changing over time. You
don't have really kind of a reference
point for the same loss. I mean you can
measure loss on some maybe some
validation set. Um but but if you only
have rewards then you're sort of back to
only being able to rely on reward
because even think think about it even
if you um if you have
uh a bunch of examples where you're um
the model is just happy generating them.
It's sort of like the loss is only
respect to what the model is generating.
So it's a kind of a self circular thing.
So monitoring the loss is um not really
kind of a so such a meaningful thing uh
to do.
Okay. So maybe just to wrap up here. Um
so you know reinforcement learning just
popping back up. I think it's really
exciting because it's really I think the
the key to making models that actually
you know surpass you know human
abilities in some sense because um label
data is only going to get you as far as
mimicking the behavior that's presented
in the label data. Um you know I think
the model is if you can measure it you
can optimize it if you have a reward. Um
I think there's you know optimization as
we've seen even with this sorting
examples I mean is can be challenging in
itself but there's also a perhaps a
bigger problem is you know how do you
design rewards that are not hackable in
environments that are you know
generalizable I think that's a pretty
active area investigation for the
optimization part I mean you know the
sorting isn't that hard I think I just
ran it for like 20 seconds on my laptop
so you don't you shouldn't expect
greatness. Um I think uh you know just
review the policy gradient framework I
think is conceptually clear. You write
down the expected reward. You subtract a
baseline. It's the same thing and then
you just you know take an you try to
find a um you know estimate of of that
uh um reward or advantage. Um and that's
one thing that we didn't talk about
which I think is actually important and
maybe next year I should try to do a bit
more of this is that building our
systems and scaling is actually much
much more complicated than you know
pre-training and the reason is that you
have to do inference um and inference is
its own can of worms you also have to
manage multiple models so you have the
policy you're training you have um if
you have PO then you have the critic
Um if you have um you know the inference
and you have maybe a inference worker
then you need to ship the model over
there to run the inference. Um if you
have like an agent environment you have
like the environment which requires
spinning up and then on top of that you
also have like the pi old and pi ref. So
you have multiple models that you need
to keep around and on top of that you
have to do everything kind of in
parallel and distributed and make it all
uh sing and dance. So there's a lot um
to be done there which you know we're
not really going to have time to talk
about in this class but if you're
interested you know there's definitely
pointers I can um send you to. All right
so that's it and see you next time.