Okay. Um so we'll get started. Uh
welcome to lecture 15. Um we've got two
pieces left to the class and that's
going to be you know various aspects of
post-training. Um, up until now we
focused very much on the big
pre-training systems data components and
then now we're going to take the big
pre-trained model and we're going to
make it useful and safe in various ways.
So that's going to be the next two
lectures from me. Today is going to be
RLHF and sort of um safety alignment
stuff and then uh Thursday is going to
be uh RL from um verifiable rewards. So
things like reasoning training and math
and so on uh will be on Thursday. As I
said before, today we're going to shift
from pre-training to post-training. Um
Percy in the very last lecture did cover
some stuff about post-training data. Um
but really I think you know the focus
today is going to be in going from you
know essentially this big transition
that we saw in the field right so we
have GPT3 uh really remarkable system
really impressive um lots of
pre-training lots of compute but this is
not really a useful system right I guess
there was a couple startups around you
know building um ad copy and things like
that but it was not very useful it
didn't follow instructions it didn't you
know do anything particularly too
interesting from a from a product point
of view And then all of a sudden, you
know, we got chat GPT. Um, and chat GPT
can do all sorts of amazing things and
follow instructions. And we've kind of
seen what that that has done to society
since then, right? So today's focus is
going to be on this arrow right here,
like how do we take a pre-trained system
like GPT3 and how do we make something
like chat GPT? And then we're going to
try to get to the to the nuts and bolts
of that process. Um, and I think many
most of you, you know, have never, you
know, worked on things like controllable
generation or like the previous
generation of of text generation
systems, but really like modern
instruction following models are just
amazing, right? Like this is one of my
favorite examples from um Sebastian
Bubck's uh sparks of AGI paper in in
2023 um around when GBD4 came out. Um
but you know it can follow this like
very long block of like nested compound
instructions um and then combine that
with its coding capability to output you
know zero shot um mapplot lib code um
and I think all of you just like take
this for granted now it's like yes of
course chat GPD can follow 10
instructions at once um but it's just
kind of amazing that it can do this
right and I think part of my my
excitement about this lecture is the
fact that it can do all of this um and
the other thing that I think is very
important right is that now that these
systems are out in the wild. Um, safety
and content moderation just becomes
really important, right? Safety from the
perspective of, you know, these models
might get misused. Someone might try to
use them for scams. Um, and also content
moderation, if you're thinking about
these this being like useful products
that you can like ship and like people
would pay for, right? Like people don't
really want to to pay for or put ads on
um systems that are like horrifically
toxic, right? Right? Like I think one of
the big big reasons why chat GBT has
been so successful is that you know it
has really significant guard rails
around it. So okay given that the goal
today is to try to enable much tighter
better controls on language models right
um pre-training you can think of mental
the mental model can be um that it packs
the model with all sorts of capabilities
right like after pre-training the model
is able to somewhere within the
parameters do lots of things like reason
and answer questions um but it's not
going to do them out of the box and so
today what we're going to try to do is
get models to do that out of the
Um, and so what we're going to do is to
collect data of various kinds of
behaviors that we do want from the
language model. Um, and train it to do
those things, right? And so the
questions that you should be asking now
is, you know, what does that data look
like? How hard is it to collect that
data? Um, Percy has touched on it a
little bit, but given the importance of
data, I'm going to re-emphasize it a
little bit. I'm going to have some
interactive um some exercises uh to go
over that. Um, and then there's
algorithmic questions like how do we me
make use of that data, right? Um certain
kinds of data are easy to use. Um like
you know if you have expert
demonstrations you just train to imitate
that. But if you have things like pair
wise feedback like model output A is
better than model output B. How do we
how do we make use of that? And then
finally like you know how do we scale
this up? How do we do the usual things
that we've been doing in this class? So
um the structure of this lecture is
roughly going to mirror the instruct GPT
paper because a lot of the post-training
pipeline that we have today is still off
the instruct GPT paper. Um and so the
first part of this is uh lecture is
going to be um on supervised
fine-tuning. So if you look at um the
instru GPD paper, you'll see this this
diagram that roughly describes a
three-step process uh for building an
instruction following model. Um so part
one of this lecture is going to be the
leftmost part, the part where what we're
going to do is we're going to do
supervised fine-tuning on expert
demonstration and then part two we're
going to follow the next two parts uh of
this structure. We're going to talk
about reinforcement learning and pair
wise feedback loop.
Um, broadly, um, I'm going to say that
the ingredients, um, in order to get,
you know, this first part working, I
mean, there's two things that we have to
kind of think about. Um, the first part
is the training data, right? If you're
going to imitate expert demonstrations,
you better have expert demonstrations.
Like, what does that look like? Um, and
then the second thing I want to talk
about is kind of the method. Like, you
you have data now. Like, how are you
going to adapt to it? Um, and there's an
obvious answer. I'll, you know, talk
about this again, but like just do
gradient descent. Um, but there's also a
kind of nonobvious part to this answer.
And, you know, in case you haven't been
following how people build these models
today, this might, you know, be still
surprising. So, I'll I'll I'll leave
that as a teaser for later. So, okay.
So, in Percy's lecture, you know, he's
mentioned already several different
kinds of instruction data, but today
we're going to like walk through a
couple of them, and we're going to do a
little bit of an interactive exercise.
So you know those of you who have your
laptops open can use those for good. Um
so I want to talk about two different
details like one of them is what's
inside these data sets. Um people often
say data matters a lot. I think post-
trainining is is one place where this is
even more true than before. Um because
you're using very small amounts of data
to get exactly the behaviors you want.
So if you have noisy instruction tuning
data, you're going to get some pretty
crazy behavior out of your models. Um
and then what kinds of things should we
be paying attention to? if you're in
charge of of post- training data
collection, what kinds of things might
matter? So, um I have taken three
different data sets um from basically
constructed in three very different ways
like you might also you might even call
them like kind of three different
paradigms um to building instruction
following or post- training data. Um and
we're going to go through each one and
then we'll look at them closely and then
we'll think a little bit about what's
going on with these data sets. Okay. So,
I'm going to talk about Flan. Um this is
uh by a bunch of Google folks and Fla is
going to be um essentially constructed
by aggregating a bunch of uh training
data sets from NLP tasks right so if you
look at it you know you see all sorts of
different tasks like you know natural
instructions v2 which has a bunch of you
know question answering and things it's
got T0 SF you know adversarial QA and
like topic classification so basically
this this was constructed by taking
existing NLP data sets
um that do all sorts of individual tasks
and then aggregating them into one big
metadata set. Right? So this is one
approach to building such data sets. Um
we've got open assistant on the right.
Um and this was I think a pretty unique
uh sort of endeavor in which a bunch of
online enthusiasts got together and
decided to write instruction tuning data
um for language models. Like right after
the release of chat GPT I think the
excitement for this kind of thing was
really high. And so there's actually a
lot of good high quality human written
data from that effort. And lastly, and
you know, of course, this is this is a
bit of self- advertisement here, but um
as a representative of the kind of like
language model generated post-training
data or like AI feedback style data, I'm
going to talk a little bit about um some
of the data from Stanford alpaca. Um so
let's just look at examples, right? Like
I think looking at examples and talking
about them are very useful. Um now this
is from random examples taken from the
FL data set. Um, and you can kind of see
the types of stuff uh that are in here.
Um, so you know, you've got things that
look like pretty normal instruction
tuning data like write highlights for
this article. Sauntering down leafy
avenues past Dutch stepgable buildings
dot dot dot dot dot. And then you know
in in the end there's even like more
information on travel in the Netherlands
at www.holland.com.
And then it answers you know the least
known of the Dutch cities, the hug was a
village dot dot dot dot. Um, and then it
it sort of summarizes, you know, this as
a highlight. Um, you know, you've got
something like this, uh, where, you
know, this is like what is this text
about? Here are your four options. It's
business, right? Um, so this is kind of
a multiplechoice training, uh, thing
that's happening. um this you know uh
Pissy talked about the Enron data set so
you all can like you know smile a little
bit but things like this of of taking
let's say maybe the Enron email data set
and you you paste back write a subject
line for this email and now you've got
kind of supervision for that task right
um this one um I guess no one here has
probably worked on uh text generation
but this is from a data set called E2E
where you have like a database entry and
then you're supposed to write a sentence
um that describes uh that restaurant so
immediately you kind of see you know you
can probably get a lot of data for free
this way, right? There's a lot of NLP uh
training data sets and you can like put
them all together um and you will get a
really big aggregated data set. And so
in that sense, FOMO was a you know ahead
of its time and produced a ton of data
for this kind of thing. But also we see
in many ways that this can be somewhat
unnatural, right? Like we can we've
already seen that like this Enron data
set is a little bit weird. we can really
definitely see things like, oh, here's a
text and then now you sort of append
sort of the options to turn it into a
task. And so you can kind of see the
surgery that you have to do uh very
visibly in order to um make this kind of
data set. And I think if you look at
this, you'll you'll agree with me that
this isn't your usual chat interaction,
right, for for something like chat GP.
Um another example for this um is uh
Alpaca. This was like a really really
early um uh attempt at using language
models to generate instruction tuning
data. Um and so you know just to
describe the procedure here you know a
language model was used um there was a
seat set of human written instructions
and then the language model was used to
essentially generate more instructions.
So that's the left column. And then you
use something like instruct GPT to
essentially fill in the response, right?
And so here, you know, now we have
something that looks a little bit more
like, you know, on the left standard um
sort of chat GBD inputs. If you compare
this to um something on the left, this
is a very benchmark ccentric set of
tasks. This feels a lot more like a set
of interactions that someone might just
throw into a chatbot. Um and the
response is almost always in long form
natural language versus with fla often
it can be quite short like one word or a
phrase or something like that right so
we kind of see that of course you know
we also see that on the left these are
in some ways not very diverse inputs
they're very short instructions um and
then open assistant is kind of the third
leg of this instruction tuning saga um
you kind of see more complex queries on
the left and then because Back then, I
guess people were just really um into
writing long detailed uh supervision for
models. You see like actually really
detailed responses and this one even has
a citation on uh you know how like what
what makes this answer correct, right?
Um and so, you know, very high quality
but also kind of very difficult. And so,
um now this is this is the first
interactive task in this class. Um but
especially those of you that have your
laptops open, um you know, please go to
this URL. This should be a Google form.
Um, and there will be a sort of one sort
of uh sort of prompt. Um, and now we're
collectively going to crowdsource
um a instruction tuning response. And
I'll give you all let's say five minutes
um to do so. Let me know if the if the
link is wrong, but I I did test this
last night. So hopefully this is uh uh
working and then we'll look at the the
responses briefly. Um and then uh I want
to talk about why I did this exercise.
There there is a a teachable moment here
rather than sort of getting you just off
your laptops for a moment.
Okay, excellent. Um I think I think
there's a decent number of responses, so
I'm going to um maybe put them up. Uh
let's see if I can put them up then.
Yeah, there we go. Okay. Um so in in
many ways, I think this reflects the
kinds of data you get. I mean, if
anything, you guys are all motivated to
do this task than I think the the
standard crowd worker, you know, but
you've got the person. I mean, I I'm not
sure what's going on here, but this is
probably chat GPT. There's a lot of
emojis. Um, I'm I'm getting trolled, but
this is I mean, I am preparing for lift
thoughts. Uh, that's good uh response.
Um, you've got, you know, the nafam,
which, you know, of course is the kinds
of things that you'll get out of crowd
sourcing. Um, and I think hopefully one
thing that that you've seen or like felt
as you were doing this is that it's
actually really difficult to write long
form responses, right? Especially for
something that you aren't prepared for,
right? Um, and so, you know, you get a
lot of short responses like this. It's
very difficult, I think, to get people
to write sort of long detailed, you
know, responses like this one at the
very top. Um, often those uh kinds of
things are um, you know, uh, from
Chachibbe. And of course, you'll get
things like, you know, I saw this one.
Ice cream is a frozen dessert typically
made from milk or cream. And you're
going to have to, you know, filter out
those kinds of things that you're going
to get um through, uh, crowd sourcing.
So, um, why did I, um,
talk about this? Well, of course, you
know, now you have a sense of what this
task is like. Annotators in the wild,
even if they're experts, will be under
time constraints. Um, and I think one of
the reasons why, you know, things like
like AI feedback or using LMS to try to
refine or generate these kinds of data
has really gotten popular is, you know,
if you look at the GPT40 response um to
this, you know, it's it's pretty good.
Um, it's a pretty good response to this
question. It's very long. It's very
detailed. Um, and generating this this
kind of a human uh response is going to
take a lot of effort and a lot of cost,
right? And so you have to, you know, if
you're in charge of human data
collection at one of these labs, you
have to think about, okay, like how do
we take, you know, what I showed you in
the spreadsheet and incentivize people
to generate something that looks like
this instead. That is no easy task um at
all. That is a very difficult um
crowding task. Okay? And so um these
things that we've we've just seen um
they vary quite a bit um in things like
length. Um we saw you know the chat GPM
which is bullet points like lots of
style variations. Um we saw in the uh
open assistant example that you know
sometimes people put in references um
sometimes they put in sort of very
complex deep knowledge like is that good
or bad? I'll talk about that in a
moment. Um and there's also other
important aspects to this process right
like maybe you want to collect a ton of
data or very little data that's high
quality. So you got this trade-off. Um,
you also have to think a lot about
safety, right? Like the the data that we
collected just now, that's just
capabilities data, right? It just makes
models answer things like what is CS36?
It does not help us make our models, you
know, um, you know, uh, refuse uh,
malicious instructions and things like
that. So, we have to think a little bit
about what that kind of data looks like,
too. Okay. Um, I think length has always
been a big kind of gorilla in the room
issue for all of these data sets. um you
know when uh back in 2023 when it was
very very popular to generate these
kinds of instruction tuning data sets um
there's a survey like Ejong Wong and
others at UDub came up with this very
nice survey coming looking over the many
different kinds of data sets that were
created um early in that year um and you
kind of see if you look at the length um
of both the prompts so that's the inputs
and the responses the completions you
see like really different lengths of
both inputs and outputs and inputs are
probably a measure of sort of complexity
of the task um in many ways and then the
outputs are in some sense a measure of
how you know much you push the
annotators or if you used AI generated
responses um and one of the things that
that you should be you know all aware of
you know let's say you got put in charge
of making a new language model you're in
charge of post- training well you know
if you're using human evals uh people
have a strong preference for lists I
mean so do actually if you use AI as a
judge they also have a strong preference
for lists um And people have a very long
preference for outputs, like 60 70%ish
preference for longer outputs. Um, and
so do sort of AI judges, right? And so
this is this is a little concerning um
because you want to be optimizing for
not just kind of the stylistic content
of your uh responses, you ideally want
to be using post- training to do things
like reduce hallucinations um and
actually make the model hopefully more
capable. Um
one thing that we do see is that you
know these factors are not super
relevant for benchmark performance. So
if you look at for example MMLU
performance um kind of despite the the
really big variation um in length for a
lot of these models um most of the the
instruction tuning data sets like the
simple ones you know give you boosts
over kind of the base model which is the
the very top row um above. So I think
one of the things that I'll say here is
you know chat style evaluations have
their place you know chatbot arena
alpaca eval these kinds of automated you
know eval
like user engagement and things like
this but benchmarks also have a very
important place um because when you post
train you don't necessarily want to be
too affected by for example length
biases and open-ended domains and so on
um and so you want to be really careful
of these effects. You want to have a
different diverse array of evaluation
strategies to try to avoid those
pitfalls.
Um, one other thing that I think really
trips people up when they initially
start thinking about these things is to
say, "Oh, what I'm doing is I want to
collect highquality data and highquality
data has lots of deep knowledge and has
lots of citations, right?" Like that's a
reasonable thing to say. Um, and I
think, you know, open assistant, I
think, had a great example of this,
right? Um, and so here's an example
input output pair. Um, you know, you've
got right introduction about monopsin
economics. um and then there's these
references um on the response on the
right. So now let's say we have a model
and we fine-tune the model to take the
left side as input and reproduce the
right side as output. Right? So um you
can kind of think about two different
things that this process is going to do
at the same time. Right? So one of the
things that this is going to do is it's
going to associate you know uh monopsin
with that citation. Right? So it's
learning new knowledge. So that is good.
Right? that is a positive thing to do.
Um, but it's also going to do a second
thing at the same time, which is this
kind of generalized thing of saying if
you ask me a complicated concept, I had
better finish the output with a
reference, right? And so it's it's
basically the sec the first thing is
teaching new knowledge, which is good,
but the second thing here is kind of
teaching the model to hallucinate,
right? like if the model doesn't already
have somewhere within its parameters an
association between monopsin and uh this
citation this uh bivven's initial book
um you know what might happen instead is
it just learns that oh what I should do
is whenever I have a complicated input I
should give a response and then make up
a reference at the very end right those
are two competing explanations for what
is happening here um and this is going
to motivate in some ways the second part
of this lecture right um John Schulman
has this kind of great talk I think he
gave it at Berkeley um where you know
his argument is um basically if you do
this kind of thing you're going to
encourage the model to hallucinate right
like the model doesn't have the
knowledge of answering a question you
force it to answer that question what
it's going to learn is of course it'll
learn the knowledge in some abstract
sense but it will also learn the other
aspect of I just need to make something
up in order to sort of type check what
the response should look like okay yes
there's a question question so human
right
one writing has a sense of like okay I
think I need to add a citation here let
me search for another citation either
from memory or let me actually use a
database it is the fact that like the
LLM is learning that like okay here I
should insert a citation is actually a
correct and desirable thing and it's and
the fact that it's a madeup citation is
a either a memory issue or b something
you can maybe augment a tool usage in
the site but like I don't see why the
behavior of needing to add a citation
itself self is problematic whe like if
you can either fix the memory issue or
the tool user issue. Sure. I mean I
think the Okay, so to to repeat the
question, the question was like I guess
that was a more comment than a question.
Um was that the the uh learning to put
in a citation isn't a bad thing, right?
Like I mean maybe you augment it with
tools and it'll actually give the right
citation. I mean, that's a fair point,
but I think the thing to to maybe point
out here is like the the deeper
conceptual or not conceptual, the deeper
issue with token prediction, right, is
that you're teaching the model to kind
of predict the right kinds of tokens.
And here, you know, essentially the the
lesser of the two errors is to say
hallucinating is less bad for my loss
than not making up the reference at all,
right? kind of the the structure of the
the response always has to be fulfilled
because you have to fill the tokens in
at the right places, right? Of course,
at scale, if you know the facts, if you
have the right tools, right, those are
those are good. You want to kind of make
the predictions on the right spaces. Um,
but I do kind of think this is very
indicative of this like this uh failure
mode that models can get into where
you're trying to get it to do things
that it can't, right? like if your SFT
data is just much more advanced than
what your pre-trained model naturally
can do, um you run this risk of teaching
the model kind of this alternative
shortcut behavior instead of teaching
models the right behavior. Um yeah, so
so that's John Schulman. Um I think he
makes a a fairly reasonable case that
you know this is one of the reasons why
like on policy RL like reinforcement
learning style things is an important
thing to do because you want to know
what the model already knows and only
teach it those things to avoid you know
hallucinating and whenever it it's
encountering some fact that it doesn't
know then maybe you should change your
fine-tuning data to say oh I don't know
that fact instead of forcing the model
to try to answer right um and we kind of
see this um on the on the kind of other
sort of uh sort of knowledge storage
studies as well. Um where people have
kind of talked about, you know, it's
much easier for models to sort of
reproduce known facts um than sort of uh
to to learn sort of unknown facts where
it just takes a lot longer um for models
to kind of learn facts that aren't shown
in pre-training. And this sort of is is
sort of matching uh what you might
expect from these phenomena. So, okay.
Um I think one of the things that I'll
sort of you know summarize that with is
that there's a very counterintuitive
phenomenon for instruction tuning which
is that you know you can have a
instruction tuning data set that is
fully correct and like actually very
rich but actually that might not be good
for your LM because it's going to teach
your your language model um to sort of
try to make up facts to match that depth
of knowledge. That's always been, I
think, one of the arguments for why you
want to be really careful with both
distillation data where the the dis uh
teacher model is stronger than your
student model. And also really human uh
annotation where the human might be much
more knowledgeable um than the model,
right? You want to be really careful to
make the model abstain nicely when it
doesn't know things. Um and in
principle, you know, reinforcement
learning style correctness could help
and we'll talk about that in a moment.
um and sort of optimizing this at the at
the instruction tuning level is just
really messy and very difficult. I don't
think people have really nailed it down
um at least in the open research
literature.
Um the other thing I want to talk about
um briefly because I think this isn't
necessarily um something that can be
solved with um instruction tuning alone
um is you know to to touch on safety um
and to think a little bit about what the
trade-offs are here. So, we know, you
know, language models um need some
guardrails. They're deployed straight to
end users. They're very capable. So,
they might be used for misinformation or
for generating things like scams or
spam. Um and so there's a need for in uh
safety tuning um these models. And I
think in parallel with a lot of the
research on instruction tuning, there's
been um actually quite a bit of of work
studying safety tuning as well. Um and I
think some of the early work um in this
in this area um you know kind of has
shown that even a small amount of sort
of safety tuning data that's mixed in uh
to to instruction tuning process can
make models uh much safer. Sort of
paralleling a lot of the findings that
people had that actually for instruction
tuning as well if you have a strong
enough pre-trained model even a small
amount of instruction tuning data can
can get you a lot of the way. Um not to
say that's sufficient um but actually
that's you know um sort of gets you to a
reasonable point.
Um, and I think the core trade-off with
safety tuning that I'll sort of touch on
um, in this brief section is this
trade-off between refusing things and
not refusing kind of too much, right?
Um, so there's always this thing of, you
know, if you have unsafe responses, you
want your safety tuned model to just
refuse to answer. And then maybe you
have these other, you know, actually
safe responses, but things that look
like unsafe responses, like how can I
kill a Python process, right? Um, we all
know that is a reasonable question to
ask. But I guess if you're not, you
know, if you don't understand English
very deeply, you're like, oh, killing,
killing sounds very dangerous, so maybe
I should refuse to answer that question,
right? Um, so how can you make models
sort of understand this nuance? It's a
very tricky thing to do um you know
purely in the instruction tuning
setting. Um and so a lot of what people
have done is come up with carefully
curated small instruction tuning data
sets to try to balance this trade-off.
Um so even um some research has shown
that even like 500 examples can make
models follow uh some of the safety
guidelines um well so okay um to put
this together um instruction tuning is
surprisingly powerful. I think you know
you would think that given how powerful
things like chat GPT are that there's
actually a ton of complexity into
getting anything that works. I think
you'll find that even if you take you
know a fairly standard instruction
tuning data set like open Hermes or um
open assistant or any of these data sets
and you take a base model and you
fine-tune on it with reasonable
hyperparameters, you'll get a model that
behaves a lot like llama or chat GPT. It
won't be quite as good. there's a lot of
of uh extra work you need to do to
optimize it, but you can get pretty far.
Um the second thing that's you know good
to remember is basically it the notion
of high quality data is just very
complex and you have to reason about it
really carefully. Um it's not obvious
how to do and then the last thing is you
know actually even a small amount of
data can have great leverage at this
stage in changing how models um behave.
The last thing I want to end this
section on is um how to do this
instruction tuning. Um there's kind of a
you know a flippant answer to this which
is well you've got demonstrations um
just put in the instruction and the
response and just do some gradient
descent, right? We all know how to do
gradient descent at this point. Um and I
think in most academic settings that's
basically it, right? Like you're done.
You do your small scale um gradient
descent and you're done. But I think if
you're at like a frontier lab and you've
got more compute and you've got more
money than you know what to to do with,
then you've got a lot of compute and
you've got a lot of data. Um, and so you
can scale this whole process up quite a
bit. Like you can scale it up a lot. And
modern instruction tuning pipelines um
are starting to look a lot like
pre-training pipelines. Um, and so
increasingly the boundaries between uh
pre-training and instruction tuning are
just getting blurred. Um, because if you
think about it, instruction tuning data
is still a sequence, right? It's just a
sequence of tokens. And so I can throw
that in into my pre-training process and
that's a totally valid thing to do. Um,
and so this is an increasingly popular
idea. Um I think you know the close labs
don't tell us anything but you know I
think uh the things that people have
tell me um in bits and pieces suggest
that this is you know what they're
doing. Um a lot of the open groups from
China do basically this now um and so
what you do is you have your you know
usual pre-training setting right you do
pure pre-training and then what you're
going to do is you're going to start um
mixing in instruction tuning data into
pre-training. So the kind of the tail
end of your pre-training, especially as
you're kind of annealing the learning
rate, um you're going to start putting
in a lot of this higher quality data or
instruction tuning data. Um and then in
the end, you might actually do a second
short instruction tuning round, but
maybe this is smaller because most of
your data has already gone into to the
second stage, what people call um
mid-training. Um and this is cool
because it lets you scale up without uh
catastrophic forgetting issues. You
might get more leverage out of your data
because it's integrated more deeply into
pre-training. Um, and to give you an
example or a sense of what this looks
like, um, and it's a bit of a shame
that, uh, data mixes are often pretty,
um, closely guarded secrets by a lot of
the groups. Um, so I've taken this
figure from, um, mini CPM, which we've
talked about before, um, great paper
from one of the Chinese groups, where
basically they have, you know, a
two-stage training pipeline where they
have a first stage where they do pure
pre-training. And if you look at this
pie chart, this is all pre-training data
sets. Common crawl uh code pre-training
pile dolma. They they've thrown it all
in into one big uh pie. Um and then they
have a second stage uh which they call
the decay stage. And so if you remember
my lecture on scaling laws, you know, I
talked about WSD, warm-up, stable,
decay. Uh so that's the stable stage.
That's the decay stage. And in the decay
stage, what have we got? We've got um
you know, Wikipedia, what people might
call high quality data. We've got still
the pre-training stuff mixed in there.
So, it's not pure post-training data.
But then if you look at the right, we've
got code SFT, we've got um Chinese
books, we've got ultra chat, we've got
stack exchange question answering and
and uh evil instruct and OSS instruct
and all sorts of other things. Um, so
those are all kind of instruction tuning
or instruction tuning adjacent data sets
that you've thrown in onto the second
half uh of pre-training. Um, and it's I
think used by most models today. Um, and
many CPM and other sort of you know
derived LMS that are derived from that
lineage of models um are have definitely
sort of publicized this um I think it's
it's extremely effective uh to do this
and so I think everyone has been
following this. Um one last commentary
I'll make before we move on to RHF here
um is that uh this whole process makes
it very very difficult to reason about
pre-trained models versus post-trained
models. Right? If you look at recent
releases from like Quen or what whatever
other companies that you're looking at
and they say base model um you know that
base model is probably at the end of you
know this process and so it has
basically gone through an instruction
tuning phase uh implicitly through its
mid-training process. Um we don't
exactly know what the mixes are for for
a lot of these closed models but it does
actually mean that I think the term base
models is increasingly uh questionable
what that really means. Um so that's my
sort of side comment that is useful for
you if you're if you're thinking about
base models so yes
the data mixture you change it during
the decaying stage like when you have
linear activity it goes to zero that's
when you get like these big loss is that
like directly totally it's seen in that
lasting stage. Yeah. So that's right. Um
that was the motivation for a lot of the
the two-phase training for for these um
groups. Like they basically use uh
essentially the large drop in loss as a
way to try to anneal the model into the
right you know mode. Um I think there's
you know increasing studies into like
what's the optimal point at which to
switch um and I think it's a little bit
more nuanced than that but I think a
first order this has been a very
effective recipe. Yes.
between lending one has trouble
computing or I'm trying to think about
the incentive citization thing from
earlier does this also have that yeah so
the I guess there were two questions
packed in one but the the question was
like is uh this primarily for
catastrophic forgetting and also um does
this help with the citations issue um so
to to answer the second part first I
think it doesn't help with the citation
issue because you know just as sort of
like a type signature The only things
that can help with the the citation
issue is if you know what facts the
model knows, right? So you have to
either ensure that the model like always
knows the citation facts before you show
it the SFD data or um you have to like
check to see if the model knows it and
then show it that that uh data if it if
it does know it, right? Which this
doesn't do. This will always
unconditionally put in those data points
whether or not that citation is learned.
So it has no way of of fixing that
adaptively. um catastrophic forgetting
wise, I think that is one of the the
motivations that um if you have so much
SFP data, um your trade-offs are pretty
tricky, right? Because unless you're
going to do this kind of almost
pre-training mixed in with
post-training, you have to think about
regularization. You have to think about
tiny step sizes to avoid, you know,
messing up your pre-training. And so I
think this is um partially motivated by
uh sort of catastrophic forgetting
adjacent issues. It keeps the model sort
of more more general.
Yes,
I understand um with the with the John
Dolman example um foration
is that if the model doesn't know the
reference that's included in the post
training data that it know it does know
that fact then it would not have the
same behavior. That's right. Or that's
the that's the claim, right? um that if
the model did know um you know this
citation that's right here um then the
model wouldn't necessarily out of these
two sort of competing mechanisms um what
it would learn is oh whenever I see this
example I should retrieve you know my
knowledge about you know bivvens and
Michelle L um and then use that as a
citation um I think the the reality of
this is that it's always very
complicated right like what does it mean
for a model to know something how
reliably does it know something um and
So these two kind of mechanisms are
always maybe in superp position for a
model. It's really just a question of
which one is more dominant. Like if a
model just has no idea about this, it's
probably two that is, you know, more
dominant. Whereas I think if the model
knows it reliably, it's more likely that
it's just going to learn the correct
citation rather than encouraging broad
general hallucinations.
Yes. Have people tried putting into all
of the pre- data some kind of thought
tokens that tell the model? Oh, I should
this looks like a fact. Let me check if
I actually know it. And so I'm going to
query myself, you know, and check if I'm
if I'm getting consistent answers. And
if so, I'll I'll print out right. So in
the entire pre-training process process,
I need to check myself. Okay. Um that is
a very interesting idea. So just to
repeat it, it's um has anyone done
something where you put in like kind of
thought tokens or the model's checking
itself for its knowledge of facts as it
trains or something like that? Right. Is
that roughly right? Yeah. Um, so
depending on how you interpret or like
implement that exact idea, it starts to
look a lot like reinforcement learning.
Um because for example there's a a
method called a quiet star um from some
folks here Noah Goodman and and Eric
Zelkman and others have done this where
they do um essentially they try to learn
the thinking process of a model um by
sort of you know predicting what happens
um on the answer token and then based on
whether or not it's correct it tries to
like you know uh reinforce the model to
have good um thought process. Actually
the the even closer analogy to this is
STAR which is the original paper which
is if the model gets something correct
then that thinking process gets fed back
into the model training and if it's
wrong then it doesn't right and it's
kind of very similar to to what you're
proposing which is to adaptively train
the model based on kind of correctness
of its its knowledge or whatever else.
I propose you just give a thought
process that say let me make use of this
tool that checks myself and I can later
at some point change what that tool is
but the point is that tool will come
with a response that says yes I do have
the knowledge no I don't and then you'
actually see that knowledge gets printed
out or doesn't depending on I see uh so
so in this like tool use example are you
imagining that um kind of the fact would
get replaced by a tool call or will the
fact still be there like I think the key
question is do you force the model to
predict the fact tokens or do you just
force it to predict uh like use the tool
to look it up on Google token? No.
You don't know what the tool how you
implement it. But you see if the tool
says I yes I do know it then the then
you there will actually be some response
printed out in the pre-training data and
if the tool says no I don't know it then
the pre- training data will just say
actually I don't know this I'm going to
skip and so right so so I think um
that's hard because when you do
pre-training like you have to know
whether you know the fact to to know
whether to take losses on that knowledge
token right like you can't defer it to
inference time because you have to
decide whether or not you're going to
take gradient steps, right? And the
other sort of logistical difficulty here
is during pre-training time um you have
a static data set where you know you for
computational reasons you would want a
static data set and if you have a static
data set you can't adaptively do updates
right like anything that solves the
hallucination problem has to be kind of
reactive of the form what does the model
know and then do I take updates on this
or not at the pre-training stage that's
very difficult um unless you're doing RL
style stuff at pre-training scale which
would get you very close to that but but
still very difficult um I'm happy to
follow But I think hopefully that
answers the the question. Oh, there's
more stuff. Yes. Okay.
So if I uh for example um um in case of
llama uh in the green data we haven't
deal with the emoji but if
you have a lot of the emojis
will cause the effect that when we start
to the model and the result model we
don't have a lot of repeating sentence
similar to emoji partners uh at the end.
Yeah. Okay. So the question was if at
pre-training we don't see emojis but at
post- training we put in a bunch of
emojis at the end what will happen? Um
it depends on the the structure of the
emojis I guess. Um if the emojis are
dependent on the inputs in a very
complex way and that's very difficult to
learn. Maybe what the model will will
learn is well in post- training what I
saw was a bunch of emojis. I don't have
enough data or training to know what the
complex pattern is. So the model will
just learn to put a bunch of random
emojis at the end. um if there's no
pattern, if there's no comp complex
dependence, then you know maybe the
model will learn to do the right thing,
which is just to put a bunch of random
emojis at the end. Um really the the key
way to think about kind of the the SFT
issues is instruction tuning will will
reliably teach the style of the output
like the type signature of the output,
right? And the model will most likely
follow that type signature at the very
least. And the real question is, do you
have enough instruction tuning data that
you could do something more than that?
And that's kind of the more complex open
question. So in your emoji case, at the
very least you'll get a bunch of emojis.
Whether those emojis are the right
emojis, open question, right? Depends on
how much instruction tuning data,
depends on pre-training, so on and so
forth.
Yes, I was wondering like uh earlier in
the lecture, I think it was said that um
the post- training part doesn't really
teach like model new knowledge, right?
It's mostly about styles and then like
the line kind of gets more blurry like
when M is like me training stage. Um so
and then he showed like the mini CPM
paper. So like in that in this sort of
new like scenario like the training part
could also instill some of new kind of
like world knowledge into your model.
Yeah that's right. So so I guess the the
question was like you know if I rephrase
it you know can instruction tuning
essentially teach new world knowledge
because mid-training blurs the line
between pre-training and instruction
tuning and we know pre-training teaches
knowledge. So why not instruction
tuning? And I think that's right that
like in some ways instruction tuning if
it's scaled up enough and it's diverse
enough will teach knowledge right but I
think instruction tuning in its like
smaller like non-midraining form it is
very difficult to have the scale and
diversity of data needed to reliably
teach you know various facts. Um I think
modern mid-raining is starting to become
a different game. Um but it's still sort
of an emerging object I think. Cool.
Okay. So now um we get to the part two,
right? So part one, this is the the
quick intro to uh instruction tuning and
SFT. Now we get to um reinforcement
learning from human feedback, right? The
RL part of this lecture. Um and
conceptually, right, and I'm going to
take it slow here because I think this
this is an important conceptual
transition, right? We're going to move
from the world of of I think generative
modeling um at the very top here which
is you know there's a very simple goal
in this world which is there's a p star
is a reference distribution from which
completions are drawn that reference
distribution probably looks like some
mixture of um you know internet data as
well as annotator written data but there
exists some abstract p star that we're
trying to imitate right that's all there
is to it um so this is pure generative
modeling now we're going to move to a
second perspective now which is um RLHF
and in this world um I no longer care
about matching any distribution right so
probabilistic perspectives kind of don't
really entirely go out the window but
you want to be careful about adopting
those because really what we're looking
for is we're really just looking for
some policy P of Y given X such that we
maximize our rewards right there's some
reward function R of Y and X that you
know take in both my completion and my
prompt and then gives me a reward and
all I'm looking for is any policy that
gives me good rewards, right? Um, and so
now LM are not necessarily a model for
some underlying distribution. They are
policies that give us good rewards. Um,
and so why would we go and do RHF? Um,
there are kind of two reasons that we
might do this. One of them is on the top
one in SFT in order to do this process
of imitation we have to get samples from
P star and that can be quite expensive,
right? Um and the second one all we need
to do is get measurements of rewards R.
Um and SFT data can just be really
really expensive. Um you know this is
kind of like a caricature of you know
various costs that you might have in
different stages right you have some
compute costs when you uh train your
base model and then you've got you're
doing like supervised learning like SFT
and then you're going to go collect a
bunch of you know pair-wise feedback and
do RL and do evaluation and so on. Um,
so when you do this, right, um, you
know, the the SFT is just really really
expensive. You're you're getting like
really expert people to write very long
form responses. And you kind of saw how
annoying and difficult that was. Um, and
Frontier Labs are going to be spending
millions on this post-training data.
Well, maybe there's a nicer way of
collecting data that makes models
better. So that's one argument for why
we're going to do all the things that
we're going to do in the second part of
this lecture.
There's also a second reason um that is
equally or maybe even more important um
that I think um you know people uh do
this kind of RL training and one of the
things that's very interesting is you
know people don't always agree with
themselves about what is good. So if you
ask somebody to write a summary um you
know they can write one summary and then
you ask them um to compare their own
summaries to LM written summaries um
there's a good amount of people that
will actually prefer LM written
summaries and this was a really
surprising result from one of my
students uh papers uh I guess two years
back now um where we were benchmarking
you know summarization systems um and
there was one person who is you know of
course anonymized annotator one who you
know um wrote a bunch of summaries and
they actually preferred you know the the
AI summaries uh actually significantly
more than their own and they're like a
freelance expert writer or something um
and we went and like interviewed them
and they were like yeah when you asked
me to write stuff I just felt like I had
to write more with like flowery language
but then I like read the the AI ones and
they just read better you know um and
I'm sure you've had similar experiences
you know where you look at the output
and it it is actually you know uh
different from your own assessment of
how to generate And so there's a, you
know, not just cheaper to to verify than
generate, but actually um maybe higher
quality to verify than to generate. And
so there's this this generator validator
gap. Okay. So we're going to cover
different aspects of uh this RHF
process. Um we're going to, you know,
talk about how we collect data and like
what are things you should worry about
if you're in charge of RHF data
collection. Um and we're going to talk
about how we do RHF. Um I'm going to
talk about two representative algorithms
PO and DPO. Um I'll defer some of the
more like detailed explanations of PO
till next lecture just for kind of space
reasons. Um and then finally we'll end
with some you know things to worry about
almost like pitfalls of RHF at the very
end here. Okay. Um so how do we get pair
wise feedback? Right. So pair wise
feedback um is oh sorry I'll I'll go
back here and just like take it a little
slower. Um, so when we do this second
part of this instruct GPT process,
right, like how does this work? Well, we
have the model sort of generate its own
outputs, right? These are rollouts in RL
terms. And then, um, we're going to
compare, you know, these different
outputs. And, and although four outputs
are shown here, um, you know, in kind of
standard settings, you often just have a
pair of outputs. And let's see, we have
A and B. All I want to know is A, is A
better than B or not, right? And then
given these pair-wise feedbacks, um, I'm
going to train a reward model that can
essentially internally give every single
output a scalar value. Um, and then just
use that to do reinforcement learning.
Like this reward model is now my rewards
and I want my model to maximize those
rewards, right? Fair fairly hopefully
simple um, pipeline. So how do we
collect pair-wise feedback data? Um
well, you know, the the the obvious
simple thing to do um is just say, okay,
like, you know, I'm just going to make
some web app. You know, I've got two
different AI responses. Um and you're
going to have a little, you know,
four-way check box that like, you know,
checks which response is better. I took
this from from one of the studies that
we did, right? All a lot of pair wise
feedback uh responses look, you know,
similar to this. But I thought, you
know, one thing that would be helpful
and useful into like actually getting a
sense of like what does this look like
for real? Um I have gone and sort of uh
dug up examples of annotation guidelines
um from different papers and different
places um sort of you know talking about
this process right so um if we look at
the instruct GPT guideline this is one
of the very few I would say um sort of
released materials from one of these
companies describing their annotation
guidelines um you know they say okay
your job is to evaluate these outputs to
ensure that they're helpful truthful and
harmless right So those are their three
pillars. Um you've got helpfulness which
is like you know writing in clear
language you know answer the question
they mean to ask like being sensitive to
to internationality like if someone says
football you know they shouldn't assume
American football. Um if it's too
confusing ask for clarifications. Um I
want you to be truthful and not
hallucinate outputs. Um and by harmless
you know um you should sort of be not
toxic and be very nice and not say NSW
things. um all fairly reasonable uh
things but you can kind of see how um
sort of there's a the interplay between
um things like the model spec which
openai publishes publicly then there's a
very detailed annotation guideline which
you know this is not that detailed it's
probably much bigger in practice um
where you would write down these kinds
of bullet points you would hand this to
annotators um and then uh they would
sort of go and and make annotations this
was you know instruct GPT is is not even
like kind of production grade this is
early days but you see how this process
kind of um works. Um the kind of other
interesting example um you can kind of
go look this one up uh later if that the
actual text is too small because I'm not
going to read through all of it. I'll
just sort of uh touch on it a bit. Um
there's actually a leaked version of the
the actual the true annotation guideline
apparently um for Google Bard um that I
think was part of some like news story.
Um and you can kind of see very very
similar things happening here, right?
We've got on the top left box like
helpfulness like you should address the
intent of the user's prompt, you should
adhere to any requirements, don't have
misleading information, like very
similar to the instruct GPD setup. Um,
you know, we've got actually here a
style box which is, you know, what kinds
of style are good or bad. Um, and then
we've got, you know, different rating
scales uh for the different responses.
Um and if I remember right, I think uh
the Google bard folks I think gets like
a minute per question to be doing this
task which is which is quite difficult.
Um okay and then uh for instruct GPT you
know they go through like scale and
upwork and they collect about uh data
from about 40 people like this is really
really tiny um sort of by today's
standards but hopefully you kind of get
a sense of you know what types of groups
are being involved here. Okay, so this
is the second part of our uh interactive
exercise.
Okay, cool. Um, so that's five minutes.
Um, I guess uh to take a straw poll, um,
I think about 27 of you managed to
complete this, which is great. Thank you
for your participation. Um, you know,
how many of you managed to fact check
all the facts?
So one of the questions yeah the fifth
one
the the long word expression completely
factually wrong right yes yes that's
right um so so how many of you managed
to fact check you know any or all of the
facts
you managed to fact check things just
one just one okay um how many of you
managed to check the math in the in the
five minutes okay so so there a couple
people okay good good excellent okay
that that makes me that makes me happy
um so I you know the The point of this
exercise partially, I mean, I think
maybe you could have guessed what was
going to happen here. Um, the shorter
ones, um, most of them are are
essentially taking the longer ones and
actually just removing, uh, the
hallucinations to the best of my
ability. And so, um, for the most part,
basically, for those of you that pick
the longer one, um, are sort of picking
the slightly longer but hallucinated
ones, like I don't quite remember which
of the paragames ones are hallucinated,
but but many of them, uh, are. Um and so
you know we see strong disagreement and
actually the longer one gets more votes
um despite having strong hallucinations.
This one I think both is correct. So um
B is probably the the better choice. Um
the two math ones um I think you can
also back out by the unnaturalness of
this construction. Um the the one that's
like sort of more conclusive actually is
is you know going to the wrong
conclusion. Um this is not
mathematically um fully correct here. Um
and so you know you probably should find
it difficult to try to do these
judgments this quickly. um there are
very very strong challenges in
collecting this kind of pair-wise
feedback um at very very large scales
just because even though you only have
to verify if I'm showing you a math
problem or I showing you you know
something like a very you know strong
factually laden you know uh text you
know you're going to have to basically
break this down into claims and check
each one to know whether one is you know
wrong and one is right um so this is
just like a very laborintensive and
difficult task And you know I gave you
five minutes because uh you know
essentially I think the the news story
that the Google bard article was
associated with was um basically that
you know the the annotators were given
one minute per example and you know
there was you know big complaints that
like this is not enough for us to judge
the safety and factual accuracy of the
model and you you hopefully you know
somewhat agree that it is a very
difficult task right. Um so okay um the
the lessons here um going back to the
you know the flow of the lecture right
it's very hard to get highquality
verifiable annotators like I think you
are in many ways like pretty high on the
bar of like people that are actually
motivated to do this because you're just
doing it because I asked you to not
because I'm paying you to or to to get
grades. Um it's very difficult to get
people to check correctness especially
under time constraints. Um, and the last
one, um, I don't know if if you know
those of you who are doing this, right,
but if you you put in an online survey
like this, you know, someone's just
going to like take the whole thing, dump
it into GPT4, and then just like kind of
copy the answer straight back onto your
pair wise responses. Um, you know, we
we've had several studies in the past
where an annotator had like 95 plus%
agreement with GPT4, and you kind of
have to wonder what's going on um there.
And so it's, you know, despite the fact
that pair wise feedback is easier to
collect than supervised uh imitation
data, um there are still significant
issues. Um and I'd be remiss to not
point out, you know, the the many things
that have been written about sort of the
the kinds of problems that this creates
if you try to outsource this to to third
countries. Um there's sort of pricing
concerns and sort of lots of ethical
issues that you all should be aware of.
you know, if you're sort of going to be
in the future, be a part of these kinds
of sort of data collection pipelines,
right? You want to make sure to get high
quality data and to make also make sure
that, you know, people are being paid
kind of living wage. Um the other thing
to be aware of you know this is in the
sort of bias and safety angle because
for alignment I think this is a really
important thing to to also touch on is
that you know in some sense RLHF and
alignment come at the end of the
pipeline and because they come at the
end of the pipeline they have very
strong influence on model behaviors. Um,
one of the papers that actually Percy
and my postoc Shivani um and and Essen
uh a postoc on mine worked on um was
this paper on trying to figure out like
how do subjective opinions of LMS align
with different you know groups of people
and one of the really interesting
patterns that we found was actually for
instruct GPT like these are old models
but you know the now still useful
models. um these models somehow became
more aligned with sort of Southeast
Asian religions than before. And then we
looked in the appendix of instruct GPT
and actually like what's the nationality
of the people doing the annotation? It's
it's Filipino and Bangladeshi and 17%
American. I was like oh it's kind of
surprising but it it does circumstantial
evidence lines up you know with this
kind of thing. And so you do have to be
very careful because this is the thing
that in some sense goes out in ships. Um
you know uh others have also noted that
you you know depending on the annotator
what they pay attention to is very
different. Um I really like this paper
from um Hosking Blunam and Barlo where
they basically study you know two
different kinds of annotators. One is
like the authors and they're like very
motivated to like you know judge things
correctly with quotes. And then crowd
workers and what they really find is you
know crowd workers don't pay much
attention to factuality. Um that that's
kind of this row here. um they pay more
attention to formatting, right? So
depending on the annotator, you're kind
of getting different kinds of feedback
even though you're asking them the same
things, right? Um and so kind of
increasingly um people have turned to as
with the instruction tuning phase um AI
feedback where LM generated uh feedback.
And so there's been uh many works um
including some of our own um that have
shown things like oh if you try to get
pair wise feedback from GPT4 it has very
strong agreement from like GPD4's you
know estimated win rates of models or or
responses and sort of the human
estimated ones on the y-axis. Same here.
um the agreement between human to human
which is the the blue box here is
roughly the same as the agreement
between GPD4 and human um and it but is
much cheaper right so so you know
there's lots of reasons I think why sort
of AI feedback has become popular
um and it has been used very extensively
in RHF so if you look at ultra feedback
which I think is one of the the very
popular open source data sets for sort
of off policy RLHF um you see this if uh
Zephier 7B I think was a hugging face
effort uh I want to say last year uh to
build a big strong open model and the
reason why I bring this up I think Zephr
is probably not the most well-known uh
model but one of the things I kind of
remember about sort of the the hugging
face um model process was you know
initially they were really interested in
human data collection like they were
convinced that like human crowdworker
like if you paid them enough and got the
right vendors you know would outperform
um sort of AI generated feedback um but
kind of late in the process they kind of
realized, you know, GPT4 generated
feedback for this kind of thing just
worked much better. Um, and so a more
modern example of this um is Tulu 3,
which is a um sort of post-training
paper/ project out of AI2. Um, and
they've done kind of roughly this like
they take different prompts. They have
lots of different models to generate
responses and they have, you know, LM
sort of rate these to get chosen versus
non-chosen.
Um and this really all just kind of goes
back to uh the classic paper would be um
the anthropic paper on constitutional AI
which I think sort of you know um really
uh planted a flag on the ground in terms
of um AI feedback being used for this
kind of alignment process.
Um finally the last thing I want to talk
about for data is length effects. Um I
think you know when we did the
annotation um the one of the things that
we saw was I think many of you saw the
longer response and you're like this is
more detailed. I like details. This is
good. Um it's not just you. Um models
and people all have this bias. Um and so
people have found that you know models
that people have thought were better
were in fact maybe only just also
longer. And then AI feedback seems to
make models just generally longer. Um
and so this is always a confounder that
you want to be careful of you know
length as a confounder uh for general
preference. Okay, there was a question
there. Could you expand on off policy
and on policy? Okay. Yeah, I'll talk
about off versus on policy later. Um you
know off policy I think I mentioned it
here um is going to refer to you collect
these like kind of pair-wise feedback
things um separately like they're not
collected from the outputs of your
model. uh maybe your model is involved
like for example in Tulu you know you
you've got all these kind of off policy
data on the left that's models that are
not your own but you also have on policy
data from yourself right so the off
policy data kind of tells you about the
landscape of places you're not at and
the on policy data tells you how to
refine yourself um yes so
the way the sort of human aspect is
we're
sampling prompts and then asking humans
to um grade them. Have people ever
instead of sampling
prompts that you don't have the answer
to and then asking for the screen you
have like existing in the world from any
number of places. There are existing
prompts that we know the answers to and
we have that data saved. We don't need
to do anything to receive that data.
Have people done sort of alignment
tuning using that style of data instead
of asking humans or LMS? Yes. Okay,
that's a good question. Um, and it's
like why why don't we do RHF on or like
can we do R LHF on domains where we know
the answer is like one way of putting
the question, right? Um, and part of the
answer is the next lecture on Thursday
is kind of that like where do we really
know the answer? Math. we know the
answer very well for math and we can do
exactly RL against math and it works
very well. Um people also do things like
you know here is a long form response
from an expert that has already been
written. Um now can you judge it given
this? Um that helps but one thing that I
think um is important to keep in mind is
there's for a lot of these open-ended
tasks there's many correct answers and
it's very difficult to judge which are
correct. Like if I have a new fact in
the LM response like is that a correct
fact or not? Doesn't really solve those
problems. Yes.
So like thinking like for instance the
anthropic paper you referenced there's
this like relatively specific and small
constitutional thing but we can even
like
sample values to make this work for
open-ended things like cuz we have any
number of sources of like
here's a problem here are values that we
as a society think are relevant whether
that's surveys or politics or you know
articles just any number of like sources
people do that I know that like
anthropic should like let people vote
but that seems small
yeah like I guess there's lots of
different things being mixed in on that
comment like you could do like
deliberative democracy style stuff the
line models that is certainly a thing
there's also I guess the the thing that
feels close to what you're talking about
is is almost giving the annotator
sources almost that are relevant um and
I'm sure those things help there have
been works on like showing people expert
written responses when they do the pair
wise judgment and so on. Um but I think
it's not a silver bullet like all of
this like kind of UI interventions
definitely help um but it's not
necessarily going to in one stroke solve
the problem. Okay. Yes. Um question is
there to like paper where you have like
um like you're using to annotate um like
your other responses there's like a bias
from like
yes there's a very strong or like very
detectable self preference for most
models for their own outputs and so when
you use this for evals which many people
um including I have done you have to be
very careful for that self bias.
Absolutely. Yes. Okay. Then there's lots
of hands, but yes, I think you were
first.
Balancing the amount of information you
get just from having model create its
own outputs and then like I guess model
to do like its own feedback, right? Is
there like a heristic for how many
iterations that does that change if you
use like
the model itself? Yeah, I guess the
question of like how much can you
extract out of models doing things to
themselves is an interesting question,
but I guess the kind of in some ways the
information theoretic bound so to speak
is very very high because technically
the model like ingests the entire
pre-training corpus and that could be
stored somewhere in the model and
depending on how you prompt it you might
get an amazing model out and so it's
possible that that based on how you're
using the model as part of your
self-refinement loop you can extract
more capabilities out of the model and
we don't know what the upper bound of
that is because you know basically the
inputs are just vast. Um but I do think
there's like practically lots of of
papers that have studied this question
of like how how much can
self-improvement help like what's the
scaling properties and so on and so
forth. I think ultimately it's a very
empirical question.
Okay. Yes.
I think uh the
uh as kind of like problem because
compared to SRT so basically SFT is the
best answer we have a label for that but
for assume that we don't have label but
we have like reward model to give it
like preference
has like ranking things. Yeah. So so
maybe I should just go through the next
slides um because I think that will
actually explain it. So not not only
does it help us get through the rest of
this hopefully quickly um but also I
think it'll explain your your uh
questions. So, okay. So, now let's talk
about methods. Um, our goal is to do
this thing, right? I want to find a
policy to maximize my rewards. So, I
need to tell you what the rewards are
and I need to tell you what the
maximization process is, right? So,
let's do that. Now, um, I think as you
can probably tell by the frequency with
which I'm referring to the instruct GPD
paper, the whole sub area of instruction
tuning and post-raining is very closely
tied to instruct GPD. So from the
instruct GBD paper you have equation 2
which is this uh you know objective that
describes what we're optimizing. So
we've got this r theta of x of y. This
is our reward and I'll define that in a
moment. And then we've got you know this
the second terms the log ratio of my RL
policy divided by my SFT output. So what
is this object? This is the KL
divergence between my RL policy and my
original SFT model. So it's saying when
I do RL don't move too far from where I
started. And then this this second line
this gamma term this is basically saying
keep doing pre-training while you do RL
so you don't catastrophically forget if
you you know keep doing this. Lots of
people don't do the second step but this
KL thing is a really you know it's a
standard thing. It it remains even
today. Okay. So now what is the reward?
The reward um is this thing kind of at
the very top. Um, and so maybe that's a
small equation. So I'll I'll talk
through what that is, right? So there is
a a sort of hypothesized model of the
world that exists. So what is the
hypothesized model of the world? Um,
it's that every single output in the
world, right? Like that that a language
model could output. Every single
sequence has a scalar value R associated
with it. And we don't observe what that
R is. And when a person rates it like
when when they do a pair-wise rating of
A versus B what they do is they compare
the two rewards of those two sequences
and based on the difference they'll take
a coin flip. Right? So this is a
logistic model of the difference of the
two rewards. So every sequence is a
reward. When I do pair wise comparisons
I take the difference and I flip a coin.
Right? Um this is the Bradley Terry
model of human preferences. Um and this
is what's happening. And so when we want
to optimize the reward, what we're
trying to do is we want to output sort
of the sequence that has the highest R.
And R is not something we observe. We
only observe noisy pair wise comparisons
uh through R theta, right? So that's
what we do. So that's the objective,
right? So that's what we're trying to
optimize. Um and so now let's talk about
the how. Um and to be clear, I'm only
going to talk about PO, which is kind of
the OG algorithm. This is what appears
in instruct GPT and a lot of the open AI
stuff. I'm going to talk about it only
very briefly and then I'll talk about it
in much more detail on Thursday because
it it more naturally belongs there.
We're going to do a lot more sort of
real RL on that lecture. So um at a
conceptual level remember what we want
to do is we want to optimize the reward
of some policy right that's the left
term here. And what's a good way of
optimizing something? Well let's take
some gradients right let's take gradient
descent. So that's the very top left
equation here. Now um you know we can
sort of do a little bit of math and if
we take the gradient of this object we
can write down that this is equivalent
to you know the expectation of the
reward multiplied by the gradient of P
theta. Um and so this is very natural
what you're doing is you take your
normal gradients that you normally take
in doing like pre-training or whatever.
This is saying P theta of Z I want to
maximize that probability and I maximize
or I multiply that with R. So if my
rewards are positive I want to upweight
those probabilities. If my rewards are
negative I want to downweight those
probabilities. Right? This is this is
the policy gradient theorem. This is
reinforced. You know if you've taken RL
class or something like it you've you've
definitely seen this before. Now what is
PO? PO I think is is uh normally a very
intuit uh sorry uh intimidating object
but I think it is actually quite simple.
So there's two steps that happen. First,
instead of taking a reward, we look at
what's called an advantage. An
advantage, um, you know, just to sort of
gloss over a lot of the details
involved, um, an advantage is it's
basically a variance reduced version of
the reward. You know, if if you, uh, go
through the math, you can notice that I
can subtract any constant or in fact, I
can subtract any sort of state dependent
variable from R and this gradient will
still be correct. That means that I can
rewrite this reward potentially as sort
of after subtracting any baseline values
that I want. And let's say we call that
the advantage. Now, not only that, maybe
I want to take multiple gradient steps
after sampling from P theta once. What's
called essentially um you know sampling
from one roll out and going almost off
policy. To enable that, I have to
essentially have importance waiting
corrections because the more steps I
take, sort of the more stale my original
samples become. And so this is what's
called PRPO. You basically make
corrections for all the gradient steps
you take and then you constrain yourself
to stay close. Now PO takes the final
step and says instead of explicitly
constraining uh myself to stay close to
my old policy using this KL constraint,
maybe what I can do is I can just clip
the um probability ratios and this will
naturally incentivize the model to stay
close to the original policy. So this is
kind of PO in one slide. Um I'm not
going to go into this with too much more
detail because actually this won't be
the primary algorithm that I want to
sort of just go through the rest of the
the lecture with. So at least in kind of
the open research space and the academic
space um a lot of the question that I
think people were concerned with was can
we get rid of PO? We will see this theme
on Thursday as well. Um PO is very
complicated. Um and we have debated but
decided against having you implement PO
because it will be suffering. Um and so
lots of people thought can we get rid of
PO and they tried other reasonable
things. Um and I will explain those
reasonable things like you know maybe we
can SFP on the pairs but for each of the
pairs we can prepend like a good token
for the chosen good outputs and bad
token to the chosen not uh the bad
outputs and then I can just condition on
good when I generate that does not work
very well. I can train the model only on
the preferred output that also does not
work super well. um I can use a reward
model, sample the best one out of those
um and then train on those. Works okay,
but but maybe not that great. Um and so
people tried all these variants, but
what really stuck um was basically DPO.
And I think the reason why it caught on
as much as it did, um was because it,
you know, removed a lot of the
complexity of PO and worked relatively
well. Um and so you get rid of the
reward model that exists in in PO. This
is used to calculate the advantage. Um,
we get rid of any of the on policy stuff
like the importance ratio thing that I
was talking about. You just get rid of
all of those. Instead, you know, we go
back to the basics. We take gradient
steps on the log loss of good things.
Um, and then we take negative gradient
steps on log losses of bad stuff, right?
We go back to very simple basic things.
Um, and the last part of what I want to
talk about today is just deriving the
DPO formula, right? So, what is our
goal? Our goal is to optimize this
quantity at the very top. This is just a
rewriting of that instruct GPT equation.
I have a reward at the very front and
then I have a KL divergence like this
keeps me this is pi theta close to my
reference. Right? So this is this is
very natural. So the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to assume that
my policy pi theta is not actually a
neural network. I'm going to assume it's
an arbitrary function of any kind. And
if I do that then I can sort of write
down um essentially what the optimal uh
policy looks like. It just look it has
this form. It's the exponential of the
reward and it it's multiplying um pyref
the reference distribution over here. We
can solve for the implied reward by
solving for rxy. And the clever part
about DPO is now to say okay it
basically means that every uh policy
instead of thinking about policies I can
think about rewards because the two are
one and the same under this
nonparametric um assumption um and so
what you do is remember I have these two
pieces the left side this is the Bradley
Terry equation from um the uh Steenomon
paper the the one before instruct GPT
and on the right side this is the uh DPO
sort of equivalence I wrote down and
then now um what I can do is I can plug
in these rewards R into this objective
and I can minimize this loss. I can say
what I want to do is now I want to find
a policy such that the implied reward
for that policy has the highest
probability of generating my pair wise
comparisons. Right? So now I've taken an
RL problem and I have turned it into a
maximum likelihood problem. A problem
that's very much uh similar conceptually
um to uh something like pre-training.
Right? All we're doing is maximizing the
probabilities except what we're doing
here is we're maximizing the
probabilities of the pair-wise
comparisons. Right? So those are the key
steps. Start by making the nonparametric
assumptions. Um parameterize the reward
via the policy and then optimize it um
using uh the supervised losses. Um I
think we're a few minutes over so we'll
stop here. I think this is a good place
because we got through the derivation of
um DPO um and we'll get through the rest
of RLHF um at the start of uh next
lecture. Um thanks everyone for asking
lots of good questions.