Um, as you may have noticed, I'm a
little bit less uh innovative in my
lecturing than Percy. So, you're going
to get um PowerPoint slides rather than
um executable Python ones, but you
should be able to find the PDFs um on
the website as well. So I I've titled
this lecture everything you didn't want
to know about LM architecture and
training because we're going to get into
some of the nitty-gritty details that I
think most other classes uh would spare
you the details of you know like what
should my hyperparameters be and those
kinds of questions um some minor
logistics um also if you're doing the
assignments we are updating assignments
as we find some uh mostly minor bugs
make sure you pull uh updates to the
assignments um as you go along
um Okay. So, what we're going to do,
we're going to start with a quick recap
of a transformer. Um, and I'll give you
two variants of a standard transformer.
One that's, you know, probably coming
from the the standard transformer, you
know, lectures that you might see in
224n. Um, and then I'll talk about what
you implement, um, and kind of the
modern consensus variant of a
transformer. And then we're going to
take a much more kind of datadriven
perspective to understanding transformer
architectures. So the question that
we're going to ask is people have
trained lots of LLMs at this point and
you can go and read you know all of
those papers and try to understand what
has changed what has been in common and
from that kind of almost an evolutionary
analysis you know try to understand what
are the things that are really important
to make transformers work right so
today's theme is the theme of the class
is the best way to learn is hands-on
experience but the theme of this lecture
because we can't train all these
transformers is to learn from the
experience of others
So the starting point is the original
transformer, right? So just as a review,
right? Hopefully you all remember this
from 224N or your other NLP classes. You
know, you've got some simple position
embeddings at the bottom. You've got
multi head attention, you've got uh
layer norms afterwards, you've got a
residual stream going upwards, you've
got a MLP, and then a softmax at the
very end. Um, and we're going to see
variance to all these different pieces
um until we get to basically the most
modern variants um of the transformer
and the and the latest one I'll talk
about will be just you know a few months
before. So what you implemented is not
you know the the vanilla transformer
variant um from the original paper. Um
we've modified a few things you know
we've put the layer norm in front of the
block. So you can see um on this slide
over here that you know there's the norm
is over here right before each of these
blocks in the residual stream. Um we've
asked you to implement rotary position
embeddings. Um the feed forward layers
use something called a swiggloo. Um and
then linear layers um you know now emit
these bias terms. Um and you might ask
why have you forced us to implement this
weird variant of a transformer instead
of the original transformer is all you
need transformer. Um, and so we're going
to go through some of those questions.
And then yesterday I was thinking, okay,
I should I should catch up on all the
developments that have happened in
architectures over the last year. Um,
and Percy warned me about this because
he said, you're going to have to redo
the lecture every year. And so I started
looking and I was like, all right, yeah,
there's a couple good good papers
recently. There's Command A, there's two
mode furious, there's, you know, small
LM and 54. And then you go looking and
you're like, wow, yeah, there's Gemma 3
and Quent 2.5 and intern LM and then
there's, you know, more. I can't even
sort of you know cover uh the screen
with these guys right there's there's a
lot of models there were about uh 19 new
dense model releases in the last year um
many of them with minor architecture
tweaks and on the one hand it's kind of
annoying to go through all these papers
and say like you know what is happening
in all of these um but also it's like a
actually wealth of information because
not all of them do the same thing and
you can kind of see you know not all of
you can especially in the back can see
the details of this slide um but I I put
together a little spreadsheet sheet of
you know what all these models are doing
and starting with you know all the way
from 2017 the original transformer all
the way to 2025 what the newest models
are doing and we'll talk about this as
we go but you kind of see sort of
certain kinds of architecture changes
sort of being explored like so here on
this column is position embeddings
people used to do all sorts of stuff
like absolute relative rope uh there was
a sort of um alibi phase for some people
but then now starting around 2023
everyone just does rope right so you can
kind of see this the convergent
evolution almost um of neural
architectures and we're going to talk
about um all of these different kinds of
things.
Right? So the the parts that I'll cover
so this is a preview of the three major
sections of this lecture and if I have
time I'm also going to talk about um
different attention variants at the end.
Um the first thing is going to be
architecture variations. Um that's what
I'm going to talk about. So activations,
feed forwards, attention variance,
position embeddings, all of those
things. Um and then having nailed down
the architecture, what do we have to do?
Well, we have to pick hyperparameters,
right? Like how big do we make the the
hidden dimension? How big do we make the
sort of inner projection layer inside of
MLP? Um, what do we do about the number
of dimensions? How many vocab elements?
Those are all sort of important things
that you have to choose when you're
actually training uh your language
model. Um, and you don't want to just
sort of pick these out of a hat, right?
You want to select them in some fairly
intelligent way. So, we're going to
start with um architecture variations.
Um and the the two things that I'll you
know mention right here and I'll you
know go back to them as I talk. The
first one is you know there's not that
much consensus in a lot of the choices.
Um there's been sort of convergent you
know evolution in the last few years. Um
what I'll call like llamaike
architectures at the very bottom here
but people do all sorts of things. They
swap between layer norm and RMS norm.
They do serial versus parallel layers.
There's one choice that basically
everyone does es since the first very
first GPT. Um, and I'll talk about that
in a bit. Um, but there's, you know,
lots of different variations that we can
learn from here. The big one I've
already talked about this guy in 224N.
So, if you remember that lecture, this
will be review for you, uh, rather than
being totally new. I think the one thing
basically everyone agrees on and agreed
on almost from the very start is the use
of pre-norm versus uh, postnorm. Um,
that terminology will get a little bit
more confusing. Um but the original
transformer paper did you know this
thing on the left over here where you
had your residual stream in the gray um
and you know in addition to the residual
stream you had these layer norms after
sort of every subcomponent. So you would
do your multi head attention you would
add back to the residual stream and then
you would layer norm that and then you
would do the same thing with your uh
fully connected layer and then you would
layerm it. Um and very very early on um
people realized that moving this layer
norm to the front of this sort of
non-residual part so this block on the
right um did much better in many
different ways and and basically almost
all modern LMS that I know of use this
kind of porm um there there have been
some sort of new innovations recently
that I'll touch on in two slides um but
lots of you know models have moved to
this the one exception um is opt 350M um
which I'm guessing, you know, they they
kind of messed that one up and and that
was sort of orphaned um when they were
training. Um that was a fun find in my
in my survey of architectures. Um so
this pre versus postnorm thing, if you
look into why it was originally
developed, um the arguments were that,
you know, if you wanted to use this
postnorm stuff, it was much less stable.
And so you would have to do some careful
learning rate warm-up style things to to
make it train in a stable way. Um and so
if you look at some of the earlier
papers you know arguing for this prenorm
approach um salar and yen and also this
xiang in 2020 paper you almost always
see sort of this comparison of hey if we
use p-orm and we do some other stability
inducing tricks then we can remove
warm-up and these systems work just as
well if not better um than sort of the
you know the postnorm layer norm with
careful warm-up type approaches and you
see this in in sort of a machine
translation setting here Um you see this
as well uh on the right um on you know
various other tasks especially using
BERT which was trained with um
postnorm. So um there were many
arguments about why this was helpful.
There were arguments about gradient
attenuation across layers like if you do
pre-orm then the gradient sizes would
remain constant whereas if you did
postnorm um you know without warm-up
then it would sort of blow up in this
orange way. It's a reasonable argument,
but I think a maybe more closer to
modern intuition would be this argument
that um porm is just a more stable
architecture to train. And so some of
the earlier work by Solazar and um
identified all these loss spikes um that
if you were training with prenorm kind
of in blue here um you would see a lot
more loss spikes and the training would
be kind of unstable um you know as you
were training. So the you see the the
gradient norm here you know is spiking
and generally higher than the one with
prenor. And so today um you see prenorm
and other layer norm tricks being used
essentially as as stability inducing um
stability inducing aids for using large
training large neural networks. Um and
so this brings us to one new fairly I
think recent innovation. I think this
didn't exist when I gave this lecture
last year. um which is this variant that
I don't think really has a has a great
name but I'm just going to call it the
double norm for the moment here. So this
is the original figure that I showed you
at the very beginning and we know that
putting layer norms in the residual
stream is bad. Um but actually someone
in 224n this year asked well but why do
you have to put the layer norm in the
front? Why can't you put it you know
after the feed forward network? And of
course you can and not only that um sort
of recent people have have gone around
and just just add the layer norm after
the you know the blocks as well. And so
Grock and GMA 2 both take this approach
of layer norms both in front and after.
Um 2 does only the the layer norm after
the feed forward um and the multi head
attention. And so this is actually kind
of an interesting change. Um porm has
just been kind of dominant and the only
thing for a while um but things have
been changed up a little bit. So now now
there's a a new variant and this is
actually you know there's been some some
evaluations of this kind of approach. Uh
people have argued it's a little bit
more stable and nicer to train on these
uh larger models. By the way feel free
to um stop me and ask me questions as
well. I have a tendency to to sort of
keep going if if no one stops me. So yes
uh why is layer in the residual bad? Why
is layer norm and the residual bad?
That's a that's a good question. Um I
don't think I can give you like a you
know this is the proof of why it's bad.
I think one, you know, intuitive
argument for why this might be bad is
that the residual gives you this
identity connection all the way from
almost the top of the network all the
way all the way to the bottom. And so if
you're trying to train really deep
networks, this makes gradient
propagation very easy, right? So there's
lots of arguments about how you know
LSTMs and these other kinds of you know
state space models have difficulty
propagating gradients backwards. An
identity connection does not have any
such problems. And so putting layer
norms in the middle, you know, might
mess with that kind of gradient sort of
behavior. And that you of course you see
uh back here right this is exactly the
kind of plot you expect to see if that's
happening. Okay cool.
Um the other thing that people now do um
is in the original transformer people
did you know layer norm u and so layer
norm is this uh equation over here. What
you do is you have you know the
activations x coming in you subtract the
empirical mean. So that's the average of
the x's up top and then you divide by
you know the standard de or the variance
plus a little fudge factor epsilon and
then you square root that so you can
roughly think of it as a standard
deviation right so that's going to you
know standardize your your activations x
you're going to scale it up by a gamma
that's a learnable parameter and then
shift it by a beta right so this makes
sense you you're going to normalize you
know your activations and then you're
going to shift them around to whatever
point you want and many models use this
layer norm thing and it worked quite
well um but many models have sort of now
moved on to RMS norm and this is one of
the consensus changes like basically all
the models have switched to using RMS
norm um and now what do you do you just
drop um the mean adjustment so you don't
subtract the mean you don't add a bias
term um and many notable models do this
the llama family palm chinchilla t5
they've all moved to to RMS norm um and
what's the reason for this um one reason
is that it doesn't really make a
difference turns out if you train models
with RMS norm does just as well as
training you know, layer norm. And so
there's a simplification argument. Um,
but really I think the argument that's
often given um in these papers and I
think it's good to appreciate kind of
the details of this argument is that uh
you going to RMS norm is, you know, it's
faster and just as good. So in what way
is it faster? Well, if I don't subtract
the mean, it's fewer operations. If I
don't have to add that bias term beta
back, it's fewer parameters that I have
to load from memory back into sort of my
compute units, right? So I don't have to
you know retrieve these this sort of
state. Um and some of you might be
thinking but wait you told me in 224n
that nothing but matrix multiplies
matter for the purpose of runtime right
and this is not a matrix multiply and so
I shouldn't care about you know any of
this and that's a reasonable perspective
to take if you think about you know the
number of the percentage of flops that
is taken up by different operations in a
transformer. um this table um there's a
nice uh paper by even all in 2023 um I
think the title is like memory movement
is all you need or something that does
profiling of all the different
components of a of a transformer and you
see that you know tensor contractions
which are like matrix multiplies that's
like 99.8% 8% of the flops um that
happen in a transformer. And so, you
know, saving 0.17% of your flops doesn't
seem like a like a huge win. Um but I
think one of the things that's important
for architecture design now is to not
just think about flops because you know
flops are important, but that's not the
only resource that you have to think
about. Um it's also that you have to
think carefully about you know memory
movement. Um and so even though you know
tensor contractions so this is things
like matrix multiplies that's like 99.8%
8% of the flops. You know, if you have
things like the softmax operation or
layer norms, all these like
normalization operations that happen um
in a transformer, they're 0.17% of the
flops, but actually they're 25% of the
runtime. And a big reason for that is
because you know these normalization
operations still incur a lot of memory
movement overhead, right? And so it does
actually matter to try to optimize some
of these like lower level things because
it's not just about flops. It's also
about memory movement. I'm going to
emphasize this quite a bit more as I get
into the systems lecture. Like when we
talk about GPU architectures, it's going
to become very very very important to
think about memory not just about flops.
And so this is one of the reasons um why
RMS norm has now become sort of um much
more popular. And so I I went back and
looked at some of the earlier uh RMS
norm papers. I think the the sad thing
is that there aren't quite as many
papers published by industry labs with
you know big nice ablations. And so many
of the ablations that I'll show you are
going to be from from a couple years
back. Um but Nang at all in 2020 had
this very nice ablation showing you know
here's the vanilla transformer here's
the RMS norm version and you kind of see
the exact thing I told you. you know the
the number of steps per second that you
can do in a vanilla transformer 3.5 per
second with RMS norm you get 3.68 68.
You know, not a huge gain, but that's in
some sense for free. And you get, you
know, a final loss that's uh lower than
the volul transformer. So that's great,
right? In some sense, we've gotten uh
runtime improvements and we've gotten uh
in fact, at least in this case, loss
improvements. And so that's a win-win um
for us.
The final thing that I'll say which is
very much in line with this RMSORM thing
in terms of theme is that most modern
transformers do not have bias terms. Um
so the original transformer if you look
at the the FFN um will look something
like this right you have your inputs X
you're going to do a linear layer with a
bias term and then you'll relue it and
then you'll have a second linear layer
wrapping around it. But um most
implementations uh if they're not gated
units, which I'll talk about in a
moment, uh look actually something like
this. They've just dropped the bias
terms. You can just make this argument
from basically the same kinds of
underlying principles. You know, they
perform just as well. Um matrix
multiplies are apparently um all that
you need to get these guys to work. Um
and the other thing which is maybe more
subtle is actually optimization
stability. Um I don't quite have the
deepest understanding of why the bias
terms are particularly bad for
stability. Um but there's been sort of
really clear empirical observations that
people have made that basically dropping
these bias terms often stabilizes uh the
training of these largest neural
networks. And so now a lot of the
implementations now emit bias terms
entirely um and train only on these like
pure matrix multiply um kind of
settings. So that's the that's the layer
norm bit. Um, and so there's kind of two
things that, you know, you should kind
of think of. This is nice because the
story is pretty clear. Everyone does
something and so you should just kind of
know this, right? Basically, everyone
does porm or at least they do the the
layer norms outside of the residual
stream. Like that's kind of the iron
rule, right? Um, you know, you get nicer
gradient propagation, you get much more
stable training. Um, it just doesn't
make sense to do it the other way. Um,
most people or most almost everybody uh
does RMS norm. um pra in practice it
works almost as well has fewer
parameters to move around and this idea
of dropping bias terms just broadly
applies a lot of these models just don't
have bias terms um in most places um I
think the one exception to this RMS norm
one as I was reading yesterday uh is I
think coher both command and R plus use
layer norm quite sure why okay any
questions on kind of the layer norm rs
MS norm and bias term stuff before I
move on yes questions
Do you think there are some long-term
lessons you can take away from these
details that are more future proof
potentially or do you think these are
Yeah. So the question was is there is
there something more future proof and I
think it's hard to have like the the
biggest picture in in many ways deep
learning has been very empirical and
like bottom up rather than top down. But
I do think there's some generalizable
lessons that you could sort of draw from
here. I think the lesson of you know
have very direct identity map residual
connections is sort of a story and a
lesson that has played out in many many
different kinds of architectures not
just you know in these kinds of
architectures. Um the effectiveness of
layerorm we'll see once again later on
in this lecture has been very effective
and so not letting your activations
drift in sort of scale is another thing
that I think generally has been very
effective for training stability. Um
those two seem like fairly generalizable
lessons. um we will also kind of see
sort of sort of the systems concerns
come into play again. So this is another
generalizable lesson of sort of thinking
really carefully about the impact of
your architecture on the systems
components of your of your uh
design. Okay. So now um there's this
other component which is the activations
um and there is a whole big zoo of
activations um relu swish lu glu and
then there's I mean these aren't
activations there are different kinds of
mlps uh galu regul swigloo and lilu um
and yeah I think this is exactly the
kind of thing that I didn't originally
want to learn when I got into doing deep
learning I was like I don't care about
activations it's going to train anyway
Okay. Um, but it really does matter
unfortunately um for both you and me
that swiggloo and other glu variants
just consistently work well. And so I
will explain those to you and you should
think about them carefully because they
do work um and internalize that, right?
Um so I think the relu and maybe the
galu you all should already know, right?
The relu you learn in like some of the
the most basic deep learning classes,
right? You just take the max of zero and
in the case of an MLP, right? You've got
your I've dropped the bias terms here.
You know, xw1 you take, you know, the
relu and then you do w2. Fairly easy,
right? Uh a gel is a gausian error
linear unit. Um this one multiplies um
the linear with a cdf of a gausian. Um
and so it's basically going to be like
the relu but with a little bit of a bump
here. Hopefully you can see that um over
here. This is not just flat at the very
bottom. Um this makes things a little
bit more differentiable which may or may
not help. Um and the GPT family of
models um 123 and GPDJ and so on uh all
use the GLU. Um and the original
transformer and some of the older models
used uh the relu and really almost all
the modern models have switched to uh
the gated linear units like swiggloo and
the geekaloo and and others, right? Um,
and really I think this is, you know,
the the Google folks really pushed for
this like Palm and P5 and others. Um,
but since it's sort of been tried and
true, basically almost all the models
post 2023 um, use a gated linear
unit. And so, you know, going back to
that earlier question of like what
generalizable architecture things can we
learn from this lecture, you know, there
are some things that have really
consistently been very useful. residual
connections, layer norms. Um, gating is
yet another one, right? And so this is
another place where gating just appears
and is a very good way of doing things.
So originally we this is our our fully
connected layer right here, right? This
is with a relu. Now instead of doing
just linear and a relu, what I'm going
to do is I'm going to gate you know the
output here with a entry-wise linear
term. So x.v V is going to give me a
vector and I'm going to multiply that
entry-wise with my original inside term
of the MLP and then I'm going to
multiply the whole thing with W2. Right?
So the way to think about this is I've
gated sort of the hidden part of the
MLP. Right? So I've got my original
activation that takes my inputs and puts
it into the sort of hidden space and
then I'm going to gate that with X.V.
And then, you know, I'm going to project
that back into sort of the the hidden
dimensionality using W2, right? So,
there's this gating operation that
happens entry-wise. And that's really,
you know, the the basic thing that's
happening here. And this is the the GLU
plus the
reloo. And then we have an extra
parameter that we've added here for the
gating. This is V. Um, and so when
someone says something like, oh, it's a
a giggloo uh fully, there's nothing to
laugh about that. there's the gigglu
fully connected layer. Um what I've got
here is you know I've got the the gel
sort of for the nonlinearity and I've
still got the exact same gating here of
x.v V right and this is the the
architecture that was used by many of
the um uh Google models like T5V1.1
um gamma 2 gamma 3 um and then uh
another variant there's a swigloo and
this has been very very popular uh swish
is x times the sigmoid and this is the
nonlinearity and you can kind of you
know a sigmoid is like this and x is
like this so it will look you know just
like the gausian error unit um and then
you know you do the same thing here you
have a gating over the switch and then
you get a fully connected layer here.
Yes, I have a question. Below a certain
negative value, the switch function and
also the also the the G function it's
not monotonically increasing. In fact,
it's decreasing, right? And a lot of the
argument about how gradient descent
works in like input machine learning is
that like okay, you want to do gradient
descent click but here it seems like it
would go in the opposite direction if
you use gh or or switch or their gated
versions. So yeah, so the question was,
you know, this isn't monotonically
decreasing. You know, there's a there's
a bit on the very left of this zero here
that's kind of flipping in the in the
derivative. Um, and isn't that going to
be a problem? Um, I think intuitively
you could you could have argued that
this would be a problem. You might trap
a bunch of activations at zeros. Um, I
think in practice, you know, if you look
at kind of like neural network
optimization dynamics, what's actually
happening is often you're throwing very
high learning rates with momentum into
the optimizer. And so you're not really
going to converge to this zero point,
right? Like these activations are going
to be all over the place. Um, and so in
practice, I don't think this this little
tiny negative piece is really an effect
that's going to be huge for the model,
if that makes sense.
Um, okay. And then going back to to
this, uh, the Swiggloo is is basically
most models today, like the llama
family, Palm, Elmo. Um, and I'll show
you the the big table later. Um, but
you'll see that the Swigloo is is very
very popular. And one thing to note, um,
I'll talk about this again in the
hyperparameters part is, you know, now
remember I've added this this V term,
this extra parameter, right? And so I
want to, you know, think about how to
size this extra parameter. And what
people do is gated models usually make
this like hidden size, you know, the
basically output dimensionality of W
slightly smaller by a factor of 2/3 um
in order to make sure that the total
number of parameters of this whole thing
remains the same as the non-gated
counterparts. And that's a convention
thing that most people do. Um if that
you don't quite understand what that is,
I'll go back over that again later. But
you can just kind of keep in mind that
basically for the gated linear units you
just make everything a little bit
smaller to make sure things are remain
parameter
matched. So oh yes question this may be
obvious in the past. Uh, one of the
benefits of relu is like it's very
easily differentiable by the input. But
if you know if you have the derivative
of the cdf of the gausian, you have like
a squared with x, does that not really
slow things down? That's a that's a very
good question. I'm not 100% sure what
the internal like CUDA implementation of
the swigloo or the the galu gloo is. I
think it's entirely possible that like
internally they might be implemented
with like lookup tables.
Go ahead. I mean what really matters is
the memory pressure here and like it
will be the exact same because you're
reading the same amount of elements
performance. So the the extra comput is
negligible on that's actually a yeah
that's probably a better uh argument
that like basically flops wise this is
negligible anyway and that actually the
memory calculus is the same.
So okay
cool. All right so uh do gated linear
units work? Uh I will have more modern
evidence for this as well but I thought
you know I should take you straight to
the the horse's mouth uh Nom Shazir's
original paper um where he you know
evaluates all these GLU variants um and
you know this is this is somewhat older
stuff. So you're seeing cola and SST2
performance um but you do see basically
that the GLU variants consistently
perform better right glu is 84.2 84.12
84.36 84.67 67. Um, and you know, wow,
it's 2020s. They they even give you the
standard deviations so you can sort of
figure out how significant um those
results are. And they they in fact um
are significant, right? Um and so this
is some nice evidence to to see here. Um
there was also you know the Nang at all
in 2020 paper which is a very nice paper
studying all sorts of architecture
variance um I think in the context of T5
style models. Um and once again you see
that the the gated linear unit variants
um consistently achieve kind of lower
losses um than their counterparts,
right? Like you see that the bolded
lines are exactly at the GLU variance.
Um and this uh pattern has basically
held up. Um so for gating and
activations, you know, there are lots of
lots of variance um across different
models. Um but the gated linear unit has
become basically widespread and dominant
and I think for good reason. Um, of
course, um, the GLU isn't necessary for
a good model. Like, it's important to
separate the two, right? Just because
it's probably the slightly better and
everyone does it doesn't mean it's
necessary. Um, and you do see examples
of very high performance models not
using a GLU. Like GPT3 uh is one
example. Uh, more recent one, um,
Neotron 340B uses a squared relu, which
I had not seen before, and Falcon 211B
uses a RELU. uh both of those are
relatively high performance models. So
you can kind of see that it's not really
necessary and so you know evidence does
point towards consistent gains from uh
swiggloo and gaggloo and that's why we
ask you to implement exactly uh that
variant.
Cool. Okay. Um the final thing that I
want to talk about for architectures and
this is one kind of final major I want
to say variation that we've seen. Um
normally uh the transformer block is
serial right in the sense that you know
uh your your for each block the uh
outputs come in from the bottom and then
you do your attention and then you pass
the result of that computation forward
and then you do your MLP and then you
pass that computation forward, right? Um
and so this is inherently serial. You do
attention and then MLP. But of course
this might have certain like parallelism
constraints. So if you want to paralyze
this over gigantic you know sets of GPUs
it might be harder to do so um if you
have this serial connection you know the
systems concerns might also be more
difficult right you might get lower
utilization from your GPUs and so a few
models have done this thing uh that I'll
call parallel layers um where basically
instead of having serial computation of
attention and then MLP they will do them
both at the same time right so you will
get your X you know from your previous
layer you will comput both the MLP and
the attention side by side and then you
will add them together into the residual
stream and then that will be your output
right um and this was pioneered uh by
GPTJ which is kind of this open source
replication effort and uh the folks uh
at Google doing palm were kind of bold
enough to do this at at the really big
scale um and many others have kind of
followed since um so if you're
implementing this right you can share a
lot of stuff like the layer norms and
the matrix multiplies can get fused
together and you can get some systems
efficiency
um out of that it hasn't been quite as
popular since then at least in the last
year. I think most of the models that
we've seen have been serial layers
rather than parallel ones. Um I think
the only exceptions to this are like
coher command A, command R plus um and
Falcon Q
11B. So now I think we have the ability
to kind of go back to you know this big,
you know, hard to see chart and then see
what what I was sort of pointing at at
the very beginning. So this column here,
you know, you don't really need to be
able to read any of the text because
think the colors will tell you
everything you need to see. This check
mark here, this is basically pre versus
postnorm. The only two models I I really
know of in the the early days uh that
did um postnorm, this is the original
transformer and GPT and BERT if you want
to include that into this table. Um and
then almost everybody else, I think
basically everyone else um has done uh
porm. The only other non-checked boxes
here are models that are proprietary and
I don't have details for. Um, this
column here on the on the leftmost
thing, this is RMS norm versus layer
norm. The gray boxes are the layer norm.
The blue ones are RMS norm. Basically,
most people have converted to RMS norm.
As I said, um, this column next to it is
serial and parallel layers. Once again,
most people do serial, but you see other
variants. Um, what I'm going to talk
about next is going to be position
embeddings, and that'll be kind of more
interesting in a moment here. Um any
questions about any of this architecture
stuff before I uh move on? Hopefully
that gives you a bit of an overview of
at least the major variations in
architectures that that we see.
Yes. Serial layer or computation more
efficient than parallel. So uh the
question was whether serial is more
efficient than parallel. Um it's it
should be the actually the reverse that
parallel is more efficient than serial
and that's why you're kind of willing to
do this. So in some sense you might
expect serial to be more expressive
because you're composing two
computations rather than just adding
them together. Um but the benefit of
parallel in theory is that if you write
kind of the right kinds of fused
kernels, a lot of these operations can
be done in parallel or the computation
is shared across the different um
parallel
parts. Okay. So cool. Um, so the last
thing uh I want to talk about in
architecture land, I think this is the
last thing is uh variations in position
embeddings. Um, and I think this one's
interesting because in the first few
years of of sort of LM land, there were
a lot of different things that people
were trying. Um, sign embeddings were
from the original transformer. You know,
you should have learned this in 224n.
There's sign and cosine positions. Um
many others did absolute embeddings like
the GPTs and OPT all basically just
added a position learned position vector
to the embedding. Um some others like T5
um and Gopher did uh various kinds of
relative embeddings that add vectors to
the attention computation and then I
think most models have converged to rope
um which is you know relative position
embeddings um and this I think actually
started in GPTJ once again another open-
source contribution um and has really
rapidly been picked up by most of the
models um and so the highle thought
process behind rope is that the thing
that matters is relative positions uh of
these vectors right and so um if I have
an embedding f of x of i where x is you
know the word I'm trying to embed and i
is my position then I should be able to
write things down in this way right so
there should exist a f such that f of x
i and f of yj if I take the inner
product of these embeddings then I can
write this down as some different
function g which is a function of the
two words and the difference in their
positions Right? So this is a a
definition that enforces um basically uh
position invariance or absolute position
invariance. So you only pay attention to
the how far apart these two words are.
Um and so you can you know do a brief
check and see okay what happens with
signs? Well you get these cross terms
that that are not relative. So you do
still leak absolute position
information. Um absolute positions like
it's in the name you know it's not a
relative uh position embedding. And um
relative embeddings um well it is
relative but it's not an inner product.
So it sort of violates this constraint.
Um and so rope is this kind of clever
observation that we do know one thing
that is you know invariant to um sort of
absolute things which is rotations. And
so we're going to exploit that structure
to come up with our position embeddings.
Um right we know that inner products are
invariant to arbitrary rotation. So
we're going to leverage that. So on the
left, this is the starting point. Let's
say my my embedding for the word we is
this arrow over here. And my embedding
for the word no is this other arrow over
here. Now I want to embed uh this
sequence. We know that. And I only, you
know, I look at the word we and no. So
how do I do that? Well, we is in
position zero. So I'm not going to
rotate that guy at all. Um no is in
position one. So I'm going to rotate him
uh by, you know, one, you know, unit of
rotation. And so now I have this
embedding for we know. And now let's say
I want to embed this sequence. Of course
we know. Now we and no are have the same
relative positioning to each other. And
so let's look at what happens. Wei gets
shifted by two positions. I rotate we by
you know I start you know in this
vertical position and I rotate them
twice. One and two. And then I rotate no
by three positions because it's 1 2 3 uh
sorry 0 1 2 3 position. Right? And so
now if you look at these two arrows,
they have the same relative angle,
right? So their inner products are
preserved. And so this is kind of the
the nice fun idea about rope. You just
rotate the vectors and the rotation
angle is determined by the position of
each word. And rotations, you know, the
inner products don't care about relative
rotations. And so these inner products
are only going to look at sort of the
the difference in
distance. Now it's easy to think about
in 2D because rotations are kind of
obvious in 2D. There's only one way to
rotate a vector. Um but in
highdimensional spaces where we operate,
it's not obvious at all how we are going
to do this rotation. So the rope folks
came up with you know in some ways the
simplest but also effective way of doing
this. And the way to do it is you take
your highdimensional vector in this case
D and I'm just going to cut it up into
blocks of two dimensions. And every two
dimension is going to be rotated by some
theta. So there's going to be a rotation
speed. Um and I'm going to rotate the
pairs of dimensions. Um and so now every
pair of dimensions is encoding, you
know, all these relative positions. And
much like in s and cosine embeddings,
I'm going to pick some set of thetas
such that some embeddings are rotated
quickly and others are rotated much more
slowly. So they can capture both high
frequency information or like close by
information and very far away uh sort of
lower frequency positioning information,
right? Um and the actual rope math here
is, you know, if you're going to think
about rotations, it's just going to be
multiplying with various sign and cosine
rotation matrices. Hopefully you
remember this kind of from linear
algebra and trig. Um and so you can
think about this as an operation where
you multiply you know your embedding
vectors with these you know block 2x two
block matrices. Um and there's no sort
of additive or cross terms that sort of
appear here. This is all purely uh
relative. Um one thing that is different
um if you're used to sort of absolute
position embeddings or sign and cosine
embeddings here is that um the rope is
going to operate at the actual attention
layer. Right? you're not going to add
position embeddings at the bottom.
Whenever these attention computations
are going to be done, you're going to
intervene on that layer and then that's
going to give you your position uh
information. And so, you know, I pulled
this from, I think, the llama
implementation of rope. You know, you've
got the initial normal attention stuff
at the very top like query keys and
values. These are, you know, your normal
linear projections. Um, and then, you
know, you're going to come up with
cosine and s angles. These are rotation
angles telling you how much to rotate
different blocks of um the uh query and
key. And then so you take your query and
your key and you're going to rotate them
by the cosiness and signs. And now
you've gotten rotated query and rotated
key. And that's going to be what's going
to go into the rest of your attention
computation. Right? So you don't do this
at the bottom, you do it whenever you
generate your queries and keys.
Hopefully that's that's clear. um that's
really critical to enforcing um kind of
this uh relative positioning only um
information. Okay,
good. So um one of the things I want to
highlight is that rope is actually one
of the things that it seems like
everyone has converged on. I I you know
went through all 19 of those papers um
over the weekend and basically all of
them now use rope um for various
different reasons. there's you know the
reason that rope has now many different
algorithms for extrapolating context
length and that's an important part of
sort of the modern productionized
language model um but also it seems to
be empirically quite effective even at
fairly small scales in small context
length so it's kind of won out on this
um uh what's it called position
embedding battle okay um any questions
before I move on to to some of the
hyperparameter stuff yes is the rate of
rotation consistent across all these
models um I don't think they're all the
same there's some variation in the
thetas.
Oh yes. Are the the thetas like for each
pair um are those hyperparameters or are
they trained? They're not. It's the
thetas that determine the rotation
angles. They're not hyperparameters.
Much like in the in the signs and
cosiness here there's kind of a schedule
to the rotation angles that are
determined and it's in the same
intuition in the signs and cosiness. You
want to cover different frequency ranges
um in order to get higher or lower uh
frequency um information.
Yes. Oh, the rotations create any
difficulty with like training. I wonder
like this like angular rotations. Um the
rotations themselves don't really create
any issues because one way of thinking
about a rotation is that it's just a
matrix multiply, right? Since thetas are
fixed, right, and the M's here are
fixed, this is really just a fixed
matrix that multiplies your vector. And
so in that sense it's not really an
issue. If you were learning the thetas
then maybe you have issues because
you're you know maybe differentiating
through trig functions but you're not
doing that here.
So okay
cool. So now I think we go even one more
level uh into the details here. Uh and
we're going to talk about
hyperparameters. Um I feel like when you
have to you know you're dropped in and
you're asked to train you know a new
language model there's a lot of
questions you have about hyperparameters
because there's quite a few of them. And
one of the things that I've realized is
that actually only a few of these really
get changed um across different
successful models. There's actually like
fairly clear rules of thumb and fairly
clear guidelines that people seem to be
following. Um so you know there are some
things like how much bigger should the
feed forward size be or how many heads
should I have or what should my vocab
size be? Um and so we'll talk about each
of those things and we'll try to
constrain the space of hyperparameters
that people um have. So you know the
starting point we're going to look at a
simple feed forward layer you know just
the you know with the bias let's say um
this is a relu version of it and so
there's two hyperparameters here there's
d model which is the dimensionality of x
right that's the input coming into your
your MLP um and then you've got dfff so
this is the feed forward dimension this
is kind of the the output hidden
dimension of your MLP and from there
you're going to project back onto D
model right so what should um DFF be um
in general eneral um you know these
these things are going to be up
projections right you're going to have
more hidden units than there were inputs
um but how much bigger well there is
actually just like a consensus um almost
everybody that uses you know relu style
uh MLPS are going to pick DFF is equal
to four times um D model um this is I
will show you some empirical evidence
for why this is a sane number later um
but as far as I can tell there's no like
you know law of nature that says you
have to pick four. This is a convention
that has really held up. Now there are a
few exceptions to this rule. Um remember
that the GLU variants are going to scale
this down by a factor of 2/3, right? And
if you scale it down by a factor of 2/3
um you're going to have uh roughly the
same number of parameters. Um, you can
do a little bit of math and if you scale
the GLU variance down by a factor of
2/3, you'll come to the conclusion that
the way to do that is to set DFF equal
to 8 over3d model, right? That's going
to be the number that you end up at. And
you can sort of convince yourself that
that will give you the same number of
parameters and that's the ratio that you
would get if you started with a ratio of
four. So if you look at many of the
models, they actually do follow this
rule of thumb. um palm for example uh
you know are palm mistro and llama are
slightly larger these are glu models but
they don't follow this 2.6 rule but if
you look at for example llama you know
one quen deepseek e and t5 they all
roughly follow um this like kind of
2.6ish rule um and I can sort of put up
the uh the big table of lms that I made
later with hyperparameters many many
many of them fall into this roughly 2.6
six range and that's the standard
parameterization of a GLU uh
unit. Um I'll go through one other
exception. I really like this exception
because I think in many ways, you know,
uh big large language model training is
a game of copying hyperparameters from
other people and so we don't learn very
much, right? Like it's very
conservative. Um but T5 I really like
because in some sense it's really bold.
Um and I think Google people actually do
some pretty bold stuff. Um, and so if
you look at the 11 billion parameter T5
model, they have a pretty pretty
incredible setting. Their hidden dim is
1024, but their DFF, you know, their up
projected dimension is 65,000, right?
Um, and so that's going to give you a 64
times multiplier um on the ratio of DFF
to to uh D model. And of course, you
know, you compare to this where Palm is
like a factor four and everyone else is,
you know, much smaller. This is this is
a very large difference. Um and there's
some other recent examples of of using
much bigger um you know multipliers like
gamma 2 kind of follows in these
footsteps um and does a factor of eight.
And I'll talk a little bit about this
exception um later. Of course T5 was a
totally fine model. So this should tell
you it is possible to train a model with
you know such a uh much larger ratio.
So one of the things that I think is you
know quantitative evidence you know I
saw that 4x multiplier and I thought is
that really the right thing to do or is
there some more quantitative experiment
someone's done to convince me that that
is a good idea. Um so one of the figures
from Jared Kaplan's sort of scaling law
paper and most people know this paper
for for the scaling law component but
actually there's also some really useful
hyperparameter components to this paper.
um you'll actually see that they do
exactly this thing that I'm talking
about the DFF to D model ratio. Um and
they plot essentially how much the loss
increases as you vary this and um you
kind of see that there's kind of a sweet
spot. This is, you know, a ratio of 1 2
3 4 and then up to like 10 or so here,
right? And so there's a pretty wide
basin here anywhere between 1 to maybe
up to 10 where you know you can pick
whatever feed forward ratio you want and
it'll be roughly optimal. Um, and four
is not too far off from your your
optimal choices over here. It's like
one, two, three, four. It's like right
here or maybe right here, right? So
that's that's a pretty reasonable
choice.
Um, so what can we learn from all this
hyperparameter stuff? I think a lot of
the evidence points towards, you know,
you can pick the same defaults of, you
know, if you're not using a GLU, you can
multiply by four. If you're using a GLU,
you can use roughly 2.66. Um, and they
can work pretty well for mostly all the
modern LMS. Um, T5 once again does show
that you don't have to follow these
rules, right? You can be a rule breaker
and do whatever you'd like. um there's
no hyperparameter choice written in
stone. You can get reasonable LMS at
many other hyperparameters. Um that
said, I think the the really funny
epilogue to this story, right, is that
P5 has a follow-up model called P5V1.1
um that's improved and it uses a much
more standard 2.5 multiplier on gaggloo,
right? So, you know, you can read
between the lines and say like maybe
they looked at, you know, the original
T5 and said actually maybe we want to
walk back that 64 times multiplier and
pick a more standard one. and they did
end up with a better model. So cool.
Yeah. Okay. So So I think that's a
that's a good question. So the the
question was what's the ratio or sorry
what's the relationship between you know
this ratio that I'm talking about here
and generally the impact on the model
right? Um and so if we go all the way
back here
uh here, you know, the ratio is
controlling essentially how wide, you
know, the the hidden part of this this
MLP is. And so the original
justification in the T5 paper for for
picking 64 was to say actually we can
get bigger and fatter matrix multiplies
if we make that dimension really really
large. And while that is a kind of a
true statement, you know, the wider it
is, you know, you're getting more
parallel computation, so to speak,
rather than serial computation. So
you're spending your flops and your
parameters in a slightly different way
than if you made your hidden units
bigger, which would let you pass more
information or using more units, which
would let give you sort of more serial
computation, right? So you're spending
your parameters and your flops in a in a
slightly sub-optimal way from expressive
power, but you might get it um get
systems gains if sort of your your
matrices are wide
enough.
Okay.
Excellent. So another thing that is a is
a surprising or maybe not surprising um
consensus hyperparameter is the um ratio
between the model dimension um and the
head dimension times the number of
heads. Um, so I I clipped this from
224N, right? But really, um, the
basically canonical choice is to pick
things so that the dimension D, that's a
hidden dimension. And if you have
multiple heads, you're just going to
split up the number of dimensions each
head gets, right? So you're going to
keep the dimensions fixed um, as you add
more heads. And you don't have to do
that, right? As you add more heads, you
could just keep the same number of
dimensions per head, and you could just
let the attention part take more and
more parameters, right? you could do
that. That's an option that you have. Um
but most models once again do follow
this guideline. Um we see GPT3, T5,
Lambda, POM, and llama 2. They all have
a ratio of one or almost exactly one. Um
T5 is the one exception uh that breaks
this rule. They tried the the big ratio
of 16. Um but otherwise it is all, you
know, fairly following this consensus.
There's been a couple papers that have
argued against this 1:1 ratio. Um, you
know, there's a a notable one by um I
don't know how to pronounce this, Boja
Panelli at all 2020 um who have argued
that, you know, if you have um more and
more heads, they're going to have lower
and lower rank. Um, and if you have very
few dimensions per head, that's going to
start affecting the expressiveness of
the attention operation. Um, but in
practice, it doesn't really seem like we
see too many significant low rank
bottlenecks in practice. Um, and most of
the models with this this ratio of one
seem to do just fine, right? This is
really a parameter that's generally been
held constant by most of the models um
that we've seen. If I have time, I'll
talk a little bit about different
optimizations that people have made on
this like multi head component. Um but
hyperparameter rise things have have
stayed fairly um
similar. I think one of the the big ones
in terms of hyperparameters is the the
aspect ratio. Um so you know we can
think about deep networks, right? We can
have more and more layers or we can have
wide networks. And generally if you want
one knob to control the width that would
be uh sort of the the hidden dimension
of the residual street, right? That
would control essentially the width of
almost all the operations um at once.
And so this seems like a pretty critical
thing to tune. You might think that
deeper networks are smarter and more
expressive or wider networks are more
efficient. Um there is generally a sweet
spot um of ratios that people have
picked. Um there have been sort of
outliers. Some of the early models used
much smaller ratios here. So what that
means is that um they were much uh much
wider than they were deep. And then some
models have gone really deep um where
they had way more sort of D sorry the
other way around really wide where they
had way more D model than N layer. Um
and there's been generally a sweet spot
of saying we want about 128 sort of
hidden dimensions per layer. Um, and
that has been generally stuck to by a
lot of the GPT3 and llama variant
models. Um, and I'll talk a little bit
about evidence for that in a second. Um,
there's considerations about aspect
ratio that are quite important. Um, they
will control the amount of sort of
parallelism um that we can do. So, if
you're doing um something called uh
pipeline parallel, what you're often
going to do is you're going to take your
different layers and you're going to cut
them up and you're going to put them on
different devices or different blocks of
devices because you'll parallelize, you
know, within each layer as well. Um and
so there's going to be certain kinds of
um constraints that you're going to put
on your model. And also, you know, if
you have really wide models, then you
can do something called tensor parallel
where you slice up the matrices and then
you distribute those on GPUs. And one
thing that we'll learn in in I think uh
1 2 3 four or five lectures is that
these different parallelism paradigms
are going to have different constraints
right you need really fast networking uh
for tensor parallel and you can sort of
maybe get away with slower networking or
higher latency networking for pipeline
parallel and so your networking
constraints might in turn drive some of
these like width depth considerations.
But setting that aside, you might
abstractly ask, you know, what is the
impact of aspect ratio model
performance? And once again, uh, Kaplan,
uh, at all have a really nice visual
sort of aid showing how aspect ratio
impacts performance. And so this is
three different scales, 50 million, uh,
274 million and 1.5 billion parameters.
And the x-axis is axis effect ratio,
y-axis is sort of loss difference, um,
in percentage change. And you see that
you know around 100 right which is once
again I told you was the around the
consensus choice of hyperparameters is
the minimum across different scales
right so this is kind of backed by some
of this like uh large scale uh
hyperparameter data that's been
published by Kaplan at all and it
roughly matches that intuition and a
really nice thing here is it seems to be
the case that aspect ratio optima does
not shift too much uh across uh several
orders of magnitude here so if this
holds up even more that's that's very
good news you can keep training um on uh
one fixed aspect ratio. Um one thing I
will note um that is quite an
interesting result is um EK um and
others at Google had this very
interesting paper sort of studying
impact of depth versus width um both
upstream and downstream. And one of the
things that they found was that if
you're looking at um losses then it
doesn't really matter. Parameter is the
only thing that matters. Deeper models
don't help you. Um, but the story is
less clear if you're looking at
downstream accuracy. At the time, they
were looking at sort of fine-tuned
superlue accuracy. They were arguing
that for the same amount of flops,
deeper models might be better. So, I'll
sort of just leave it at that. There's
not quite as much follow-up um to this
work, at least in the open, that I've
seen, but downstream performance may
actually be slightly different in terms
of the the aspect ratio considerations
here.
Okay, cool. Um the final thing um that I
want to talk about in this sort of very
low-level hyperparameter world is what
are kind of the vocabulary sizes that
you might want to pick. Um and in
general vocabulary sizes have been
trending upwards. Um and I think a big
part of why is because you know LLMs are
being deployed out in the wild. They're
becoming more useful services. And when
that happens, you're going to interact
with people speaking different
languages, um people using emojis, all
sorts of other kinds of, you know,
almost modalities or languages um than
what you might expect. And so I think
some of the earlier models and
especially monolingual models um ranged
around in the 30 to 50,000 uh token
vocabulary range. Um you can kind of see
this in like GPTs, the early llamas. Um,
but if you look at uh the multilingual
or I would call like production systems
um that have come out, they've all sort
of been shifting towards the 100 to
250,000
uh range for their vocabulary sizes. Um,
and you know, I I looked at Command A,
which is one of Coher's models. They're
a company that emphasizes a lot of
multilingual stuff. You know, you see
very large uh vocab sizes from them. um
even with GPT4 and and many others that
have copied the GPD4 tokenizer are going
to be around the 100k tokens, right? And
so that's kind of the the the standard
that a lot of people are operating at
roughly at 100k to to 200k uh token
size. And I think there's been work
showing that as models get bigger um
these models can in some sense handle
more and more or make good use of more
and more um uh vocab elements. And so
you might see, you know, increasing
trends uh to token counts as models get
scaled up or more more data is used to
train
them. Cool. Okay. So the last thing um
this is no longer sort of specific
hyperparameters but sort of two other
things that you might need to do before
you sort of set your model to run. Um
which is dropout and other kinds of
regularization, right? And I think this
one was really interesting to me when I
was originally doing kind of the
research for putting this lecture
together. And if you sort of think about
pre-training, pre-training is about the
furthest place that you might think of
from regularization, right? Because
pre-training you do usually like one
epoch, right? You you can't even go
through all of your data because you
have too much of it. So you're going to
do one epoch training um and you're
almost certainly not overfitting the
data in that one pass that you're doing,
right? And so you might think, all
right, we don't need regularization for
pre-training, right? Let's just set your
your optimizer loose. It's all about
minimizing loss. Um, and this is this is
really good arguments for for why you
shouldn't need to to regularize. But
then if you look at what people do, um,
the the story is actually kind of mixed.
Um, and this story actually is is maybe
even more mixed than than what has uh
turned out to be, but you know, early
days people did a lot of dropout. Um and
then you know there's a lot of weight
decay that also seems to be happening.
Um and these days I think a lot of the
the people have stopped publishing
details on precisely their training
hyperparameters but dropout has sort of
gone out of fashion but weight decay has
really been something that a lot of
people continue to do. Um and why is
that? That's like a a really odd thing
to be doing. Right? So I'll give you a
moment to just kind of think about this
state of affairs. Right? If you're
doing, you know, training a really large
neural network for one pass on SGD on
vast amounts of data, why would you use
weight decay when you're doing that,
right? So maybe some of you know the
answer, but I think that's a kind of
interesting thing to think about. It's
very intuition sort of violating uh at
least uh for me.
So okay so the reason is because um you
know it's not to control overfitting in
the sense that if you look at weight
decay different amounts of weight decay
don't really seem to change the ratio of
of training loss to to validation loss
right so you can train with different
amounts of weight decay if you train for
long enough where you know you control
your hyperparameters appropriately
you'll end up with the same train to val
loss gap so overfitting nothing's
happening here even with zero weight
decay but what is interesting is that
the weight decay seems to be interacting
you know somewhat in a strange way with
the learning rate schedules of the
optimizers. Um and so what's happening
is that if you look at um sort of a a
constant uh learning rate so this is a a
model trained on constant learning rate
and then you know you suddenly decrease
the learning rate in 10 year zero. So
you see this drop off as you you know
decrease the learning rate. Um and then
let's look at um different kinds of
weight decay that you could do. And what
happens is, you know, with weight decay,
the model's not training very well at
this high learning rate. And then when
you decrease the learning rate, it'll
very rapidly drop off. And when you look
at sort of cosine learning rate decay,
what happens is that you know the models
with high weight decay start out very
slow, but then as they cool down, that
is their their learning rate decreases,
they very rapidly optimize. And so
there's some very complex sort of
interaction happening here between the
optimizer and the weight decay and some
sort of implicit sort of acceleration
that happens near the tail end of
training that ends up giving you better
models. And so the answer to the
question I posed you is, you know, you
don't weight decay because you want to
regularize the model, which is kind of
what it was designed for. You're weight
decaying in order to get actually better
training losses. And you end up doing
that because of the various learning
dynamics at the tail end of training as
you decrease your learning rates to
zero. It's a very sort of very
interesting and complex and in some ways
you know uh troubling you know thing to
be doing uh with language models. But
now you sort of see why you know if you
look at the a lot of the reports you'll
see we use weight decay. This is kind of
why that ends up
happening.
Cool. Okay. So, um, putting all that
together, so there are certain things
that I think are just kind of
no-brainers. So, if you're picking
various hyperparameters for your model,
you don't really need to think too
deeply about them, um, in the sense that
they've been validated and basically
everyone else does them. So, this is
things like, you know, the hidden size
of a of a MLP, the head dimensions of
your your multi head attention, um, your
aspect ratio, um, and your choice of
regularization through weight decay.
like all of those there's fairly good I
think uh consensus evidence of how to
pick most of these hyperparameters and
those defaults roughly give you the
kinds of um things that we suggest in
the assignment so you can kind of follow
along and they'll roughly give you
something similar um to this. So okay
any questions about uh the
hyperparameter uh piece?
Yes. Yeah. Is there a reason why
dropouts like gone out of pattern?
That's a good question. Um I don't think
I've seen uh the question was why did
dropout go out of fashion? Um I haven't
quite seen a deep analysis of of why
dropout is or isn't helpful. Like I
haven't seen any uh result that for
example shows that it helps for training
loss. And as sort of this you know what
this paper argues and logic would
dictate there's not really a training
overfitting issue with these models that
can't even do one epoch over their
training data.
Yes.
Um, do multilingual vocabularies
actually contribute to improved
performance in one language? So, I get
Yeah. So, the question was, do
multilingual vocabularies contribute to
improving uh performance in one
language? When you say one language, do
you mean do mon multilingual or like you
know larger vocabularies help
performance in English? Is that the
right question? Yeah. So, I think in
your high resource language, the impact
is less, right? So, you know, if you're
only thinking about, you know, English
language language modeling, you can get
away with smaller vocabularies. This
much is kind of, you know, true. Um, but
the place where larger vocabularies is
really helpful is when you're starting
to get at, I wouldn't say the tail of
your distribution, but when you get to
languages that are sort of more
minority. And one great example of this,
um, if you look at any of the coher, uh,
announcements about their models or
their tokenizers, um, they basically
always argue that because of the way
they have larger vocabularies and the
way they train their tokenizer, um,
non-English and like low resources
languages, they they are packed into
much fewer tokens and so people using
those pay much fewer, you know, uh, much
lower cost at inference time, right?
Which is a which is a great
benefit. Oh yes, question. these plots
um if weight t doesn't have a
significant impact on the valve loss
like why why do we care about like the
training dynamics or the favorable
operation dynamics right okay so the
question was if it doesn't have an
impact on val loss why do we care about
training dynamics um the goal is still I
want to get you know um good training
loss right this is the game that we're
playing and the surprising thing about
weight decay is that somehow it gets us
better training losses like I think the
intuitive thing that makes sense is you
do weight decay it gives you better val
losses But that's not what happens. What
what it's getting you is better training
losses which are also the same as vales.
Yes. Are there differences in the
architecture hyperparameter choices
people make as they move towards like
multimodal architectures if they're
images text? Yes. So the question was
about multimodal models. That is a great
question. My my survey of multimodal
models is very incomplete. Um what I can
say is a lot of the academic and open
work that I've seen um they do uh what
you might call like shallow or like
later fusion um or early fusion of the
modalities and the way that works is you
kind of bolt the vision modality onto a
existing language model. In those cases,
the hyperparameter and architecture
choices are fixed. Right? Um, one thing
I will note and I will talk about this
in just a few slides, um, is that the
multimodal models pioneered some pretty
interesting techniques in stabilizing
language model training and that's been
a really big theme and I'll talk a
little bit about those. So what is
different is often when you like bolt on
this new kind of vision piece and you
like retrain with that that's a big
shock to the model and so you have to
think carefully about how to stabilize
that training process and those
innovations have actually seeped back
into like pure text language model
training. Okay, cool.
So um I went back through and you know I
looked through all these new papers and
as I was trying to think about okay
what's been new in the last year and
sort of what new architecture and
related things have happened actually
you know the the core architecture
hasn't changed much but I think the one
thing that stood out as being very
emphasized in a lot of the releases um
has been what I would call stability
tricks and so these are things where you
would like to train your model in much
more stable ways um and as you make
bigger and bigger models or you train
for longer and longer um these kinds of
issues start to appear more and more. So
I've taken this um from the mode 2 paper
um and actually that paper is a great
sort of set of you know academic results
on LLM training stability and you know
one thing they start with is is kind of
this figure and you look at this blue
curve over here and you look at this you
know L2 norm of the gradient graph and
this is terrifying graph to look look at
right like you know your your loss curve
kind of seems to be behaving okay but
you've got some some bad spikes every
now and and you open up your gradient
norm and it's this horrible plot where
you've got spikes everywhere where your
norms are completely blowing up. Um, and
you know, if you're training models like
this, you're going to have a really
tough time getting it to converge
reasonably. At some point, it's going
to, you know, hit, you know, gradient
norm explodes and like you can't do
anything and your training is done,
right? So, you can't train any further.
And so, there's been a lot of emphasis
basically trying to turn this blue curve
into something that looks a lot like the
orange curve. Um, and of course this
loss is higher, but ignore that fact
because I think they just switch data
sets in between these two training runs.
Um, but this orange curve, you know, has
nice low gradient norms throughout. And
that's really the kind of pod that you
would much rather
see. And so you might ask, where do
stability issues arise in transformers?
And of course, they can arise basically
everywhere. Um but if you look at the
kind of interventions that people are
making um there's really one place that
really stands out as the the kind of
problem child and that's the soft maxes.
Um and it can be a problem because
you're going to be taking exponentials
and those can be numerically you know
badly behaved. Um you're also dividing
two numbers and so you might have a
division by zero, right? So for many
different reasons, this softmax piece is
a is a part that you know um you might
have lots of issues with. And so
actually one more thing I want to talk
about. So where are the softmaxes in a
transformer? Well, there's one at the
very end. So you've got to be careful
about that output softmax. And also
there's soft maxes in your self
attention, right? So there's two soft
maxes that that we're going to think a
little bit about. And for each one I'm
going to mention a stability
intervention that has you know generally
seemed to be
effective. Okay. So the first one is
called the zloss. Um and in my desire to
site a paper that's older I've gone back
to Devlin in 2014. Um where in a machine
translation paper um you know their goal
was to try to you know make sure that
this normalizer was near one. So if you
look at P of X that's the output softmax
over here. Um the output softmax is two
terms. You exponentiate your logets and
then you divide by the normalizer Z
right the Z is just summing up you know
the the values across all the vocap. And
so if you want this Z of X you want to
train the network to have a Z of X close
to one. Well then you can you know
rewrite your loss and you can add a
little second term here to try to force
log of Z of XI to be close to zero.
Right? Okay, so you're going to end up
with an auxiliary loss term that's alpha
log 2 Z of XI, right? You can kind of
see that derivation on the on the right
here. Um, and this is, you know, in some
sense what people often call the Z loss.
Um, I think, you know, Jacob Develin and
others did this for machine translation
for totally different reasons than what
it's used for today. Um but this was I
think the first instance of this in in
language modeling land was Palm who used
this as they called it auxiliary loss of
Z loss 10^4 log 2 Z to basically
encourage the softmax normalizer to
behave nicely and you can kind of reason
through the behavior of this
regularizer. If it succeeds and it
forces log of Z of X to always be zero,
then the log and the exponent the
exponential cancels and you've basically
just got U of R of X. And that's a good
place to be, right? That's a nice
numerically stable operation. So all of
these sort of problematic operations
kind of go away. And so you can think of
the softmax as being well behaved when Z
of X um is close to to uh one or log of
Z is close to zero, right?
And you know, palm in some sense is a is
very much a pioneer because they did
this zlos trick. Um, and many others
didn't really do it for a long time or
at least the ones that had open papers.
Um, but then there was a kind of
sequence of papers um that have done
this. Byron 2 is actually the the
earliest follow-up that I know of. And
then DCLM and Almo and now um several
others have basically picked up on ZLOS
as a very nice convenient intervention
uh for for improving stability. Um and
then uh the other trick that we see so
that was um how to stabilize the uh the
output softmax but we've got another
softmax we've got to deal with right the
other softmax we have to deal with is in
the attention operation um and so you
know this is um from a Nvidia paper I
forgot to put the citation marker um but
here you know this is a a block diagram
of how attention works you know you've
got your your layer norm at the
beginning um you got your 2KVS um ignore
this for the moment. Um you might
multiply your your Q's and your K's.
You'll softmax it. You multiply the V
and then you'll project it. Um and then
that's going to give you your fully
connected and your output, right? So so
if you ignore this this little piece
over here, um you know, this looks just
like your normal multi head attention
operation. So what's kind of the
difference here? Um so several folks uh
came up with this idea or this approach
called the QK norm where you take the
the queries and the keys and you pass
them through a layer norm layer um
before you you know take their inner
product for the softmax operation. Um
and this is a you know very different
kind of approach to controlling the
behavior um of the softmax. Here you're
not controlling the the normalizer Z.
Instead, you're controlling the inputs
to the softmax to be kind of bounded in
size, and that's going to naturally
control uh the the bad behaviors of the
softmax. Um, and as I said before, this
is originally an innovation uh from the
vision and sort of multimodal model
community. Um, Deani in 2023, this was,
you know, a paper on training very large
vision transformers. Um and then
Chameleon and uh Edith Feix from uh
Hugging Face sort of used these tricks
for their like multimodal training
components. Um and then you know it got
picked up by several others like GMAT 2,
DCLM, OMO2 um all basically uses this
kind of techniques um in order to
stabilize um their training. And I think
I'm allowed to add one joke per lecture
and so this is the one I'm going to go
with here. Um I think one of the things
that really has stood out in terms of
stability interventions has been just
how strikingly effective layer norms
are. Right? So we've seen, you know,
going from layer norms just in the the
pre part of the block to the both the
beginning and the end of the
non-residual component and now we've
also thrown it into the Q and the K uh
component. At least in terms of
improving stability, um layer norms have
been shockingly effective without
affecting performance too much.
Um the last trick that I'll note um I
think this one has been sort of not
quite as frequently used um which is to
soft cap um the uh the lojets that go
into the soft. So the other approach
that you can take so qk norm is in some
sense a very heavy-handed intervention
because we're going to operate over the
entire vector. Um but one thing you
could do is after you take the inner
products for self attention, you could
pass them through kind of like a soft
maximum operation. So you can pass them
through this uh equation over here. So
you have your low jets as your input
divided by the soft cap multiply by the
soft cap. What does that do? Well, if
your lows start exceeding the soft cap
by a lot, the tanh is going to clip them
off to one. And so you're going to have
a maximum value of soft cap over here,
right? So this is going to control in
some sense soft clipping of the logets
um and gamma 2 um and I think 2 also do
this um it hasn't been I think quite as
uh popular otherwise and I think the
other sort of evidence against this um
the the Nvidia folks that I mentioned
earlier did actually quite a few
different sort of stability uh improving
interventions and what they find is you
know you have your baseline model over
here this is the the perplexity of the
baseline model 11.19
Soft capping makes it worse. QK norm
actually makes it better because you can
use more aggressive learning rates and
sort of push the optimizer further.
Um, cool. Okay. So, so that's the um end
of sort of the stability improving
intervention stuff. Um, does anyone have
any questions? Um, I think that's been
kind of the the new development over the
last year. Yes. So, for the QKV norm um
like understand that during training you
will have the layer norm being applied
at inference time. Is the layer norm
still being kept? Yes. So the question
was at inference time do you still use
the norm? And the answer is yes because
the layer norm has kind of learned
parameters like the whole you know
action of the layer norm is it takes an
activation normalizes it to unit and
then scales them to some size. If you
take that out that's a huge change to
the model. It will have no idea what to
do with those unnormalized
activations.
Okay
cool. All right. So um I have this last
bit last few slides um that I want to
end with. Um if we if we go over then we
can always push this into the thee
lecture but I think we also have a lot
of content next time because I have to
cover um deepseat v3. Um so the last
thing I want to cover is variations on
the attention heads. Um so attention
heads I think haven't had as much you
know work done to them. Um but there
have been a few I think important
changes that you need to know about in
order to understand uh the models that
are being trained. So the one thing I'll
talk about the first thing I'll talk
about is GQA and MQA. Um and these
aren't really critical to kind of the
training time behavior of the models but
they're very important in understanding
the inference cost and inference
behavior of the models. And because this
is a important architecture change I'll
mention them here um in addition to
probably being mentioned by Percy um in
some of the inference lectures. The
other thing that's a kind of new
development I'll mention is how the most
recent models like Llama 4, if you've
heard of it, supports supposedly 10
million tokens of context. How does it
do that? Well, it does so by sort of
messing with the attention pattern in
very structured ways. Um, and so I'll
talk about um that as well.
So, GQA, MQA. Um, if you've looked at
like some of the larger models like the
big llama models or or others, you'll
have heard or seen this term GQA or MQA.
Um, and I'll talk through what that sort
of means. So, to set the stage, let's
think about the compute that you need to
do attention, right? So, this is once
again 224n slides here. um you're going
to take your you know XQ your your query
and your X K and then you're going to
form your big uh sort of quadratic
attention matrix and you can sort of
walk through each of these matrix
multiplies and you can convince yourself
that the total number of arithmetic
operations is going to be B * N * D ^ 2.
So that's going to be um B is the batch
dimension um N is the sequence length
and D ^ 2 is going to be the hidden uh
dimension
squared and you can ask about the total
memory accesses and this is going to be
B * N * D and this is going to be for
example accessing just this matrix here
this XQ is going to be that size and
then the softmax is going to be B * H *
N^ 2 and you can kind of convince
yourself of that by just thinking about
the size of the softmax matrix.
which is going to be batch time number
of heads times all the different softmax
activations that you have. So that's n^
squ of them, right? Um and you've got a
projection and you've got d squ
projection operations at the very end
over here. And so we can take the ratio
of uh total memory accesses and
arithmetic operations. Um and this is
going to be something that will be very
important in a couple lectures. Um this
idea called um arithmetic intensity,
right? So we want our arithmetic
intensity to be high. What that means is
we want to be doing a lot of compute for
every single memory access that we do.
And this is going to be because memory
accesses are very expensive on a GPU
relatively speaking. And compute is
relatively cheap. Um and so in this you
know batch computation that I'm showing
you here you know the arithmetic
intensity if you take the ratio of those
two things is going to be 1 over um k +
1 over um bn inverse. Um and so this is
going to mean that we can kind of keep
our GPUs um
running um because if we have sort of
large number of heads and we have large
um batch size and large sequence length,
you know, those are all going to be sort
of good large numbers. Of course, this
is what happens at training time, right?
So the issue is that inference time we
do not have these big chunky matrices to
multiply together. And so that's going
to really change the the nature of the
behavior of of our algorithms. So when
we're generating text, right, remember
that we have to generate a token and
then the the transformer has to read
that token and then it has to process
it. And now we can get the next token
distribution and then we do the things
auto reggressively one token at a time,
right? And by doing this, we can't
parallelize this generation process. We
need to go step by step for every single
new token. Um, and when we do this,
we're going to need to incrementally
compute attention. an idea um that
people call the KV cache. Um and so what
do you do? This is a lovely animation um
of a KV cache um that's been explained.
So if you can um sort of look at this
this uh figure, what you're doing is you
know you've got a query token, right? A
query token here is you've generated a
new token. You're conditioning on it and
now you want to ask what sort of
information should I look up in the past
that query token, right? and your query
tokens are shifting from one through n
because you're generating new tokens one
at a time. You're building up this sort
of key cache over here where basically
I'm building up all of the past tokens
keys, right? And the past tokens keys
don't change because they only depend on
things in the past. And so I'm
incrementally as I generate tokens
building up all of these past keys. And
each time I can compute one new element
of Q.K. Right? So the big attention
matrix is going to be this lower
triangular matrix. I'm computing one row
at a time and that row is exactly what's
necessary to generate the next token.
Right? So so this KV cache idea if
you've not seen this before is this idea
of saying I'm going to generate the K's
and the V's um incrementally as I go as
I generate each token and I'm only going
to compute Q um that's absolutely
necessary to do my
operations. And so once again you can go
through and do um sort of the the
various arithmetic uh components of you
know how many uh flops do we do what's
the total number of memory accesses and
if you think about the KV cache right
I'm only multiplying the absolute
necessary keys and values right since
I'm saving all of the intermediate
computations um I'm not wasting any sort
of matrix or vector vector multiply the
total number of arithmetic operations
remains exactly the same B and D
But the memory access patterns are now
different. Why is that? Because you know
when I do this KV caching thing, I'm
going to have to move various kinds of
uh parameters in and out of memory
repeatedly. Whenever I multiply with a
key sort of K matrix, I'm going to have
to put that into memory, right? And then
multiply by K. And then I need to, you
know, put that away and I need to
compute some activations. And so I'm
repeatedly loading in um different
matrices. And that's going to give me a
much higher total memory access of b ^2
d plus n d^2. And so when you take this
ratio now the arithmetic intensity is
not so good. You're going to get n /d +
1 over b inverse. Um and so if we sort
of reason through this. Okay. So if I
want arithmetic intensity to be high, I
want this thing inside to be very small.
So I need really large batches and I
need n / d to be small. What does that
mean? I need really short sequence
lengths or really big model dimensions
and this n /d is really unfavorable
because I don't want a bigger model and
I don't want a shorter sequence length
right and so this is the core in some
sense inference cost trade-off that
people face right you have this very bad
memory access pattern where you have
this one term n /d that's kind of really
killing you in terms of you know the
throughput of your
system and so this motivates this thing
called mqa Okay. Um, and the key idea
here, right, hopefully, you know, you
kind of see from this figure back here
that really the part that's really bad
is the keys and the values. They have
this KV cache thing being built up and
there's memory moving in and out. So,
what you do is you can have multiple
heads for the query, multiple query
heads, but only one dimension or one
head for the keys and values. This
immensely simplifies things. Once you do
this, now you're moving much less
information for the K's and the V's. And
so, you know, KMV is shared. Um, but
query has many heads. And so, you still
have multi head attention um or multiple
queries um but only single K's and V.
So, that's why it's called multi-query
attention. And now when you do the same
kind of arithmetic, we have fewer memory
accesses because we've shared the K's
and the V's. And the arithmetic
intensity is much much better behaved,
right? And so we can increase things
like you know we have uh we've decreased
the first term by a factor of n so
longer sequence lengths are now viable
and the second term is now divided by
the number of heads. So this term is
also not so terrible right so all the
different terms are controlled now and
MQA can give you much better um
behaviors. um GQA or group query
attention basically changes this
slightly. Um instead of having you know
single uh query or sorry um multiple
query and single key you can reduce the
number of keys by some multiple and so
this will let you trade off between kind
of the the inference time behaviors and
the expressiveness of the model because
maybe going from multi head all the way
to multi-query is a little bit um too
aggressive. Um, you know, some works
show that uh GQA uh doesn't hurt, but
multi head attention hurts. I'm not
going to get into that. I'm just going
to close off with this this very last
thing, which I think is a really
interesting development in the last few
months. Um, so back in 2019, OpenAI had
this kind of cool paper um basically
arguing how to build longer attention uh
models. And they were basically arguing
well one way to do that is to come up
with sort of sparse attention patterns
right so instead of paying attention to
all of the sequence I'm going to pay
attention to let's say a local window at
each sort of chunk and then I can have
sort of um other sort of attention
patterns that are like diagonals that
help propagate information across. So
you can build sparse or structured
attention that trades off you know
various kinds of expressiveness versus
runtime. GPT3 uses exactly these kinds
of tricks when they originally released
it um to get larger um attention
windows. Sliding window attention is
another variant of this idea where you
know at each layer you only pay
attention to a small region around your
current position. Um and this also is
going to control the total amount of
sort of resources that you need. Um the
total amount of resources you need in
order to do longer contact. So your
effective receptive field is now the
local one times kind of the the
layers. The final trick. So those were
kind of the older ideas. But the way
that this has kind of been modern
instantiation is some of the recent
papers like llama 4 um and gamma and
cohhere command a have now come up with
this very clever trick of basically
having um transformer blocks where in
this case you have a block a set of four
transformer blocks. The very bottom one
uses full self attention with no
position embedding. So there's no rope
no nothing. It doesn't know about
position at all, but it's full self
attention and it only happens once every
four blocks. And then the three blocks
above it use sliding window attention
with rope, right? And so this is
actually a really clever trick to both
control the systems aspect of things
because the full tension only happens
every, you know, every now and then and
also the length extrapolation aspect
because rope only deals with local
context windows and anything that's
really really long range has no position
embeddings at all. So it could, you
know, extrapolate very very
aggressively, right? Because you don't
have to do this position um
extrapolation that you do uh with
something like rope. So that's a really
cool development that we've seen in the
last um couple months. So all right, I
think we're coming up on time. Uh feel
free to to ask any questions about
architecture or hyperparameters. Um I'll
be happy to answer questions after.