Today we're going to be going into
details on um make writing high
performance code for GPUs. So part of
assignment two is going to be you're
going to have to you know do a bunch of
profiling. You will have to write um
your own Triton kernel uh for flash
attention too. You will need to sort of
make all of this stuff very high
performance. And so in this lecture,
we're going to kind of drill down a
little bit and we're going to try to,
you know, write some high performance
code for um standard components in a
language model. Um so the the plan for
this lecture is we're going to just do a
brief amount of review about GPU stuff.
Um just to make sure you have once again
the basic components of the GPUs that we
need to to understand in order to to
follow the rest of the lecture. Um and
then I'm going to show you a bunch of
sort of really basic things about
benchmarking and profiling which will be
helpful for both the assignment and in
general if you want to write high
performance um pietorrch or deep
learning code. And then um we're going
to basically write some kernels. Um
we're going to write uh CUDA kernels in
sort of C++. We will then do uh the same
thing in Triton. And then lastly, we're
going to, you know, do the easy but very
good thing of using PyTorch's existing
uh JIT compiler um to have it optimized
for us. And then we'll compare all of
those and profile and benchmark things.
And throughout we're going to really dig
in deep. We're going to go down all the
way to uh the PTX. So, so pretty close
to the machine code um to understand
what you know the GPU is actually doing
under the hood when we write um all this
code. Um and then um hopefully we'll
have time and I think we will uh we'll
finish by writing sort of a fast Triton
implementation of softmax at the very
end. Okay. So um assignment one uh has
come to a close. There's still a
leaderboard. You can still submit and
update things there. Um some of you may
be using late days. So um please finish
up assignment one. Um and then
assignment two is now out. And as I said
before um there's going to be you know a
bunch of systems uh stuff that you're
going to need to do. Um there's fun
parts uh that you can do now involving
um GPU kernels and then next week we're
going to talk about parallelism and
that's going to be the other half of the
assignment um writing fast parallel code
like data parallelism um and so on. So
we will get to that next week. All
right. So now remember how GPUs work,
right? So when we have something like an
A100 or an H100, we're going to have a
whole bunch of SM streaming
multipprocessors. within each SM is a
large number of of units that can do uh
computation. Um we have in32 ones or
FP32 ones. Um and then each SM is going
to launch a large number of threads,
right? Um and we have the memory
hierarchy. Um which is that we have DRAM
or global memory which is big and slow.
And then we've got caches that are much
faster. Um and in fact, you know, there
you see here there's this thing called a
register file. This is very very fast
memory that each each thread can access.
And we're going to be making heavy use
of these registers as we write high
performance code for GPUs um today. Um
so the basic structure for the execution
model is going to be we're going to have
a collection of thread blocks and a
block is going to be scheduled on a
single uh SM. Right? So this is kind of
the atomic unit that we're going to be
thinking about especially when we write
uh code in things like Triton. And then
within each block there's going to be a
whole bunch of threads and the threads
are actually going to be the ones doing
uh the computation. And so if you have a
vector and you're going to be operating
over elements of that vector, right,
you're going to write code where each
thread is going to go in and maybe
operate over a few elements of that
vector um at once, right? And all the
threads together will sort of process
the vector um completely. So um why do
we have these things called thread
blocks, right? Why not just have threads
and your your big global uh context?
Well, thread blocks can um communicate
with each other. There's shared memory
kind of within the SM that's pretty
fast, right? So when you need to do
something like matrix multiplication,
you're going to need to pass information
from thread to thread. Um, and within a
thread block that's very fast across
thread blocks or across these groups,
it's going to be very expensive. So you
any data that you need, you're going to
want to keep within the same thread
block or within the same sort of pile.
Um, and that's going to keep things
very, very fast. Um, and that's going to
be as fast as sort of a L1 cache. And
that's a great, you know, place to be.
And so you can use this to to
synchronize across threads. Um but you
can't you know for example synchronize
across blocks you can't really control
um what's going to happen right um and
remember um the thing that I mentioned
last week um there's this thing called
waves right waves aren't sort of an
inherent thing that you you normally
think about but for performance it is an
important component so um when we
actually run these things the threads
are grouped into into consecutive blocks
of 32 threads um and that's a wave and
that gets executed kind of all at once
um in an SM Um and so one thing that we
would like to do is to make sure all the
waves have an equal amount of of uh
computation. We can't always do that. Um
but you know if we can we would like to
do that right? So we want to make the
number of thread blocks ideally uh
divide the number of SMS and to make
sure that each wave has an equal amount
um of uh work. So we're going to ideally
have a lot more thread blocks than SMS.
And we're going to try to make that
happen as we write um high performance
code. Okay. And then the last concept
and maybe maybe amongst the most
important concepts here um is arithmetic
intensity. Um we would like to keep
arithmetic intensity high. Uh we would
like to have more flops than we have
bytes of memory movement. Um and this is
because you know if you remember the
scaling plot from from last lecture um
our compute scaling is much much faster
than memory scaling. So a lot of the
time um computations are going to end up
um being memory bound and we're not
actually getting all all of the work
done right. So um as a general rule you
know matrix multiplication is
computebound if we kind of do it
cleverly. Everything else is going to be
memory bound and we're going to try to
cleverly reduce the amount of of things
that are memory bound or how badly um
things are memory bound. Okay. So that's
our our very very brief sort of review
of GPUs. Hopefully everyone remembers
this. You still have a fresh sort of
memory of of the execution model. Um
feel free to to stop me and ask
questions if if any of you you know have
sort of lingering doubts or questions
about how this is all uh going to work.
Yes. What was the function of warp? What
was the function of sorry warp? A warp.
Um a warp is uh essentially a group of
threads that get executed together. And
the reason why warps exist is that they
reduce the amount of control machinery
that's needed. Um because you're
executing all these threads at the same
time. Um you don't need a control thing
for for each thread. you need them for
blocks of 32, right? And so you see, for
example, there's a lot more compute
units than there are sort of warp
schedulers. Um, and so you're able to do
a lot more parallel work without
worrying about control. And this is one
of the trade-offs with CPUs, right?
CPUs, a lot more uh sort of uh silicon
area dedicated to control and branch
prediction and things like this. Whereas
for GPUs, much more uh emphasis on
computation with simpler controls.
Okay, so now we're going to get into
sort of sort of newer content now. Um,
and I think if there's one highle thing
to remember, um, it's if you want to
write high performance code, you should
remember to benchmark and profile your
code. And that seems very obvious, but
you know, I've seen a lot of things
where, you know, students or or people
go in and they're like, well, I think
this is the bottleneck, so I'm going to
spend three hours optimizing it. And it
turns out it wasn't the bottleneck at
all. I'm sure it was fun, but that, you
know, there were it was kind of time
that was uh misallocated. And so if you
actually use a high performance or very
detailed profiler, you can kind of see
exactly where your you know bottlenecks
are and exactly what the machine is
doing. And once you have that, you can
go and spend your efforts um in sort of
the most important parts um of your code
execution. And so that's the high level
thing I want to get across because some
of the details about you know GPU
execution and you know how you write a
softmax kernel that's going to kind of
change um and maybe you even want to
just rely on the torch compile you know
autojit thing. Um, but the fact that you
should profile isn't really going to
change no matter what the tools are. So,
um, I want you to sort of internalize
that idea that you should be always
profiling if you want to be writing um,
high performance uh,
code. And really, you know, there's a
limit to the theory. I think systems is
part of this course that you can reason
about pretty well. Architecture is
somewhat hard to reason about and you
can, you know, really think about sort
of the roof line model and so on. But,
you know, how fast does your matrix
multiply? Well, maybe that depends on
the library version or your hardware
like which things are bottlenecking for
what reason. There's all sorts of, you
know, microode things that you don't
really fully know. And so, you have to
in the end have to do endto-end
benchmarking whenever you're developing
these things. Okay. So, um I'm going to
have an example computation. This is the
simplest thing you know that we can run
compared to all the things that you all
are doing in your assignment one. Um but
I'm going to run a very simple MLP. It's
going to have 128 dimensions. It's going
to have 16 layers. It's going to have
some batch size and it's going to have
five steps. I'm going to just do
forwards and backwards um for five
different steps here. Um and just to to
make the code clear, it's it's something
like this, right? I'm going to define a
MLP model and we'll sort of I'll show
you that in a moment here. Um and then
I'll define, you know, a random gausian
input and then I'll run it for uh five
steps in that last case where I compute
some forward and then I compute a
backwards and then I return uh sort of
uh the result which is just the mean of
the output of my MLP, right? Not there's
not even losses. It's so simple. It's
just you run the MLP forward and I just
average pool at the end, right? Um and
then the MLP is just kind of the
simplest thing you can also imagine
here. It's just a bunch of linear layers
stacked on top of each other. Um which
is this bit and then you know I've got a
GLU in between, right? So this is just
GLU linear linear GLU so on and so
forth. Everything is nice and square,
right? So hopefully this is a very
simple MLP that you all feel uh pretty
comfortable with. Um and then uh let's
go back. Yes. Oh, sorry. Uh, I want to
go back up to here. Okay, good. Um, and
so now I have this, you know, MLP code
that I want to run. And now I'm going to
do two things. I'm going to benchmark.
So I'm going to do some timings. So I
want to know how long does this function
take to run? And then I'll do profiling,
which is to go inside the function and
ask, you know, where am I spending all
of my time? So let's start with
benchmarking, right? So benchmarking um
is just the measurement of wall clock
time of performing these operations. Um,
and I'm only looking for the endto-end
execution time of, in this case, my MLP
function. And you know, there are some
subtleties to this, like you're sitting
there and you're like, why am I being
told how to invoke, I don't know, uh,
the time it function. Um, but you do
have to be a little bit careful about
how you measure times. And I think, you
know, if you're not paying attention,
you will run into these pitfalls, um,
when you do assignment, too. Um, and so,
what are we doing this for? We're going
to compare implementations later. We're
going to compare our Triton to our
handwritten C++ to um PyTorch's
implementation and torch compile and we
want to know was it worth it to write
that CUDA kernel. Um and we'd also like
to understand when I make my matrix
multiplies bigger, how much slower does
it get? Right? So we'd like to do some
empirical benchmarking of those. So um
throughout this lecture I'm going to be
using this benchmark function. Um and
that's going to be sort of a wrapper
function. I'll step through it. Um
benchmark is going to do the following
things, right? It's going to have a
function that I want to benchmark, which
is run. And then I'm going to do some
number of warm-up iterations, and then
I'll do some number of trials, right?
Um, and you might wonder, okay, so like
what's this um warm-up thing that we're
doing here? Well, one thing that's
really important is, you know, when you
do when you first run your PyTorch code
and let's say it dispatches something to
the GPU, um, it might look very fast and
transparent to you, but that very first
time something is executed in the
background, machine code is being
compiled. you know, that code
instruction might be being sent to the
GPU. There's all sorts of things that
happen to sort of initialize your code.
Um, and so you always want to do some
warm-up iteration to make sure that
you're not measuring sort of the startup
speed. Instead, you want to measure kind
of the the steady state speed, right? If
you're running thousands and thousands
of iterations, you know, what you're
interested in is that part, not
necessarily, you know, how fast can you,
you know, do on the-fly compilation of
your of your CUDA code, right? So,
that's why we have warm-up, and you
should always have a bit of warm-up. Um,
and then, um, another thing that's
really important, and I'll get to this
once we get to the profiler, is you want
to call this thing called torch CUDA
synchronized. Like, what is that? Well,
the GPU and the CPU are basically two
independent compute units in your in
your computer, right? Um, and they can
basically run kind of independently. And
so, their execution model is going to be
this Python code that I have here. This
lives on the CPU, right? And when I run
something, it's going to dispatch a
bunch of CUDA kernels, right, to the
GPU. It says, "Please run these things
for me, right?" And the GPU will go off
and execute those things. And the CPU
will actually go on and keep running,
right? It doesn't wait for those CUDA
executions to stop. And so that's great
for for writing high performance code,
but you should hopefully see the the
immediate problem if you want to do
benchmarking, right? If you're
benchmarking and you've got this model
where the GPU runs off in the side and
your CPU is doing something different,
you're actually not measuring the GPU
execution time, right? Um, so torch CUDA
synchronize basically says, all right,
let's make sure that the GPU and CPU are
in the same state and there's sort of no
cued uh things running and that we're
we're kind of at the same point in terms
of the code that's being executed. And
now, so the GPU and CPU are kind of in
the same state and I'm going to time it
for real, right? and I'm going to time
something for for some number of times
and I'm going to run the computation
which in this case is the is the sleep
command I'm going to do it three times
and since I'm trying to sleep for for 50
uh milliseconds um that's the time that
I'm going to kind of get at the end
right so I I do time three times and of
course here right I'm also calling
torch.cuda CUDA.synchronize at the end
of run to make sure that the GPU and CPU
states are the same. So, right, so the
CPU is running ahead. It's going to wait
uh for the GPU execution to actually
finish here. Uh and vice versa. Um and
so now I sort of finished and then I'm
going to average because you know each
single measurement might be you know
fluctuating because of things like
thermal properties of the GPU and so you
want to take multiple replicates take
the mean and return that. That's our our
benchmarking code, right? Very simple,
but remember kind of the two important
pieces here, right? Always do a warm-up.
Make sure to call CUDA synchronize. Um,
if you do those, it's very simple. If
you get forget to do those, you'll get
pretty crazy numbers like you'll get
that your big matrix multiply finished
instantly, which is definitely not true,
right? Okay. So, now we can do some
benchmarking of matrix multiplies. Um,
I'm going to walk through some of these.
Um, they're just putting numbers to
things that we already know, but I want
to, you know, just walk through it and
and make sure we're on the same page
here, right? So, um, I ran this on the
on the class H100s. I have GPUs. I'm
going to do matrix multiplies over over
these sizes. Um, and then I'm going to
go and collect a whole bunch of matrix
multiply timings um for each of these
dimensions stepping through kind of this
uh benchmark result. And so, we kind of
see, you know, as we expect, right,
super linear scaling of our runtimes as
we increase the matrix size. Of course,
at the smallest sizes like 1024 and
2048, we actually see that the times
don't grow at all because there's
constant factor overhead in just doing
these matrix multiplies like uh these
numbers have to get shipped from the CPU
to the GPU. You know, there's uh
overhead in like launching the kernel.
Um and so it's not the case that you
know it's super linear all the way to
zero. Um but once the matrices get big
enough, we see exactly the kind of
scaling that we expect to see um with
our matrix multiplies, right? Okay. So,
um, hopefully straightforward. Now,
let's try to benchmark, um, our MLP. So,
what are we going to do? We're going to
make our MLP bigger. We're going to have
256 dimensions. We're going to have four
layers, batch size of 256, take two
steps. Um, and so, what's the time that
it takes to do that? Well, it's going to
take 6.2 seconds um, to do that. And now
I could do some basic things. I can uh
scale the number of steps from two to
five and I can benchmark all of those
and I'll get 2 3 four and then five
steps. And unlike in the in the matrix
multiply case, right, if I'm scaling the
number of steps, so the number of
forward and backward passes on my MLP,
right? What do I expect the runtime to
to behave like? Well, I expect sort of
linear scaling, right? And that's kind
of what we see. um there's about five
seconds uh per MLP execution and we see
uh it's about n times five for the
runtime of kind of the endtoend um
object here right okay let me see if I
can reset the uh thing that's being
monitored here oh nope I can't okay I'm
going to zoom out a little bit sorry
about that okay now we can also scale
the number of layers from 2 three four
to five um and what does that give us
well it gives us you know increasing uh
run times once again linear in the
number of layers, right? This time once
again one layer takes about 5 seconds um
a little bit less than that and so we
get about uh four times actually four
times the number of layers um and linear
scaling sort of shows up again.
Unsurprising, right? So both steps and
layers obviously have linear
relationships uh with the runtime and
that is exactly kind of what we end up
seeing at the end here. Um, I'm going to
skip the batch size thing because this
is getting a little bit unwieldy in
terms of the amount of things uh that
are being tracked here. Okay. All right.
So, um, that's the end of this
benchmarking bit. We can kind of make
this nice function that that does a
little bit of warm-up, does CUDA
synchronize, and we can measure the
runtime of anything that we want. And
this is good, and you should do this all
the time in your code, right? You can
measure how long it takes for your new
fancy architecture to run. But then I
think if you want to fix some problems,
uh, benchmarking is a very coarse grain
tool. It tells you that your code is
slow, but it doesn't tell you where the
time is being spent. And so what we
would like to do, um, is instead do, um,
profiling. Um, and so this is going to
be a much more fine grained object that
we're going to want to do. Um, and so
profiling is really nice because it not
only helps you see what where the time
is being spent, which functions, but you
know, when you look at what you're
calling, usually you you interact with
the PyTorch interface, right? Like the
the parts of PyTorch that you call, but
beneath PyTorch, there's this whole
universe of CUDA stuff that's being
called. And when you run a profiler, you
can actually see all the way to the
low-level calls um what is actually
being called. And so you can get a much
nicer intuition for how the the program
is actually being executed on the
hardware. And so we'll step through um
profiling a few simple functions um and
then get a little bit of intuition about
what is um happening. And so one of the
things that is nice is that um if you
want basic profiling um PyTorch has a
very nice kind of built-in profiler that
you can use. Um, and this will allow you
to not leave the Python PyTorch world
and get some fairly reasonable looking
um, outputs. And so I've profiled some
functions here and you can kind of see
the output of this as well. Um, and so
you know I've taken the sleep example
from before. Um, and here is you know
the sleep function and when we profile
the sleep function the profile function
looks something like this. you know, I
have a warm-up again. I have torch CUDA
synchronize. Um, and then I call the
profiler and I'm tracking both CPU and
the GPU times. Um, and then, you know, I
run something and then I synchronize
again and I print out the average table
uh across all the time. Okay. So, I go
back
now. So, now I'm going to profile the
sleep function. Um, and if we look at,
you know, what's happening uh what
happens here? Well, 100% of the time is
being spent on something called CUDA
device synchronize. Uh because there's
no GPU work being done. This is just
kind of a noop. You know, it's kind of a
silly thing to be profiling. And so now
let's look at something kind of
non-trivial, right? So let's look at um
this basic operation here of adding two
uh matrices, right? So I defined a add
function that takes in an A and a B and
adds them together. Um and this is a a
helper function that instantiates two
random gausian matrices and then invokes
uh you know whatever is the in the
operation argument. So this is adding
two uh 2048 size matrices together.
Okay. So now I'm going to profile this
and I'm going to call the profiler and
I'll get back something that looks like
this block over here. Right? So this is
what I get back. Um and I'm going to
have to zoom back out because this is
not going to be all righty. Okay. Um is
this visible from the back? Can someone
give me a thumbs up if it's visible from
the back? And uh Okay, good, good, good.
Or thumbs down if it's not. All right,
so um when we when we uh call the add
function in Python, right, this is kind
of all that we interact with this add
function a plus b, right? That's all we
think about. But actually underneath
here, the underneath the iceberg so to
speak, um there's a lot more that
happens. So this gets dispatched to the
GPU and first um there's this thing
called A10, which is the uh C sort of
interface for PyTorch. And so this
wrapper gets called and it says okay I'm
going to add some numbers right this is
what's being called that's the outer
wrapper and then that dispatches to a
particular kernel um called vectorize
elementwise kernel for comma native CUDA
funure add dot dot dot dot dot right and
this is the thing that's actually doing
the adding and then there's this um also
other thing called CUDA launch kernel
that's taking some time and this is
actually you know the CPU is taking the
command and sending it over to the GPU
that's the kernel launch and that takes
some time and then finally you know the
CUDA device synchronizes we're waiting
for the the GPU to finish and send
things back to us and that also takes
some time right the the mere act of
having a synchronization barrier is
going to cost us some time and so we
basically have you know the time total
in the end here 1.4 4 milliseconds on
the CPU and uh 17 microsconds uh on the
CUDA. Right? So, so they're really fast
on the GPU, slower on the CPU. And if
we're looking at the CPU time that's
being spent, um which is the self CPU
time, we see that kind of the the C++
interface or the C interface is actually
the thing that's costing us a whole
bunch of CPU time. And there's sort of
overhead to doing anything where we're
sending stuff over um to the GPU. So,
that's the ad function. um and we see
you know what's happening under the
hood. Same story here if I want to do a
matrix multiply. So I'm doing you know a
multiplied by b. So this is a matrix
multiply of a and b you know I'm doing
2048 matrices once again. And then I do
profiling. Um now this time I see you
know a10 map mole. So this is saying
like this is the the lower level
interface to do matrix multiplies. Um,
and this is going to dispatch the
cutless, which is Nvidia's sort of high
performance matrix multiply CUDA
library. And then it's dispatching to a
very particular cutless kernel, which is
going to have some tile size. Um, the
names are truncated here. I'll show you
a more detailed version in a minute. Um,
you know, there this is basically
pointing towards a very particular set
of like tile sizes, um, and the number
of of blocks and so on. And so this
thing is parameterized. Um, and that's
actually doing the matrix multiply. And
once again we see the same two things at
the bottom here, you know, the kernel
launch um and the synchronization uh of
CUDA devices. Um and you can sort of see
once again um the the CPU time CUDA time
split. And we're spending way more time
in CUDA because you know matrix
multiplies do take more time than just
adding two vectors.
Okay. Um any questions uh so far? I can
I can pause for a moment here. I think
I've just been uh going sort of very
quickly and on my own through the
profiler. So if anyone has questions I
can I can stop for a moment. If not I
can keep
going. Okay. Oh yes. In this case our
time is greater than our CPU time but we
did have a barrier that like said to for
the CPU to wait for it to synchronize
and so by that shouldn't the CPU time
always be at least the same time?
Counting the time.
Yeah. I don't I don't think this counts
the time.
Cool. Oh yes. Sorry. there's too much
there. Uh is there any particular reason
why like when we switch from adding to
matt the CPU time went down? Um is there
a reason why when we go from adding to
Matt mode the CPU time goes down? That I
am not sure um to be entirely honest.
Yes. Is
there time compared to like running it?
Is there overhead in the profiler um
that can distort things compared to
running it in the real world? Um yes uh
there is overhead in the profiler. Um
like the barriers will do that. I'll
show you a more advanced profiler from
NVIDIA and you can add things like
annotations that will also slightly
distort the timings but but not by much.
Um the really large scale things that
you see aren't going to be really
distorted by the profiler. Um so if
you're looking at like micro timings,
yes, probably. But a lot of the things
that that we care about in the class,
no.
Yes. Just to make sure I'm interpreting
this correctly. So is that like for the
ad case um is the 98% CPU being utilized
over the time period that it's like the
millisecond time period. That's right.
Yeah. So this is the percentage of time
as you can see that the actual
millisecond time that A10 ad was
actually executing in some capacity on
the CPU.
I don't think the
CPU% of what the CPU is doing. Yeah,
that's right. This is the time that the
CPU is active, not not percentage
utilization if that's Yeah. So, this is
not like the total amount of CPU flops
or something. This is a total percentage
of time that the CPU is doing
something. Yes. Okay. Cool. All right.
Um, here's another example of a maple.
Um, so this is a different
dimensionality, right? So, this is a I'm
multiplying 128 uh dimensional matrix
here. Um, so 128 by 128, much smaller.
Um and you'll actually see that now um
it's actually directly executing sort of
this different command. It's executing
um XMMA GMM. GMM is is the uh a matrix
multiply uh type and this is float 32
float 32. You can kind of see from the
the naming of this kernel um what's
actually happening here which is that
this is a tiled matrix multiply um of
some kind and it's not sort of going
through cut list. It's executing this
particular command directly. And so for
a small matrix multiply, you know, you
see that it's dispatching to a different
kernel. Now, so you can kind of see um
kind of the complexity of matrix
multiply um when we're operating at this
high level abstraction, we just think of
matrix multiply as a single thing,
right? We call like a at b and we're
done. But underneath the hood, depending
on the dimensionality that you have,
depending on the hardware that you have,
it will actually dispatch to very
different um matrix multiply sort of
primitives under the hood. And that will
actually manifest in very very different
um sort of performance characteristics.
And so one fun tip is um torch compile
which I will talk about later actually
has an option to sort of microbenchmark
the matrix multiply performance on your
hardware and then it will actually then
pick the the highest performing uh
matrix multiply subruines for your for
your model which you know in the past I
found you know gives you like 10% speed
ups for free. It's very cool that like
optimizing for these things actually
gives you uh free gains out in the real
world. Okay. Um so that's another maple
example. Um and so the cool thing about
the profiler compared to the just the
raw benchmarking is we can now kind of
see which CUDA kernels are being called.
Um we can see that you know different
sizes of matrices lead to different CUDA
kernels. Um and we see you know cutless
80 simp right is a is a diff is this
cutless linear algebra library and it
tells us things um like the t tile size.
So, so far um these operations are very
boring in a way like matrix multiplies
and adds um they're basically one to
one. You you have a you know operation
on the CPU side, it translates to a GPU
operation and it just gets shipped over,
right? So there's just a single
operation in all of these that does
anything on the GPU. So I want to look
at um some more complicated operations
um two more of these um that have sort
of more compound behavior. So what I
want to do now is I want to do um I want
to look at this operation uh called
torch.cis C dist and this is computing
you know for for two sets of matrices
the the pair-wise uklidian distance
between two sets of vectors right so
this is going to be a big distance
matrix computation between a's and b's
um that I want so that's c dist um and
so this is obviously a much more
complicated operation if you want to
compute uklitian distances uh you're
going to need to compute uh dotproducts
you're going to need to compute square
roots um and we're going to see that
once we um compute cedist so now here is
the is the profiled output of cedist. Um
so we see that this torch you know
python command does map in the in the c
interface to some sort of lower level
cedist. So this is a10 cedist which then
maps to a10 uklitian disc. Um and then
this will decompose into a whole bunch
of things like a10 mm mole at 10 pow um
and then sum because these are all
primitives that you're going to need in
order to actually to compute uh the
uklidian distances um between uh all of
your vectors and when you for each one
of these like matrix multiplies and
concatenation um and taking the powers
um you have a corresponding uh cuda
command that is being called here you
know we have gmm which become we've
become familiar with So this is a matrix
multiply. It's taking 78% of our compute
or our compute time on the GPU. Um we've
got you know copies um and sort of
concatenation of arrays. This takes um
6% of the the execution time and then
this sort of vectorzed elementwise
kernel which is taking the power um
takes 5% of the GPU time and and 3% goes
to the sum. So now we get this very nice
low-level breakdown of where, you know,
my GPU is spending all of its time. Um,
and from this, you know, I can get some
sense of um where maybe I should should
spend my time optimizing. You know,
maybe I think I can optimize my matrix
multiply. That would be great because
that's 70 plus% of the time spent um in
the
GPU. The the final example um the final
two examples, sorry, that I want to uh
talk about is GLU and softmax. So these
will be our running Oh, sorry, there's a
question. What's the too wild.
Um, okay. So, I will maybe answer that
question in a in a few minutes because
there's a cooler profiler that shows you
a much nicer picture and so I can
justiculate here, but I think it'll be
better to show that with pictures. Um,
okay. So, I'm going to talk about uh now
the GLU um and the softmax. Um, so the
GLU is going to be um our running
example um throughout the class. So,
this is a nonlinearity. If you remember,
it's the Gausian error unit. Gausian
error linear unit. Um and that's going
to be a product of a uh tanh and a uh
exponential if I remember right. Um and
so we're going to have you know um all
sorts of operations. So we're going to
add a and b and then we're going to call
gelu sort of simulating the the linear
plus nonlinear uh structure that we
might have um in our MLP. And so we see
once again uh basically the same sort of
mapping. we see a10 add corresponding to
a plus b and then we have the cuda
equivalent and then we have actually a
gue function implemented in cuda which
is all the way down here and that takes
about 33% of the compute okay fairly
reasonable and then we have once again
the softmax I won't go through all of
these in sort of gory detail um since
you know they all start to look the same
after a while but the thing to to really
point out that I think is cool is that a
lot of these really core primitives like
softmax and gellu um there's kernels
written for them, right? So, it's not
like the GPU is executing the the basic
primitives. There's sort of a fused
operator that computes all of this. So,
there's no back and forth between CPU
and GPU for all of these. So, okay. Um,
I mentioned before that I was going to
sort of answer this question of what the
CPU was doing. Um, and so let's think
about something a little more
sophisticated, right? I had the MLP
example that I started with for
benchmarking. Um, and I would, let's
say, like to optimize that MLP, make it
run really fast. So how can we do that?
Well, ideally we would sort of profile
this um in a nice sort of fine grained
way. So if we use the torch profiler,
this is kind of what we would get. Um if
you remember the MLP, there's you know
stack linear layers. There's a forward
and a backward. Um and you see roughly,
you know, uh there's this backward thing
that's happening. There's a matrix
multiply. There's linear. Um and then
there's accumulate grad operation um for
the backward. Um and here's the matrix
multiply kernel. And then there's only
10 things that can fit here. So I think
this this gets cut off at a certain
point. But this this is nice. It does
tell you that most of the time is being
spent in the map moles. Um but you do
kind of wonder like where does all the
rest of the time go and why does only
31% of my time stay here and where's the
60% here? It's a A10 mm but there's no
corresponding kernel. Right? This is a
little bit mysterious and for something
that's very complex um module this is
not a very good
visualization and so for that I think we
have to actually uh get out a real sort
of grown-up profiler um and you will
have to you know or we will ask you to
um look at uh this thing which is
Nvidia's endsite systems um and this is
the kind of Nvidia's sort of detailed
way of looking at GPU behavior um and
performance And so we will actually kind
of see exactly what is happening as we
run this MLP. So actually in the back
can you see I don't know this tiny text
over here. Thumbs up. Okay. All right.
If you can see it then I'm not going to
zoom in but it does it does seem small
even from here. Um all right. So
basically if we look here um we see
several different things. We see CUDA HW
over here and then we see threads. Um,
and so this top half, this CUDA part,
this is what the GPU is kind of doing.
And then in this threads part, um, we
see kind of what the CPU is doing. And I
can also pull up the code, I think. Yes.
Um, the code here, um, when I profiled
it, I've added a few annotations. Um,
okay, this one I zoom in for sure. Uh,
okay. Let's,
um, excellent. All right. Um so I've
annotated the code with this set of
things that says let's see uh
NVTX um which basically annotates uh my
code with annotate uh with markers. So
when the profiler comes in here it will
know that this piece of code belongs to
a block called define model. And for
example the this part that says step
range push and range pop. this range
here from line 77 to line 55 should be
annotated with something that says step
underscore step. Okay, so I've added all
these annotations in my code before
calling um my profiler. And so let's go
back here. So now if we go to this line
that says nvtx, we can kind of see
define model um which is the thing that
I wrapped my my model construction call.
And then I see step zero, step one, step
two, step three, step four, step five.
So each step is now nicely annotated in
this profiler and we can kind of see all
of the things that the model is doing um
as we as it goes along and I'll start on
this side. One thing we see is that this
um piece of code it doesn't do very much
work. It takes only 14 seconds. So
actually most of the time for the
profiler is spent on overhead. So the
part up until roughly here is you know
things like just loading the libraries
and that takes a long time. It takes
apparently 7.5 seconds. just initialize
everything and then on at least on the
GPU at
7.5 seconds or so into the program it
starts actually building the model and
you see here on the memory footprint you
know this is the place where now memory
is being sort of uh allocated and on the
GPU memory the memory usage starts to
grow right now the model is now
constructed at this point and then step
zero is where sort of the action starts
to happen and so you were asking earlier
what's happening um between the CPU and
and sort of GPU. And so how the
execution model of this works is um here
is sort of step zero on the CPU. And I'm
starting right here and here's the
forward pass and this is layer zero. So
let's just kind of think through what's
happening. Um as I said before when you
first encounter or when you first call a
piece of code in PyTorch um it doesn't
just directly execute. it will actually
do things like um you know on the fly
compile things and so um so you know
this thing like runtime triggered module
loading um is sort of overhead work
that's being done in order to just
initialize the layer and the computation
and move sort of various bits of code
into the GPU. So this takes a long time.
Um and then after this layer zero is
done now if I look at sort of any slice
here let's sort of zoom in um to
selection we'll see that each of these
layers is really really really quick and
what happens here is when I highlight
this layer one over here on the CPU side
notice that that's not where layer 1 is
on the GPU side right so as I said
before the CPU and GPU are kind of two
different execution devices so I start
at layer zero I'm done with layer zero I
start layer one. Now, the CPU is
actually just sending all of the the
sort of um CUDA commands um the CUDA
kernels um it's launching all the CUDA
kernels already to the GPU at this
point, right? So, when the CPU is
saying, I'm doing layer one, what it's
actually doing is it's queuing commands
into the GPU. It says, "Now run this
thing next. Run this thing next. Run
this thing next." Right? Um and so the
CPU is running way ahead of the GPU. And
by the time layer 1 starts executing um
on the GPU, actually, we're already at
layer 9 on the CPU, right? Right? The
CPU is running way ahead and there's
basically um a queue that the the CPU
maintains where um it's sending a fixed
number of uh kernel uh CUDA kernels to
the GPU. And so once you hit that Q
depth, it's going to sort of stop
running ahead. But until that point,
it's just going to keep going and going
and going as far as it can, right? Um
and in this case, this does become um
I'm gonna zoom out again. Uh okay, undo
the
zoom. There we go. Um, in this case,
this kind of gets uh a little extreme
because if I zoom out once more, um,
notice how, you know, in these
steps, I'm running way ahead. Like the
step zero is here, step two is here.
This was step one, which basically took
no time at all. Um, step two is here.
So, it's the CPU is basically running
one entire step forward and backward
ahead of the GPU. Um, one interesting
thing that you might do is if you're
writing, you know, various code for for
training a language model. One normal
thing that you might do is let's go back
to the code. Um, I might do something
like print, you know, my losses in
between iterations. Um, this seems like
it should have no effect on what the GPU
is doing, right? You're like, well, it's
a print statement. How much could it
could it do? Um if you think about it
for a moment, this will have big impacts
on the execution layout uh on the GPU
because in order to print this
statement, right, this print statement
happens on the CPU and the CPU needs to
get the loss. That means it needs to
wait for the GPU to compute that loss.
And so let's look at what happens. So
here, you know, as I said, you know,
step four on the CPU happens way before
the GPU equivalent. Now, let's switch
back. Now, this is the version that I
profiled where it has the print
statement, right? And then now I sort of
zoom into selection here. Now see how
step one and step two are basically kind
of synchronized now, right? Because I
have to wait for the loss to get
computed. And and you look at this and
you say, "Oh, but it's still a little
offset, right? Like step two, step one
isn't exactly aligned with each other."
So now let's kind of zoom back in and
see, okay, what happened to step one on
the CPU? Well, um, basically the end
point of step one on the CPU is also
kind of where the optimizer step starts,
right? So by the time that forward is
done, um, sorry, this CUDA stream
synchronizes the thing. So this CUDA
stream synchronize command on the CPU,
this is basically saying I'm just
waiting for the GPU because I can't run
ahead. I'm waiting for this loss to be
computed and to be spent sent back to
me, right? So this is kind of a dummy
operation where it's saying CPU waits,
waits, waits, waits, waits, waits,
waits. Um, well, the backward step is
done. So now I can print the loss. I've
printed the loss. Okay, now the CPU can
start running ahead. And it does run
ahead and starts sending step two stuff
now. And then well, once this hits here,
it's sort of run out of commands. It's
waiting for the loss again. CUDA
synchronize. Wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait. Backward step is done. Now I can
print the loss. Now I run ahead again.
Right? So um, in this case, you know,
the GPU is still essentially full
utilization in both cases. But in
extreme cases where let's say you're
printing tons of stuff all the time,
actually you're going to introduce a CPU
bottleneck, right? Because the GPU has
to the CPU has to keep waiting for the
GPU and it can't launch the kernels um
sort of ahead of time. So um that's kind
of a really cool thing that you can see
uh with the profiler um sort of this CPU
versus GPU and they're actually
different devices that communicate to
each other. It's not at this single
unified object and you wouldn't see that
unless you you started to look at some
of these like more advanced profilers.
Um any any question about that sort of
set of
things? Cool. Okay. Um and the other
thing that I want to kind of show you is
you know the the profiler thing that I
was playing with before. You can also
generate very similar views um in NSIS
as well where you sort of select some
range of of things that you want to
let's let's uh do a warm-up. I said we
should so we should exclude the first
couple of steps. So we'll start at step
three and we'll we'll measure some
steps. Um sort of in this range we could
take the kernels. This is what's doing
the computation. And you can see that
there's actually many different kinds of
matrix multiply. This is one matrix
multiply kernel. This is a different
matrix multiply kernel. There's a
different sort of like vectorzed element
kernel. Um and all of these are taking
different amounts of computation. And we
can take this and we can say oh show me
um in the events view all the things
that are happening. Um, and I can also
see sort of the stats view all of the um
the time that it takes. Wait, let's see.
We want
um we want the average time. No, we want
sorry the CUDA
kernel
execution summary. Yeah, we want the
total duration of the kernels and so we
can see which kernels are taking the
most time um and aggregate across these
views. So this this is actually a very
very powerful tool that can give you
both like the the aggregate view of
what's slow and what's fast as well as
individual kernels that are being
launched and when they're launched and
where the CPU uh commands for that came
from. Um and I guess one one final side
note here is this is one of the reasons
why um you know it doesn't matter that
we're programming in Python and Python's
not a very high performance language,
right? Because the CPU is never the
bottleneck because the CPU can run ahead
and sort of cue commands into the GPU.
Um, and so this sort of detaching or
like this disconnecting uh aspect
between the GPU and the CPU is one of
the key reasons why we can use this nice
highle programming language and yet
still get sort of full utilization um
out of sort of our
GPUs. Cool. Okay. Any questions before I
sort of switch back to to this because
I'm going to leave uh NSIS sort of
forever for this lecture at this
point. Cool. Yeah, but you'll get to
play with it in assignment two, and I
think you'll appreciate it because it
gives you like a a really interesting
view uh into what your hardware is
actually doing to make these like
language models uh train. So, okay, that
was benchmarking and profiling. Now, you
have all the tools you need to be able
to do sort of performance things. Um,
and now we're going to write some
kernels in the remaining time. So,
remember kernel fusion, right? So, this
was the the image that I showed you um
in lecture, right? there's a little
factory. Every time I need to do an
operation, I need to ship it from the
warehouse to the factory and back. And
so if I, you know, naively do a bunch of
operations in sequence without thinking
about it, I'm paying for a lot of sort
of shipping cost back and forth from
from the warehouse, what I should do is
have one factory that does all the
operations at once. So I do not pay for
this cost multiple times, right? That's
very important. So now we're going to do
GLU. And we're going to write a kernel
for GLU. And I'm going to write that
kernel in several different ways. And
we're going to look at the performance
impact of doing that. Um, and so we have
the PyTorch implementation of GLU. And
that looks just like this. Um, torchn
functional GLU. Um, and I I invoke
approximate equals tanh because um I
want this to exactly match the naive
thing that I'm going to do next. So this
is not going to be, you know, actually
multiplying by um the the CDF of the
gausian. it's going to be some
approximation to that that's easier to
compute. Okay, so that's the PyTorch
Gal. And now I'm going to do the dumb
thing, right? I'm you're going to look
at this code and say this is going to be
low performance. Um I'm going to go in
and in PyTorch I'm going to write GLU as
0.5 * X * 1 +
tanh / 2 * X +
0.044715* X cub. Right? Um magic
formula, but this is a good
approximation to the GLU. can you can
look it up or or convince yourself this
is true. Um but if you do this um you
see that there's a lot of operations
that happen right there's like a tanh
there's a x cubed there's multiplication
by a constant in addition um and
multiplication by 0.5 and x um if this
involves you know multiple different
CUDA kernels this is probably going to
be slow right that should be our
intuition at this point from fusion um
so let's see if that's true okay so
these two are are the same you can see
at the top left they compute the exact
same numbers um and you know we can
systematically check this on random
gausian. And now let's sort of benchmark
the two. Okay, so the manual time is 8.1
um seconds for a really really big GU.
Um and PyTorch time is is 1.1, right? Uh
milliseconds, sorry. Um and the fuse
version is going to be uh significantly
faster. In fact, eight times faster.
Wow. You know, big difference from from
writing a simple kernel. Um, of course
your your map moles are probably still
going to be the bottleneck, but it would
be really cool if we could go from that
8 milliseconds to that 1 millisecond,
right? That would feel very satisfying.
So, we're going to try to get close to
that 1.1 millisecond um in the next few
parts of the lecture. So, now um let's
look at the the what's happening under
the hood. Um I don't need to look at
NSIS because all I really want to know
is some very high level stuff for the
manual GLU. You know, kind of just like
I said, it's going to do a whole bunch
of operations. It's going to do a bunch
of multiplications. It's vectorzed, but
it's a bunch of, you know, CUDA kernels
being launched here. Um, and notice on
the right, this CUDA kernel gets called
three times because we have a whole
bunch of multiplications floating around
here. Um, we've also got, you know,
addition. We've got a tanh. Um, and each
one of these is is probably kind of slow
and in the end, you know, we're
incurring fairly large overhead doing
this. Um, now let's do the same thing,
um, sorry, with the pietorchu. And this
is this is really great. There's a
single CUDA kernel launch. It happens
once and it just processes the whole
thing. This is what we'd like to see. Um
and of course this is very very fast
because it's just a single uh CUDA
kernel, right? So um this is really nice
and we would like to to you know somehow
get to to the CUDA kernel. And so the
first thing you might think of um
depending on how much you know about
writing GPU efficient code is all right
the PyTorch people must have written
this in the lowest level language
possible. So we're going to do the same
thing. We're going to go to not the
lowest level possible but we're going to
go to the the C++ API and we're going to
write the CUDA kernel in C++ right? So
let's open it up and write our own um
CUDA kernel. So how is that going to
work? Okay, so we have gone in and sort
of created a C++ version of the whole
thing. So CUDA, you know, when we say
CUDA is actually the the C++ API for
interfacing with and programming GPUs.
And just like sort of the the logical
model of a GPU that we describe, you
know, we're going to write some sort of
function f. Um, and then when we sort of
invoke this CUDA kernel, it's going to
automatically call F on all the elements
of a vector or a matrix. Um and then we
will get to parallel compute um
everything that we want. Um as
nomenclature we're going to have a grid
um which is a collection of thread
blocks. So think of this as I have a
task. I'm going to cut it up into
pieces. Um and there's going to be a
number of blocks. This is the you know
in in a 2D grid for example. Um there's
going to be sort of a row uh coordinate
and then there's going to be a column
coordinate. And this will be very useful
if you're working with matrices. And
then there will be um the size of each
of these blocks like you know how how
big are these in terms of the number uh
of thread blocks. So this is the
dimension of the blocks. Um and then
there's a collection of threads um
within these blocks and this is the
coordinate that for example one thread
block lives in and then each thread is
within each block. Right? So there's
sort of hierarchical structure here.
There's a grid and then there's a thread
inside a grid. Right? And then we're
going to basically each function is
going to take in uh three things. It's
going to take the block index like which
thread block do I belong to um which uh
what's kind of the block dimensions um
and then what is the index that I am
like my my thread index and with these I
can kind of know which coordinate that I
am in in the matrix or the vector and
then I can sort of decide what logic
that I want. Um, one sort of last thing
before we uh go through the actual C++
code is, you know, whenever you're
you're trying to debug CUDA, um, you
want to launch with CUDA launch blocking
equals 1. This will allow you to
actually debug um your CUDA kernel. It
will give you sort of error messages
back um at a at a cost in terms of the
the runtime. Um, if you don't do that,
you are going to have a bad time uh if
you're writing CUDA code and and needing
to debug. So, okay. Um, here is uh my my
GLU code and let's go through it kind of
piece by piece and then I'll talk about
what all the pieces are doing. Um, this
will probably take the longest out of
the the things that we're going to walk
through. Um, other than the machine
code. Um, and once you understand this,
you should be able to understand all the
other pieces. So, we'll go through this
a little slowly. Um, so there's two
parts of this code. So, the first part,
this GLU kernel piece up here, this is
the actual kernel. This does the
computation, right? This is going to get
sent to the GPU. It's going to do the
computation and then it will return the
results. This piece, the GLU function
here, this is a wrapper, right? This is
lives on the CPU. It's going to
orchestrate the launch of the kernel
which is actually going to go out and
live in the GPU, right? Um, so maybe we
can start with kind of this uh sort of
wrapper piece, this GLU function first,
right? So we're always going to check
two things. Um, basically in in the the
Triton or the the CUDA code, we're
always going to check. Oh, sorry.
There's a question back there.
Okay. Sorry, that's my bad. Okay, let me
zoom in. That is an easy fix. Um, but I
needed to know that that you can't see.
Okay, good. Um, all right. Is this good?
Okay, excellent. Um, okay. So, um, we're
going to start with the gallery
function. And there's two things that
we're we're always going to need to do.
The first one is to um make sure that X
lives in like the the GPU device, like
the CUDA tensor of some kind, right? If
it's not um well well that's going to be
a problem um we're not going to be able
to do anything on the GPU. The second
thing which is maybe less obvious is
that we want to check to make sure X is
contiguous. What that means is it lives
in a contiguous block of memory because
when we index into X, we're going to do
a whole bunch of indexing arithmetic and
we're going to assume that X lives in a
block of memory, right? And if it
doesn't, it's just going to be, you
know, basically impossible to do this
with with any level of generality. Um,
and so when we compute the GLU, right,
we take in an input X and we're going to
output a Y, right? And so we need to
allocate a output. So torch tensor Y
equals torch empty like X. This is just
saying well give me sort of a output
tensor space or a pointer to a output
tensor um that is just like the
dimension of x and notice that I'm not
calling zeros. This will save on extra
operations. I don't need to zero out
these y's because I'm going to write
into them anyway, right? So this is a a
minor but you might as well do it
optimization. And then um basically in
all the code that we write, we're going
to need to figure out the grid, right?
So what's the total number of elements
that I have? What's the size of each
block? The number of threads that I have
in each block. And then how many blocks
total do I have? And when I need to
figure out the number of blocks, I'm
going to, you know, call CD, which is
going to be essentially take the the
ratio of num elements to block size and
then take the ceiling, right? Because I
need to round up to make sure that very
last set of elements that sort of isn't
divisible by block size still gets
computed, right? So I I take the ceiling
uh rather than the floor. And then this
is all very simple bookkeeping stuff.
And then I say all right launch the
kernel. You know the GU kernel gets
launched. Um and this sort of angle
brackets is saying this is kind of the
um with uh the given number of blocks
and the and the size of each block. And
this is going to be passed into um sort
of the the kernel command. And then I'm
going to pass in the pointers to x's and
y's, right? I'm not actually going to
pass the the the values of x's and y's
um and the total number of elements. And
I need this to compute sort of um
essentially the boundary conditions um
of my kernel. So now let's go to the
actual kernel itself. Right? So I have
global void gel kernel and I get in
pointers for in and out and I have
number of elements items. Um and this
keyword global um the the website sorry
the the rendering here has mangled it a
bit a little bit but you should think of
this as underscore global and this is a
keyword that distinguishes it as a as a
CUDA kernel uh function. And so what am
I doing? Well, you know, this thread is
actually supposed to operate on a single
element I, right? Um, but I don't get I
as input. Like the code doesn't actually
tell me you're in a vector in coordinate
I. So I need to compute where I am. And
how I'm how am I going to do that? It's
going to be I take my block index,
right? I only have one dimension. So
it's block index.x. So just the first
coordinate. Um, and then multiply it by
the size of each block. The the block
dim.x. X and this tells me, you know,
basically the starting point within
within my current block. And then now I
add in thread idx. So, you know, I know
where the start of my current block is
and I add in the offset to where I am
within the block and that gives me my
global coordinate I, right? So, some
some bookkeeping computation just to get
the coordinates here. And then this is
important too. You see this pattern uh
basically in all the CUDA code that
people write. Um there's no kind of out
of bounds checking naturally. And so
what you do is I have my coordinate and
I'm going to check to make sure that you
know I am supposed to be processing
something that's inbounds. And some of
the threads at the very end of your
block, they're going to be processing
stuff that's out of bounds in memory.
And you do not want it to touch those.
And so you you basically condition it on
i less than num elements. And you do
nothing if you're outside of that.
Sorry. Yes.
Sorry.
This is just the extension uh that you
sort of write the the CUDA code in. It's
to distinguish it from, you know, just
your standard C
code. Okay. Um so this is just a file
name thing is this CU. There's nothing
particularly special about it. Um okay.
And then so now you know within here
we're going to just do our computation,
right? It's just going to be I'm going
to write out um I have my input in. I'm
going to index into the E element and I
compute my GLU just like I did before
and I assign it to out of I and then I'm
done. Right? That's all that's all that
I need to do. And since this is all
pointer stuff, um I don't really need to
worry too much about what is um kind of
actually happening here. So um that's
basically it. I can then take my sort of
CUDA gelu uh code that I have um and
then I can load this sort of C++ code in
line and then I can just have it compile
into a module all within Python. It's
all very nice and convenient. You don't
really have to go out onto the command
line um and do things. And so now um we
have CUDA galu defined. Um, so this is
nice and basically it's a compilation of
this. Um, and I can call it from within
Python and we'll use the C bindings to
call this guy. Okay, we're done calling
CUDA GLU. Um, I have my, you know, I can
check that the manual GLU and the CUDA
GLU are the same. And now let's
benchmark the two. Um, so I have the
time that it takes to run PyTorch. And,
you know, just like last time, it's
about 1.1 milliseconds. Um, and manual
time, remember, is 8.1 milliseconds. And
so, drum roll, what is our CUDA time?
Well, we've gotten it down to 1.8,
right? Not quite as good as PyTorch's
implementation, but, you know, we're
we're uh getting pretty close to PyTorch
time, right? We've we've gone from 8
milliseconds to 1.8 milliseconds, which
is which is not bad. Um, because that C
code wasn't that hard to write. And so
now we we also do some profiling. Um,
and we can kind of see what is happening
here now. Um, and you know it's called
the GLU kernel, right? This is the the
code that got shipped off to the GPU.
Um, and then it's calling empty like
this is the initialization. Um, and then
empty strided, right? Um, and then CUDA
launch kernel and CUDA device
synchronize. Um, and that's basically
all that's happening. And notice how you
know once again this is a single CUDA
kernel eats up 100% of the GPU time.
Kind of like what we what we wanted,
right? Okay, so there's some further
optimization we can do, but this is
really already solved the problem of you
know kernel fusion. We fused all the
operators together. Okay. Um so pretty
good. Um these kinds of elementwise
operations are easy to write in CUDA.
Like if you have a new kind of I don't
know um uh nonlinearity. You could
easily write a CUDA kernel for it
yourself if you really wanted to. Um but
more interesting operations are going to
require reading multiple values like
doing reductions. Those are going to get
a little more complicated. um flash
attention will be a little bit more
complicated but not too much so when you
have to do it um in the assignment.
Okay. Um any questions on the on the
simple C++ uh CUDA kernel? Yes.
Check the beginning. Yeah. Does that
throw an error? Is it like caller
kernel? Yeah. So so the question was
what happens if it's not contiguous? At
least in the code that we wrote it will
just throw an error because it's an
assert. um you could potentially write
code to handle it, but there's almost no
reason for memory to be fragmented
because it will allocate contiguously.
Um and you won't deallocate like the
middle of a memory unless you're doing
something like really tricky. Um and so
you should you should really unless
you're doing something pretty advanced
expect to have continuous memory.
Sometimes you do like a transpose or
jump operation that makes memory not.
So like when you're encoding at a higher
level should you be careful to
conversely make like forced to be
continuous before calling operation.
Yeah. So so the question was like if
you're uh transposing then you're no
longer going to be continuous. You're
going to have like a you know jump
between all the elements in the index.
If you're sort of row traversing
something that's sort of column stored.
Um yeah. So so I think transpose or like
views or like essentially shuffling
dimensions is like the one exception to
this. But that's handleable in like the
outer like sort of the wrapper part,
right? You can basically pass it
something that is continuously indexed.
Um and for a lot of the matrices, you
won't really care, right? So yes, what
would happen if you were to choose a
different block size, right? So what
would happen if you chose a different
block size? Um the sort of uh GPU
related sort of concerns would kick in.
Sort of like do you have enough uh
blocks for to saturate your SMS? um and
do you have enough work within each uh
block? And those are like kind of the
two things that could uh matter here.
But I think my guess is that for block
sizes that are are relatively large like
1024, it probably won't matter past a
certain point because we're not doing
anything advanced. It's all entry- wise
operations for this like very very
simple example. Um yeah. is the reason
that our non GPU version was so slow
because this ask to like do a small
operation of GPU back.
So, so the question was like why was our
um non CUDA kernel sort of like manual
thing so slow? Um it's not that it's
sending things back from GPU to CPU per
se like X is going to live in the GPU.
we allocate it in GPU like we'll do like
as the device like CUDA um but it's
going to basically not be in the SM uh
the whole time right so once we do like
X squar right that's a you know a CUDA
kernel and so that multiplication
operation will read the the the sort of
vector from the global memory into the
SMS do the computation it'll write it
back and so this is all in the in the
sort of DRAM to SM communication cost
rather than the CPU to GPU communication
cost um of Of course, if you write like
as device CPU, then you'll hit get the
uh you know CPU transfer cost in
addition to the to the DRAM transfer
cost. Okay, so now um you've seen that
and like okay so that was not too
painful but it would be really nice if
we had nicer sort of Python abstractions
for writing CUDA kernels and this is
what Triton is and Triton is quite nice.
It like has this very nice middle ground
where you don't have to manage literally
everything about the GPU. So um Triton
um is sort of a domain specific language
uh developed by OpenAI in 2021 um and it
makes GPU programming um much more um
accessible. So like you you write
everything kind of in in Python um and
you don't really think about the threads
anymore. You think about thread blocks
um and Triton manages a lot of stuff
that is annoying but can be
automatically optimized. So it can
manage uh coalesing of memory. Um so
remember that you know from VRAM you get
four uh sort of adjacent values at once
with something called burst mode. So you
really want to make sure that you know
your memory retrievalss are are sort of
grouped into adjacent sort of four
element or more um sort of calls at
once. So it will handle those
automatically. It will group those. Um
it will do shared memory management um
when you need to sort of manage um which
sort of uh memory that you're writing to
within the SM with multiple threads um
from within each SM you know you might
need to stop or start threads all
managed automatically um but scheduling
across SMS or what different SM do
that's manual so like the kind of the
programming model is that you're going
to think kind of at the SMcententric
level and the compiler will handle a lot
more of the lower level details Um, and
Trion is quite nice because it can
outperform by quite a bit a lot of
PyTorch implementations. So, it's kind
of like going all the way to writing
CUDA, but you're still in the very
familiar Python land. And I think a very
underappreciated um advantage is sort of
as it's written here. It's all in
Python. You can step through it. You can
kind of debug it uh fairly nicely. And
so, let's step through a Triton kernel.
Like once again we're going to write GLU
um and we're going to do it um in
Triton. So this I I've you know put the
code to be as similar structure as
possible to our other code. Right? So
this is sort of the the CPU side code so
to speak. This is the the wrapper code.
It takes in X which is a torch tensor
and I've got my two asserts at the top.
Um and I'm going to allocate um an
output tensor Y using empty like once
again. And it has the same exact sort of
coordinate computation. uh sort of
components and even the the kernel
launch looks very similar. I've got this
num blocks annotation and then my block
size is is you know at the end here not
in part of this brackets but basically
I'm passing the the same information to
my kernel and now trying kernel um is
this code over here um and this is going
to do the same thing as what we were
doing before but now it's nicely written
in Python um and you know the mental
model here is the inputs are going to be
at x pointer um yp pointer is the output
uh vector sort sort of the starting
coordinate and the block size is how big
you know each of my blocks are and num
elements is going to be sort of the very
end of my array. So now I need to to get
this set of of lines 557 to 561. This is
doing the the computation of my index
right I did I equals you know some
formula before this is doing the same
calculation over here. I'm calculating
where is the start of my current block.
Well that's my block ID times the size
of the block. that gets me. Let's say I
live in block one. It'll get me this
point right here at the middle. Um and
then um afterwards I need to know where
do I live within my block? Well, that's
going to be um kind of the offset. But
now notice one difference. Um I don't
get in an offset because I'm not
programming threads, right? I'm
programming blocks. And so what does
that mean? Well, my offsets are actually
a vector, not a single value. because
this this is basically going to be I'm
going to do vectorized operation where
the vectorzed operation is going to be
handled by different threads. So here my
offsets are the start of the block plus
a vector this range of block size sort
of offsets. So I'm my offsets are all of
these coordinates within block one at
once. Of course, if I'm at the very end,
I might go off the edge. And so, I need
a mask to handle anything that lives off
the the boundary of my vector. Now, I'm
going to load in a sort of single
vectorzed operation um everything um at
once. So, xpointer plus offsets. These
are sort of the values that I'm
responsible for masked up and it's
loaded into X which is um uh my sort of
internal values my internal sort of
temporary vector that I need and with
this temporary vector I'm going to do
exactly the old GLU computation. Um
there's no tanh so I compute that
manually but this formula you can
convince yourself is the same as what we
have here. Um and then y is going to be
the formula computed up here. Now once
I'm done I need to write it back into my
output sort of buffer or my output
vector and so I compute sort of my
targets. So this is y pointer plus
offsets. I take my values um my
temporary values y and then I store it
right. So this is very very very similar
to what came before but this one is the
vectorzed version. I get to operate on
an entire block at once. And so instead
of kind of thinking at the perspective
of um of a thread, I'm thinking from the
perspective of a block, but not too
different, right? This is all fairly
similar um stuff. So now I've written my
Triton Gellu and all right, I will I
will do this fairly quickly. All right,
so one last thing I will only point out
a few things here because I don't want
to get like so in the weeds that you all
like get up and leave. Um, but the one
last cool thing that we can do is Triton
of course compiles into low-level sort
of almost machine code for the GPU. And
we can look at, you know, this very
low-level called PTX code um after the
Triton compiler sort of goes over it.
And it's actually kind of cool. You can
kind of see how the GPU like actually
works at the threat uh thread level. So
this is the the Triton Gelu kernel. It
was generated by the compiler. And at
first it's going to do some of the
really basic stuff. So what's it doing
here? It's saying, well, I'm going to
need to store some values, right? I'm
going to need to store intermediate
computations. B means actually um sort
of untyped sort of basically like bytes.
So I need bytes um that are sort of
32bit size. I need floats for doing
computations called f. And I need
another set of registers uh that are 64
uh bits. And you know that's another set
of registers. Um and so I have all these
sort of registers that I need for
temporary computations. And then
starting here I'm going to start
computing um basically my coordinates.
So sorry this part is is loading um the
the various arguments to the function.
So things like um the x pointer and the
y pointer get loaded here. I starting
here I start computing um the coordinate
offsets of my Triton sort of kernel. And
then once I get down here, this LD
global, this is the code that's used to
load um the values from Xpointer back
into my temporary registers. So it's
basically saying load R2, R3, R4, R5
using um the uh the the memory position
in RD1. And notice how it's loading four
things at once because it's cleverly
handling coalesing, right? We know we
can get four values for free. we should,
you know, operate on all four of these
values at once because we get them. And
then you do the same thing um uh again
uh for um you do the same thing again
here. And then you start to get uh
basically the floating point operations
mole f32 which basically goes through
and does the tanh computations. Um I'm
not going to explain all the different
pieces, but you know here it's doing
it's multiplying by a constant. It does
a x to the cube like multiplying the
same numbers multiple times. Um, and
then it's going to compute here, you
know, 2 to the x, but we want e to the
x. And so it multiplies by log two to
get the the exponentiated base. You can
really see all of the different like
literal step-by-step operations that the
GPU does in order to get you uh the
final result. And so I'll skip all over
to the end. This is all floatingoint
computations that it needs to do. And
then at the very end it stores the
values that it has R38 through R41 um
into RD4 which is the memory position of
our output. Right? So this is kind of
like what's actually happening at the
low level. Um and we see that each
thread is operating on four values at a
time and its temporary storage is the
registers which is the really really
high-speed uh storage that it has very
locally. So we can see you know this is
going to you know just looking at it be
probably pretty fast code right. Okay.
So that was the PTX and we can you know
go through and see what it's doing for
all sorts of um things. But now let's go
back um and actually benchmark things.
So we got manual GU 8.1 seconds, PyTorch
time 1.1 seconds, CUDA time 1.84
seconds, Triton time 1.848 seconds. So
we didn't get any faster, but it was
much easier to write Triton code, right?
We wrote it in Python. We thought about
blocks. We could do vectorzed additions.
um if you're doing more sophisticated
stuff, you know, it basically Triton
will handle a lot of the the memory
stuff for you. Um and so it's actually
pretty good. And then profiling once
again, we see single kernel launch that
consumes um all of the GPU time, right?
So that's great. Um and that gets, you
know, Triton kernels. The last thing, um
at least in this sort of uh
Whoops. One second here. Okay. um that I
want to talk about is torch compile. Um
of course writing CUDA kernels is cool
and it makes you feel really good. Um
but maybe we don't need to do that,
right? Like the things that we were
doing here were very simple. We were
just taking these like you know x cubed
and like exponentiation operations and
we were just shoving them all into a
single um CUDA kernel. And so maybe we
can just do that without you know doing
much. And so, you know, we've had the
several different ways that we've showed
you, but the last one I want to talk
about is this thing called torch
compile, which will take um, you know,
uh, nonoptimized PyTorch code, and it
will write um, more optimized code. And
so here it's going to attempt to
automatically do optimizations like um,
kernel fusion. Um, and this compiled GLU
is going to be, you know, equivalent in
the actual uh, outputs that it
generates. But now let's let's look at
the run times, right? Um so we've got
some runtime variation, but basically
the same kind of numbers, right? 8.1
seconds manual, 1.1 seconds pietorch, um
1.8 seconds, and then 1.47 seconds um on
torch compile, right? So um the punch
line here is modern JIT compilers are
pretty good. It can do optimizations
like operation fusion um without you
having to do very much at all. And if
you look under the hood, um you can kind
of see that there's um basically once
again one thing that happens. This is a
a sort of fused add multiply tanh Triton
code. So it's generating Triton under
the hood um that basically is doing
similar kinds of things as our Triton
code, but it's actually slightly more
optimized um than what we did. And so
it's getting slightly better performance
than even our our code. So um torch
compile is quite nice. Yes. How do you
feel like
compiled? Like you're going to like try
to implement your price
version like it can't do flash in right.
Yeah. So so the the question was like um
when do you know that I guess maybe the
better way to phrase that question is
when do you know you can do better than
torch compile right is is sort of the
the relevant question. Um and I think
for for simple stuff like simple
operator fusion or um the other thing
that it's very good at is um optimizing
matrix multiplies. Um so torch compile
as I said before can do things like if
it knows the shape of the matrices can
figure out which kernels to dispatch. It
is very good at those things. I doubt
that you can get much better than that.
But there are things like um if you've
seen flash attention one two and three
um those are pretty non-trivial
optimizations like these days torch
compile and like um Jax's like XLA
compiler can do those but that's because
we know in hindsight that those are the
right optimizations to do. Um I think
some of those things are a little bit
non-trivial to figure out like Flash
Attention 3 has additional sort of
hardware level optimizations that
leverage you know the H100 hardware
that's not obvious to do with a JIT
compiler. Um, and so there are some
things that I think are quite hard with
with uh torch compile that I think you
could do better. But in general, like I
think the point here is, you know, you
shouldn't go home and say, um, I'm going
to CUDA kernel like I'm going to write
CUDA kernels for every single part of my
language model, you know, that's
probably not a good use of your time.
But if you're writing a new architecture
with some complicated piece and you're
not getting utilization, but you think
you can, that's maybe the time to really
bust out the Triton.
Okay, so we're we're basically at time
um but we can quickly go through one
last example of uh Triton. Maybe this
will be useful for you um in assignment
two um of doing softmax. So one
difference is until now we were doing
just basic element wise operations and
that's really easy because you just
operate on each element and there's sort
of no sort of complexity to those kinds
of things. So now let's do soft max
which is it has a reduction operation
where you have to add across all the
elements. So how do we do that? Well um
what we want to do is we want to
normalize across each row of the matrix
and you know what we would like to do is
we'd like to to make this fast. So a
naive version of this is uh going to be
pretty slow. And now we're going to
write the the Triton kernel. So if I
wanted to be lazy, the the easiest way
to do this is okay, actually you can
think for a moment about what the
easiest way to do this. Now let's say
you want to write a softmax. So you're
going to normalize each row of a matrix
and imagine these matrices are pretty
small. So you're just writing a kernel
for small matrices, right? So if you're
doing this, what's the right kind of
block design? Well, maybe what we should
do is our grid should actually just be
rows. So each SM is going to handle a
single row. That's kind of the optimal
thing to do because if we can fit a
whole row into an SM, then we just sum
across that row in the SM and then we
divide, right? That's that's great. And
so that's going to be the simple design
for for our very, you know, naive
softmax kernel here. So all we're going
to do is that we're going to make the
block size um basically uh sorry, we're
going to make each block a row. And so
the block size should be number of
columns plus, you know, a little bit of
buffer to sort of be able to fit all the
columns. So this is Triton next power of
two of n. And that's a nice way of
padding out um your columns. And then
I'm going to make each block a row. So
the number of blocks is exactly the
number of rows. And then I have um my
Triton softmax kernel which is written
in kind of the way that you expect. So
now we have a matrix rather than um a
vector. So we have x pointers, we have y
pointers, we need the strides of the
matrices. Um, and then we can basically
figure out what row index I'm in. I can
get the column offsets. This is going to
be the same kind of code as before. In
fact, getting the row offsets simpler
because each row is a block. And then
now I'm going to do basically the same
kind of stuff. I'm going to load in each
row into my sort of SM's sort of local
memory. And then I'm going to do
computation exactly in a way that looks
like a softmax. I have have my row. I
subtract my max. I take the exponent. I
sum it and then I divide which is going
to give me my softmax normalized row and
I write it back to global memory. Right?
No complexity at all. Um whenever your
your computations fit nicely in SM,
writing Triton code looks very similar
to writing just normal Python code just
with a little bit of load and store and
keeping track of where the blocks are.
Right? So life is pretty simple. Let's
go back. Um, oh wait, where were we? To
the Triton. Here we go. And then we can
kind of see how fast all of our um
different pieces of code are. So I'll
zoom out again just make sure. Okay, so
manual time takes 3.7 seconds. Um, our
compile time is 1.3 seconds for for
torch compile. Um, the PyTorch time is
is 1.5 seconds. Um, and the Triton time
is 1.9 seconds. It's a still a little
bit slow. um torch compile can actually
do better than sort of the native
PyTorch implementation um especially
when it knows about the shapes and sizes
uh of certain operations. Um so finally
we can look in the profiler the the
manual softmax is kind of a disaster
here. You see all sorts of crazy
operations happening um all over the
place. Let me let me clear this uh if we
go back up here. Okay. Yep. Um we see
all sorts of operations happening. you
know, we have x, we have max, we have
sum because we've implemented things
naively and we've got memory reads and
writes everywhere. Um, the compiled
softmax is just going to be sort of one
fused softmax operation that goes quite
fast. Um, and then we've got pytorch
softmax which is also one
CUDA CUDA kernel call and same thing
with our Triton softmax. We have our
nice Triton softmax kernel um that is a
single fused kernel um for everything.
Okay, I won't go through the PTX code
for this. I think, you know, we're we're
kind of at time and I don't want to drag
you through that low level again. Um,
but hopefully this has given you a
flavor of uh lower level GPU programming
for uh the purpose of making language
models go fast. And hopefully you'll
have fun doing assignment two. Thanks.